今天您 重新20岁
没有人脉 没有资源
您会怎么重新开始？
给年轻人的建议
我觉得就是
也还是
不难
太营养了
太干货了
太干货了*2
而且我觉得这一期播客
应该真的是能
帮到很多人
这是实话
认知决定命运
其实都是认知
黄毛 薄肌 Crypto
都是认知
今天能看到我们这个节目的听众
就非常幸福
赶紧点保存
如果你的周围人给你发这个节目
你就是要
千恩万谢
每年过年得去ta家拜年
就是说
“太感谢你发给我这个视频了”
“这改变了我的人生啊”
绝对
哈喽 孙哥
Hey, Justin
我自我介绍一下 我叫邵艾伦 Alan
Let me introduce myself. I'm Alan Shao
是一个千万粉丝口语博主
I'm a spoken-English creator with over 10 million followers
也是"薄肌理论"的创始人
and the founder of "Lean-Muscle Theory"
那很高兴今天
I'm really happy today
可以获得这个采访的机会
to have this chance to interview you
那我们就直接开始
Let's get straight into it
好 开始吧
Sure, let's start
那孙哥现在开始练薄肌了吗？
Justin, have you started training for lean muscle yet？
已经开始了 开始了一天
Yes, I started. It's been one day
计划什么时候成为薄肌版的孙哥？
ecome the lean-muscle version of
Justin？
我觉得三个月吧
I'd say three months
三个月到六个月
Three to six months
然后我们可以看一看
Then we can take a look
就是到时候的这个进展吧
and see how the progress is by then
好的 非常期待
Great, I'm really looking forward to it
孙哥现在多高、多重？
Justin, how tall are you and how much do you weigh？
体脂率大概多少？
Roughly what is your body-fat percentage？
我现在就是172吧
''m about 172
（身高）172
（height） 172cm
然后大概 75公斤左右
and around 75 kilograms
体脂大概 29吧
Body fat is about 29%
第一个问题 您现在平时一天
First question: what does a normal day
大概是怎么样去过的
look like for you now？
然后在工作之外最喜欢做什么？
And what do you enjoy most outside of work？
我讲讲就是这两天开始这个
Let me talk about the last couple of days
练习薄肌之后的人生吧
since | started training for lean muscle
跟前面可能不太一样
It's a little different from before
就是先说一下 我现在呢
Let me start with what | donow
可能就是也很简单
It's actually pretty simple
我现在就是起床之后呢我就吃
When I wake up, I basically start by
先工作吧 可能也就是先工作
working first, probably work first
然后就开始吃饭
Then I start eating
吃第一餐 然后我现在会把我
For my first meal, I now send
所有吃的餐
all the food I eat
都丢给Claude
to Claude
然后 Claude 会帮我算一下
Then Claude helps me calculate
就是今天
for the day
这一餐吃多少卡路里
how many calories are in that meal
就是其实也很简单 就是我会丢一张
It's actually simple. I send a photo
先丢一张（吃饭前）餐桌的照片
First | send a photo of the table before l eat
然后呢 吃完之后
Then after I finish eating
吃饱了我再给它丢一张
when I'm full Jsend it another photo
这个第二张照片
the second photo
然后它还会告诉我怎么吃
Then it also tells me how to eat
顺序 因为有几道菜嘛
and in what order, since there are several dishes
它会告诉我就先吃高蛋白的那种
It tells me to eat the high-protein food first
然后我就是现在也配了
And now I've also added
蛋白粉和肌酸
protein powder and creatine
蛋白粉 25克
25 grams of protein powder
肌酸5克
5 grams of creatine
然后就吃
Then leat
然后吃完之后呢 就训练
After eating, I train
如果训练日就训练一下
If it's a training day, lwork out
硬拉、深蹲
deadlifts, squats
就是主要几个动作嘛
mainly a few key movements
然后如果不是训练日就正常工作
If it's not a training day, ljust work normally
现在是训练日和非训练日
Right now l alternate training days
是刚好一天交叉一次的
and non-training days every other day
然后就工作完就吃第二餐
After work, I have my second meal
大概晚餐吧
Basically dinner
然后就 晚上就继续工作
At night I keep working
然后就睡觉了 然后睡觉呢
Then l go to sleep. And for sleep
第二天呢 就是我现在呢
the next day, now lalso
现在也就是
basically follow the idea that
“工欲善其事 必先利其器”嘛
"If you want to do a good job, sharpen your tools first"
对吧 我现在就是有
Right? So now I have
（智能戒指） 也有这个 Oura Ring
an Oura Ring, a smart ring
也有这个 Oura Ring（智能戒指）
就是抓一下这个
to track things like
睡眠的指标
seep metrics
卡路里的这个指标
and calorie metrics
然后抓一下
Then I pull the data
然后也是直接丢给 Claude Code
and send it straight to Claude Code
然后 Claude Code 就会抓一下这个卡路里
Claude Code pulls the calorie data
再抓一下饭的卡路里
and the calories from my meals
然后二者相减
Then it subtracts the two
600 卡以内 就说是燃烧脂肪
A deficit within 600 calories means I'm burning fat
（蛋白质）现在定的140吧
For protein, the target is around 140
150 克蛋白质
to 150 grams of protein
然后呢
And then
然后就增肌减脂
I build muscle while losing fat
同时增肌减脂
both at the same time
然后 Claude Code 就是跟踪
Claude Code tracks all of it
我给 Claude Code 我专门开了一个项目
I created a dedicated project in Claude Code
然后它每天会整理
Every day it organizes everything
然后给我出一个日报
and gives me a daily report
然后就今天完成怎么样
on how l did that day
然后再结合睡眠什么的
combined with sleep and other data
Oura Ring 读取的数据
including data read from Oura Ring
全部给 Claude Code
It all goes into Claude Code
然后再加上每天的拍照
plus the daily photos
然后我现在每个练每个动作呢
And now for every exercise I do
我也会
Ialso have
给旁边我的这个
my coach next tome
教练会给我拍一个视频
record a video for me
然后这个视频也发给 Claude Code
Then I send the video to Claude Code too
然后发给 Claude Code
I send it to Claude Code
Claude Code 就帮我记好了嘛
and Claude Code logs everything for me
每组 12个做三组
Twelve reps per set, three sets
然后几公斤的 对吧
and how many kilograms, right？
然后就我们不是这个
Then we use
渐进超负荷
progressive overload
对对对 然后就加一点 对吧
Right, right, and then add a little more
再加一点
add a little more again
然后 Claude Code 也可以做个日记
Claude Code can also keep a training log
每天都记
It logs it every day
然后练完之后它也算多少卡路里
After training, it calculates calories burned too
像昨天是
Like yesterday
昨天练第一天是 275 卡路里
my first workout burned 275 calories
然后它就也记录起来
and it logged that as well
推起来
It keeps the record going
然后就我大概打算 重复
Then I plan to repeat
这个情况 然后就看三个月
this routine and look at it after three months
目前就是这么一个流程吧
That's basically my current process
好我想问一下
Okay, I want to ask
你有看我的那个薄肌教程吗？
Did you watch my lean-muscle tutorial？
是有看吗？
Did you see it？
对当然有看
Yes,of course
这个理论建设花了一周
spent a week building the rtheory
理论建设就包括
That theoretical groundworkincluded
就是我刚才讲的
what I just mentioned
准备这个 Oura Ring
getting the Oura Ring ready
对对
Right, right
然后包括读了你的《薄肌圣经》
and reading your Lean-Muscle Bible
对对对
Right, right, right
先吸收到底怎么回事
First understand what it's really about
对吧 到底怎么回事
Right, what it's actually about
然后呢购买蛋白粉 肌酸
Then l bought protein powder and creatine
肌酸 对对对
Creatine, right, right, right
然后这些 因为没办法
And those things, because there's no way around it
因为蛋白粉我就确实要喝
I really do need to drink protein powder
而且我觉得就是最近
And Ithink recently
就这个理论建设
this theoretical groundwork
就是打破了我以前
broke one of my old
一个很陈旧的一个观念
and outdated assumptions
就是说 这蛋白粉这些
that protein powder and things like that
就是说 这蛋自粉这些
就是说 这蛋白粉这些
that protein powder and things like that
东西是不是科技
might be some kind of performance enhancer
会不会喝了等一下就是跟
and that taking it might end up feeling like
那个打药的那种感觉一样了
using drugs or steroids
后来我才明白
Later I realized
其实蛋白粉就跟吃蛋白一样
protein powder is basically just eating protein
对一样的
Right, exactly the same
所以呢就是我们平常的饮食
So in our normal diet
我觉得确实吃到140克
I think getting to 140 grams
150 克蛋白质还挺难的
or 150 grams of protein is actually pretty hard
所以我觉得现在这个
Sol think now
25 克的这个蛋白粉
25 grams of protein powder
是一个很好的补充 对吧
is a really good supplement, right？
我们也不是说全都是
We're not saying everything should be
就是蛋白粉 对吧
protein powder, right？
但是我觉得就确实
ButI do think
需要一部分蛋白粉
you need some protein powder
这样也可以减轻不用吃
so you don't have to eat
那么多的一个压力嘛 对吧
so much food, right？
所以您现在是不是生活中
So would you say your life now
几乎各方面都是 AI 化了？
is almost completely Al-powered？
因为听你说都没有用人去做
Because from Whe
t youre saying, people aren't really
doing it
而是让 AI 去做
Al is doing it instead
对全部 AI化
Yes, completely Al-powered
然后当然 AI 呢
And of course AI
也会先给我一个反馈
first gives me feedback
5口
它也会给我一个建议
and recommendations
就是包括我昨天就开始的
For example, with the workout | started yesterday
练的这个动作
the exercises I did
大概做了多少组
how many sets I did
然后每个地方练到什么肌肉
which muscles each exercise hit
行不行
whether it was okay or not
然后它建议是做多少
and how much it recommends I do
就是全部都
Basically everything
因为我动作是拍了这个视频的
because I recorded videos of the movements
然后全部 AI会过一遍
Al reviews all of it
当然我也有一个教练
Of course l also have a coach
盯一下
watching me
Al 盯一下
Al watches too
教练阿一下
the coach watches too
教练盯一下
这个练没练到位
whether todays workout hit the target
所有东西 行不行
whether everything was okay
进行一个整合
It integrates all that
然后 Claude Code 给我再推一个日报
Then Claude Code sends me another daily report
就全部我们现在是可视化 数据化
Now everything is visualized and data-driven
然后可总结化
and can be summarized
然后全部都搞了 MD 文档
We also turn everything into MD documents
然后呢照片也全部都保存了
All the photos are saved too
然后建在本地文件夹MD 文档
in local folders with MD documents
然后 AI也都训练好的
and the Al is already trained on it
所以它呢
Sothen
下一个AI来就直接读 MD
a new Al can just read the MD files
如果 Claude Code
If Claude Code
比如说我们要把它请出去
for example, gets replaced
换 Codex 也可以直接来
Codex can step in directly
README.md 全部都有
All the README.md files are there
然后就是直接接手
and it can take over immediately
所以大概就是这么一个理论吧
That's basically the framework
好的好的
Got it got it
非常期待看到"版本答案"
I'm realy looking forward to seeing the "optimal build"
薄肌版的孙哥
the lean-muscle version of Justin
那我们换下一个话题
Let's switch to the next topic
那如果
So if
今天您重新20岁
you were 20 again today
没有人脉 没有资源
with no connections and no resources
您会怎么重新开始？
how would you start over？
给年轻人的建议
What advice would you give young people？
对我觉得还是不难
I don't think it's that hard
就是我觉得几点吧
I'd break it down into a few points
就是 我给年轻人的建议
My advice to young people
尤其是今天了
especially today
因为我觉得每个时代还不一样
is that every era is different
每个时代还不一样
Every era is different
就是现在这个时代
And in this era
我觉得是最好的一个时代
Ithink it's the best era
所以我要是年轻人
So ifl were young
我现在要是年轻人
if lwere a young person now
当然看从多么底层爬起好吧
it depends how far from the bottom you're starting
多么底层爬起
how far from the bottom
如果是最底层
If you're at the very bottom
一天可支配收入 and your disposable income per day一
不是 一个月吧
No, per month
我们是按一个月
let's use monthly income
一个月可支配收入
if your monthly disposable income
不超过1,000人民币
is under RMB 1,000
咱们先一个个讲
let's go through this step by step
我现在
For me
因为我以前就是在北大的时候
when l was at Peking University
我就是一个月可支配
my monthly disposable
收入不超过1,000 人民币的 好吧
income was under RIB 1,000, okay？
所以我从这个讲起
So l'll start from there
如果一个月可支配
If your monthly disposable
收入不到1,000人民币的
income is under RMB 1,000
我觉得呢
Ithink
你可以先注册一个
you can first sign up for
智谱的或者 Kimi 的AI
Zhipu Al or Kimi
他们这个Z Code 什么的
Their Z Code or something like that
现在每家都有这种
Every company now has something
类似于 Claude Code 的这种东西
similar to Claude Code
当然 Claude Code 太贵了
Claude Code is expensive, of course
可能用不起对吧
so you may not be able to afford it
光一个月就要200刀对吧
It's $200 a month, right？
很多人用不起对吧
A lot of people can't afford that
就是我如果
If lonly
一个月我就拢共只能花100刀
have $100 total to spend in a month
我哪有钱用啊
how could I afford it？
但是我觉得可以装一个智谱
But I think you can install Zhipu
Kimi Code
Z Code 这些应该都是免费的
Z Code—those should all be free
也可以来撸我自己做的一个 AI
Or you can use an Al l built myself
我也做了一个就 B.AI
I built one too, B.AI
当然是结合所有的
It combines everything
对 B.AI
Right, B.Al
反正所有的 AI 网站吧
Anyway, among all the Al websites
你就找一个便宜的
just find a cheap one
你就给它装上
and set it up
然后呢也用我刚才这个理论
Then use the framework ljust described
你所有的什么东西
Put all your things
都读到一个文档里面
into one document
然后呢
Then
你也不用跟我讲说
don't tell me
"孙哥
"Justin
我连电脑都买不起
I can't even afford a computer
电脑都没有一台"
I don't even own one"
电脑没有一台 手机总有吧
No computer? You still have a phone, right？
对
Right
丢到手机里面也可以 对吧
You can put it all on your phone too, right？
都一样的
It'sthe same
然后呢就是建个文件夹
Then just create a folder
反正丢到手机里
Put it all on your phone
所有东西 首先呢
Everything. First of all
个人无论多少钱
no matter how much money you have
其实现在都可以免费
you can basically do all of this for free now
先全部Al化
First, make everything Al-powered
我们现在就我们公司
Atour companynow
包括产品线
including across our product lines
我也都是推行都全部 AI化
I'm pushing everything to become Al-powered
全部 AI整合
Full Al integration
我觉得多少钱都可以做
I think you can do this at any income level
先把你的这个整套流程全部 AI 化
First make your entire workflow Al-powered
你的意思是生活中的每一个方面
You mean every aspect of daily life？
包括他的健身 上课 日程安排等所有事情
Fitness, classes, scheduling, everything
对什么东西
Yes, everything
你就先做一个 AI 化
Make it Al-powered first
我们讲这个
We've talked about this
我以前孙学
In what l used to call Sunology
里面讲一个重要的理论
there's an important principle
也是就是先是用理论武装自己
First, arm yourself with a theory
理论武装自己那现在
Arm yourself with a theory, and now
最重要的就是 AI化
the most important thing is becoming Al-powered
就跟 不亚于
It's comparable to
我觉得就跟以前
what happened in the past
日本说先崛起就先做君主立宪 对吧
when Japan said modernization required constitutional
monarchy first, right？
这个现代化
That modernization process
对以前日本是一个封建国家嘛
Japan used to be a feudal country
它要变成一个资本主义国家
and had to become a capitalist country
先Al化
First,become Al-powered
先AI化
First, become Al-powered
这第一步
That's step one
这是无论多少钱
No matter how much money you have
我觉得可以零成本开始的
I think you can start at zero cost
因为你像我刚才讲的
Like ljust said
你只要这个
all you need to do is
你跟它直接说
tell the Al directly
你就说"我要 MD 文档"
Say， "I want an MD document"
然后这些全部都输入好
and enter everything into it
所以你就
Then you can
可以白嫖嘛对吧
use the free options, right？
今天智谱免费
Zhipu might be free today
明天 Kimi 免费
Kimi might be free tomorrow
就直接嫖
Just use whichever is free
其实不用充钱
You really don't have to pay
就如果这
If youre in a situation where
我现在可能有点钱
I personally have a bit of money now
钱不是我一个最主要的一个阻碍了
sO money isn't my main constraint anymore
我就
thenI
包给 Claude
just pay for Claude
也求个稳定对吧
for the stability, right？
但是如果
But if
你不想花钱
you don't want to spend money
因为换 API 也花点时间嘛
because switching APls takes some time too
但实际上如果你是
then if you really
一分钱都不想花
don't want to spend a single cent
那你就全部就 直接看每家的活动
just follow each company's promotions
今天吃东家
use one provider today
明天吃西家
another tomorrow
没问题的
No problem
不用花一分钱
You don't need to spend a cent
也可以全部 AI化
and you can still make everything Al-powered
然后我觉得呢
And I think
这个 AI 化之后呢
once you've done that
就是先我觉得
first, I think
如果你是零基础起步
if you're starting from zero
我觉得呢
then
就是我那天总结的
this is what | summarized the other day
我觉得三个理论
I think there are three theories
第一个就是“孙学"
The first is "Sunology"
就是理论武装自己
using theory to arm yourself
因为孙学是一个大脑相当于升级
Sunology is basically an upgrade for your brain
你操作系统总得换吧 对吧
Your operating system has to be upgraded, right？
你就跟这个操作系统要升级
It's like upgrading your operating system
就是对金钱的理解
Your understanding of money
对财富自由的理解
your understanding of financial freedom
升级
all need an upgrade
对对金钱的理解
Right your understanding of money
财富自由理解
and financial freedom
包括对万事万物的理解嘛
and your understanding of everything in life
用孙学先进行一个升级
Use Sunology to upgrade all of that first
然后呢与此同时呢
At the same time
我觉得就是
I think
薄肌可以
lean-muscle training
确实可以练一下
is definitely worth doing
为什么呢
Why？
等一下我会讲薄肌
Hll talk about lean muscle later
就是长时间段也很重要
The long-term time horizon is important too
因为薄肌还不光是为了泡妞了
Lean muscle isn't just about picking up girls anymore
我觉得保证身体健康这点很关键
I think staying healthy is crucial
特别是在 AT时代
especially in the Al era
它是无价的对
That's priceless
对身体健康如果都不能保持
If you can't even stay healthy
这个是一票否决
that's a deal-breaker
对吧一票否決
Right, a deal-breaker
因为你身体不健康
If you're unhealthy
对吧那一票否决
then that's a deal-breaker
等一下我会讲
T'll explain later
就是如果不练薄肌 肥胖
If you don't train for lean muscle and become obese
导致很多问题
it causes a lot of problems
就会严重拖慢你的这个
and seriously slows down
就是财富自由的进度
your progress toward financial freedom
然后 以及呢
And also
给你的生活带来很多麻烦
it creates a lot of problems in your life
你知道吧
You know？
所以薄肌绝对得练
So lean-muscle training is absolutely necessary
都不为了泡妞
even if it's not for picking up girls
当然泡妞也很重要
Of course, picking up girls matters too
因为连妞都不泡
Because if you never date anyone
都没有后代
you won't have descendants
是的
Exactly
我们这个 后代也要保证质量嘛 对吧
And we want the next generation to be high quality too，
right？
这我觉得很重要
I think that's important
所以泡妞也很重要
So dating matters too
但是薄肌还是为了身体健康
But lean-muscle training is still mainly for health
第二 薄肌
Second: lean muscle
第三呢
Third
就是为什么我还加了个"黄毛理论"
why did I add "Blond Hair Theory"？
我觉得也挺重要
I think it's important too
为什么"黄毛理论"很重要
Why is "Blond Hair Theory" important？
就是孙学和薄肌
Because with Sunology and lean muscle
你但凡在今天的中国
Mf you actually start applying them in China today
或者我们这个华人社会开始实施
or in the broader Chinese-speaking community
绝对会遭到很多反弹
you'll definitely face a lot of pushback
就是因为这个还毕竟是个小众理论
because it's still a niche idea
虽然是对的
even if it's right
等一下我们讲
We'll talk about that later
但是会遭到很多
But you'll face a lot of
打压以及这个
pressure and
就嘲笑 对吧
mockery, right？
会说你是“嘉豪"
People will call you a "Jiahao"
就是你有点格格不入了 对吧
like you're a bit out of place, right？
而且你如果一旦练了孙学和这个薄肌
And once you practice Sunology and lean muscle
你想你又帅 又有肌肉 还有钱
think about it: you're handsome, muscular, and rich
还有认知对
and knowledgeable too
在社会中
Insociety
认知 你绝对在社会中
with that level of knowledge
就会遭到嫉妒
people will definitely envy you
这是 100% 的了
That's 100%guaranteed
所以就是你还是需要
So you still need
“黄毛理论”武装一下自己
“Blond Hair Theory" to arm yourself
"黄毛理论“就是说别人说什么你不管 Alan：【你需要黄毛思维-哔哩哔哩】
"Blond Hair Theohy* twBans ignoring what other people say
“黄毛理论“就是说别人说什么你不管
"Blond Hair Theory" means ignoring what other people say
自己认定对的就是充分执行
and fully executing what you believe is right
所以我觉得就是
Sol think
简而言之
in short
就是孙学、薄肌、黄毛三个都具角
once you have sunology, lean musdle, and blond-halr
mindset
我觉得就可以开工了
you're ready to get started
而且我也讲了 零成本
And as | said, it costs nothing
不需要任何钱
You don't need any money
只是认知升级
It's just a cognitive upgrade
一分钱不花
It costs nothing
所以我觉得就是这三套
Sol think these three frameworks
就是为中国 现在可能
are for China today, maybe
就是我那天讲的20岁到40岁
what | was talking about the other day: ages 20 to 40
年轻男性有2亿
There are 200 million young men
女性也算上
and if you include women
年轻男女有4亿
there are 400 million young men and women
都可以使用我们的这个
who can all use our
孙学、薄肌、黄毛这个理论
Sunology, lean-muscle, and blond-hair framework
这个理论就是升级自己
This framework is about upgrading yourself
对它是认知上的升级和身体上
Yes, it's an upgrade in cognition and in your body
健康的升级和一种心态的升级
an upgrade in health and in mindset
这样你在遭到质疑的时候
So when people question you
你还是敢坚信 坚持自己的路
you still dare to believe in and stick to your own path
因为即使它不是传统道路
even if it's not the conventional path
就是你要坚信自己
You have to believe i yourself
这样才能拿到结果
That's how you get results
对坚信自己
Right, believe in yourself
我现在就是
For me now
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
就是孙学、黄毛和薄肌 对吧
Sunology, blond hair, and lean muscle, right？
三大理论
Those are the three big theories
然后当然了
And of course
总体来讲呢
overall
现在我们就是加了一个
we've now added
最核心的掌舵者
the most important person at the helm
就是 AI
which is AI
百分百相信 AI
Trust Al one hundred percent
这个大家当然前一段时间
Everyone probably knows that recently
也知道我有一个小风波
I had a small controversy
也是因为过于坚信 AI
and it came from trusting Al too much
所引发的一场风波
That's what caused it
很多人说我可能甩锅给 Claude 对吧
A lot of people said | might be blaming Claude, right？
但其实不是
But that wasn't it
只是因为我绝对百分百坚信 Claude
It's just that | trust Claude absolutely, one hundred percent
Claude 说什么我就执行
Whatever Claude tells me, l execute
就是无论有多大阻力
No matter how much resistance there is
我都执行
Istill execute
就是这种概念
That's the idea
当然 Claude 可能是一个 AI
Of course, Claude is just one AI
你不用Claude 没问题
You don't have to use Claude
你用 OpenAI 这个 Astra 对吧
You can use OpenAl's Astra, right？
Astra 现在也是最先进的了 对吧
Astra is also one of the most advanced now, right？
你用 Astra 也好
You can use Astra too
你用智谱 GLM
You can use Zhipu GLM
那我想说 当一个年轻人
So what | want to ask is, once a young person
他安装了薄肌、黄毛
has adopted lean muscle and blond-hair mindset
孙学以及应用了 AI之后、
Sunology and AI
孙学以双应用了^之后
Sunology,and Al
孙学以及应用了 Al之后
Sunology, and Al
一些执行？ 再怎么具体化地进行一
how should they actually purt all of that into practice？
再怎么具体化地进行一些执行？
how should they actually puit all of that into practice？
-些执行？ 再怎么具体化地进行-
hrow should they actually put all of that into practice？
好 我先讲一下
Okay, let me explain
就是 我觉得
Ithink
这个也不用花任何钱
this doesn't have to cost anything either
First 真然我評茶eh
K you should just start implementing this
framework
K you should
just start implementing this
framework
我相信执行下去之后
I believe once you start executing it
无论你在地球的哪个角落
no matter where you are on Earth
我现在给你讲的
what |'m telling you now
只要你通网 有手机
as long as you have internet access and a phone
你就可以执行 对吧
you can do it, right？
这个是零成本的
It costs nothing
比如说你现在
For example,right now
你现在是自由职业者
maybe youre a freelancer
是公务员
or a civil servant
无论什么
whatever you do
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
都是零成本
it can all be done at zero cost
就是安装我们刚才这个 对吧
Just install what we were talking about, right？
就听到我们这个播客
Just listen to this podcast
有手机就是立刻安装 对吧
If you have a phone, you can start immediately, right？
这个不耗任何成本 零成本
It costs nothing, zero cost
然后我建议呢
Then I suggest
就是两点
two things
m口
第一点呢
The first one
你可以把你的现状
is to take your current situation
全部
all ofit
因为那个 AI 是比较懂你的嘛
because Al already understands you fairly well
你健康数据
your health data
各种数据什么的
all kinds of other data
你呢
and then
积累一下数据
build up that data
先不用慌
Don't rush
咱们先积累个2到4个月
Let's collect it for two to four months
然后你也把你的这个
Then gather
所有的数据都收集齐
all your data together
各种各样的数据数字化
Digitize all kinds of data
然后呢 你就把它统一
and put it all in one place
包括你一个现状的分析
including an analysis of your current situation
你就丢给 AI
Then give it to AI
让它帮你
and have it
分析一下
analyze everything
甚至是去找方向
It can even help you find a direction
以及他如何去挣钱都可以
and figure out how you can make money
因为 AI更了解他
because Al understands the person better
而且 AI有更多的数据
and Al has more data
更理智
and is more rational
对就是这样
Right, that's the idea
然后呢 你呢
Then
可以问 3个 Al对吧
you can ask three Als, right？
去我们这个 B.AI 对吧
Go to our B.Al, right？
如果你觉得麻烦
If you think it's a hassle
而且不想充钱 对吧
and you don't want to top up an account
你用 B.AI
use B.Al
因为 B.AI
Because with B.AI
我们买 API嘛
we buy the APls
其实你就问一个问题
You basically just ask one question
如果你就问一个问题
If you're only asking one question
你就交一个问题的钱 对吧
you only pay for that one question, right？
你可以问3个 AI 都问一下 对吧
You can ask all three Als, right？
我们这个 B.AI 都是API 的
B.Al uses APls for all of them
所以你就把
So you just
你直接把API 换一下就可以了
switch the API and that's it
你换每个模型 直接换
For each model, you just switch
换一下API就可以了
the APl and that's all
然后你可以问一下 Claude
Then you can ask Claude
问一下 OpenAl Astra
ask OpenAI Astra
问一下比如说GLM
and ask GLM, for example
三个可以了 对吧
Three is enough, right？
就是中美大模型全都有
merican frontier
models
而且都是最顶尖的
and they're all top-tier
然后给你全拉满
You can run them all at full power
然后三个取其中即可
and just pick one of the three
对吧 给你出上中下三策
Have them give you a best, middle, and fallback option
取其中即可 是吧
and choose whichever one works, right？
首先这是第一个思路 对吧
That's the first approach
第二个思路呢
The second approach
就是 我建议的就是
my second suggestion is
第一个问 AI
First, ask AI
第二个呢
Second
戈建议的就足随时天汪
ep up with the direction of human technoloqical
keep up
progress
我建议的就是随时关注
keep up with the direction of human technological
progress
人类科技发展的动向
That's very important
很关键
Because for me
因为我的
our Sunology
咱们孙学
think about it, Sunology was established in 2016
你想孙学是2016年建立的
and it's been ten years now, right？
到现在10年了 对吧
And of course I myself
这个我自己当然也
am a practitioner of Sunology
就是孙学的践行者
In 2016|was nobody, right？
我16年什么都不是 对吧
Then I started practicing Sunology
开始践行孙学 对吧
started training for lean muscle
开始练薄肌 对吧
and maybe I had a big belly too, right？
可能也是大肚腩 对吧
Later I can take a photo
我到时候可以拍张照片
and compare it myself
一会自己
Right, put two photos side by side
对吧 这个两张照片对比一下
After six months, after a year
6个月一年
we can look at the change, right？
对吧 看一下这个变化嘛
We'll use
我们用这个
a controlled-variable method
控制之后变量法这个变化 对吧
to look at the change, right？
但是呢 比较重要就是随着科技进步
But more importantly, as technology keeps advancing
有不停的新的东西出来
new things Keep coming out
所以呢 我觉得也得有一个就是抓取
so I think you also need a way to keep track of them
当然这个抓取你也可以让 AI抓 对吧
Of course, you can have Al track them for you too, right？
当然你自己如果平常
And if you personally
因为我自己是对 AI
like me, are interested in AI
这些东西很感兴趣
and these kinds of things
所以我就是自己也抓
then I track them myself too
这个平常自己我也会关注
I follow this stuff myself in daily life
也会抓的嘛
and keep track of it
因为我看一下X
For example, 1 look at X
看一下这些 对吧
and look at things there, right？
这个 马斯克 每天在干嘛呀 对吧
What Elon Musk is doing every day, right？
我就是全部
1 basically track all of it
我就是会自己也抓一下
I keep an eye on it myselftoo
自己抓加AI抓
I track it myself and have Al track it
当然了 你也结合你兴趣
Of course, it also depends on your interests
如果你对这个东西不感兴趣
If you're not interested in this stuff
也没必要
then there's no need
你就结合你自己最感兴趣的那个
Just focus on what you're most interested in
因为你抓一下这个方向就很多了已经
because by then there are already so many possible
directions
然后你就抓一个
Then pick one
自己最感兴趣的方向
direction you're most interested in
然后你就开始
and start
也要钻研一下
studying it seriously
钻研一下
really studying it
因为毕竟你知道每个人都会
Because everyone, after all
有自己的一个擅长的领域 对吧
has an area they're good at, right？
你就不可能所有领域都是专家
You can't be an expert in every field
所以你就自己再钻一个方向
so pick one direction and go deeper
我觉得就 然后呢
I think, and then
这个决策呢
once you've made a decision
你做了 也就是用我们英文的话讲
to use an English term
就是还有个 调优 的过程 对吧
there's still a tuning process, right？
就包括这个大模型也是训练嘛
Large models are trained too
所以你就根据填补的数据不一样
so the result depends on the data you feed in
就跟每天 对吧
just like every day, right？
我有 Oura Ring
I have Oura Ring
有这些乱七八糟
and all kinds of other stuff
读数据推过来的数据
feeding data in
我们再根据这个数据的这个
Then based on that data
推的具体情况
and what it shows specifically
就是再改进
you keep improving
所以我们也 调优
So we tune as well
也不是一锤子买卖 对吧
It's not a one-and-done deal, right？
在不停地 调优
You keep tuning
这个不停地改进
and keep improving
然后最后就
And in the end
像训练模型一样
it's like training a model
就训出来了
you eventually train it into shape
所以您的意思就是
So what you're saying is
无论是从方向还是到执行
from dhoosing a direction to execution
包括其中的一些改变
indluding changes along the way
一些小调整
and small adjustments
冖些小调整
一些小调整
and small adjustments
全部借助 AI
you use Al for all of it？
对全部借助 AI
Yes, Al for all ofit
全部借助 AI
All of it through AI
然后当然也加一些自己的判断 对吧
Of course, you add some of your own judgment too, right？
就是这个 但是呢 AI为主
But Al is the main thing
我现在就是
For me now
比如说我有可能如果是开飞机的话
ifl were flying a plane, for example
90% 的时间让 AI开了
I'd let Al fly it 90% of the time
我自己呢
and Imyself
可能就 10％ 的时间
would spend maybe 10% of the time
可能就 10%的时间
週一下 AAI
adjusting the AI
调一下 AAI
调一下 JAI
adjusting the Al
我有时候也有可能不同意见
Sometimes | may disagree with it too
我也讲 比如说前两天
Like / mentioned, a couple of days ago
我和 AI
Al and|
就发生一个很简单对话
had a very simple conversation
就我刚才跟你讲的
Iike the one ljust told you about
改变我一个思维
that changed one of my ways ofithinking
这是我以前一个就是
It was something I used to have
相当于先入为主之见
a kind of preconceived notion
就比如说我觉得
For example, I used to think
蛋自粉是不是有点科技 对吧
protein powder might be some kind of PED, right？
对对对
Right,right right
然后我跟 AI我们俩交流了
Then Al and I talked about
这件事交流了
that issue
然后 Al 也给我讲说不是
and Al told me that wasn't the case
蛋白粉呢
Protein powder
就健身领域有很多科技 确实有
There are plenty of PEDs in fitness, that's true
但蛋白粉、肌酸这种是
but things like protein powder and creatine
唯一就是不算科技的
are simply not PEDs
其实就是一个普通的吃
They're just ordinary food
我一看
When I saw that
我说"明白了"
I said， "Got it"
然后它给我一讲这个原理都是啥
Then it explained the reasoning to me
然后给我这么一讲
Once it explained it like that
我一下就
I suddenly
这个理念就翻过来了
completely changed my view
就我就这样讲
So that's what I'm saying
就说你的理念可能跟 AI也会有冲突
your own views may conflict with Al too
但你们俩就是可以频繁交流嘛 对吧
but the two of you can keep talking frequently, right？
然后呢就是把这个理念也更新了
and then update your thinking as well
其实我觉得就是这么一个理论
That's basically the framework, I think
非常 很有启发
Very inspiring
所以说基本上我这边去理解的话
So basically the way l understand it
就是其实我要问的很多问题
many of the questions | wanted to ask
您这边的意见都是
your view is that
因为你不知道每个人的具体情况
because everyone's situation is different
所以你建议他一定要建立好
yourecommend first building
这个 Al、黄毛、薄肌的思维
this Al, blond-hair, and lean-muscle mindset
然后他要大量地通过AI去
Then they should use Al extensively
根据他自己的情况找到
based on their own situation
他的方向和适合他的方向
to find the direction that suits them
并且进行调整
and keep adjusting
对
Right
是的是的 是的
Yes, yes, yes
绝对是这样
Absolutely
但是呢
But
还是很具有这个参考性
is still highly useful as a reference
因为其实每个人的这个情况呢
because each person's situation
也不一定是那么复杂 对吧
isn't necessarily that complicated, right？
所以我觉得就是
Sol think
升级思想
upgrade your thinking
升级这个身体
upgrade your body
以及这个专注于个人发展
and focus on your own development
这个"黄毛理论”对吧
this "Blond Hair Theory" right？
专注于个人发展
Focus on your own development
我觉得是最关键的
I think that's the most important thing
所以我觉得就是
So I think
这三件事可以立刻去做
those three things can be done immediately
然后其他事结合大家
For everything else, take into account
自己不一样的情况
your own individual situation
我觉得就是可以问问 AI
Ithink you can just ask AI
问问 AI呢
ask AI
我前面大家也可能在网上
People may have seen online
看到我一个很有名的名言
one of my well-known sayings
我进行了一个
Imade an
但现在也进行一个升级 好吧
but now I'm upgrading it again, okay？
孙学也不断升级嘛
Sunology keeps getting upgraded too
我前面就说呢“不要跟
I used to say， "Don't chat on
微信聊天
WeChat
要跟豆包聊天 对吧"
chat with Doubao instead, right？"
跟豆包聊天
Chat with Doubao
这个是一个升级
That was an upgrade
首先你从微信聊天到去豆包聊天
First, moving from chatting on WeChat to Doubao
你是已经进行了一个升级 好吧
was already an upgrade, okay？
但现在呢
But now
我再要进行一个升级
I'm upgrading it again
用API跟全球的 AI 聊天
use an APl to talk to Als from around the world"
你就用一个 API
Right, just use an API
你就用一个
API
Right, just use an API
就是所有文件
Keep all your files
保存在本地
stored locally
然后就用一个 API 读取
then use an APl to read them
然后帮你做整体的这个
and help you build the whole thing
一个大模型的这个构造
into a large-model setup
所以这个我觉得又是一波升级
Solthink that's another upgrade
会需要一丢丢的计算机的一个常识
It does require a tiny bit of computer knowledge
但实际上也很简单
but it's actually very simple
你去网上直接问
Just go online and ask
那个 AI怎么做就行了
an Al how to do it
大家不要一听 API 感觉就是
Don't hear APl and immediately think
难度超高 就是拒之于千里之外
it's impossibly difficult and shut yourself out
就其实跟你用那个豆包
It's actually not that different
差别不大
from using Doubao
就是一丢丢的渠道的变化而已
It's just a tiny change in how you access it
对 就反正借助一个 AI
Right, just use an AI
然后不断地升级自己的认知嘛
and keep upgrading your understanding
你不会就间 AI嘛
Iyou dontt know.how, askAl
问AI怎么弄 MD 文件
Ask Al how to make an MD file
间它怎么API
ask it how to use an API
问它怎么API
只要愿意学都是能学会的
If you're wiling to leam, you can learn it
对就是
Right
其实非常简单
It's actually very simple
好的好的
Got it, got it
非常 很有启发
Very inspiring
我觉得这个对我自己的
I think this willchange
工作流都会有调整
my own workflow too
因为我觉得我还不够足够拥抱 AI
because I don't think I've embraced Al enough yet
所以我觉得对我帮助非常大
so this has been very helpful to me
那其实刚才很多想问的问题
A lot of the questions | wanted to ask earlier
其实孙哥说的这个AI 都能够帮他解决
Justin has basically said Al can help solve them
但是我还是想问一下
but I still want to ask
就是站在您的认知
from your own level of understanding
您的视角去看的话
and from your perspective
您觉得年轻人未来几年
what areas and industries do you think young people
最值得 全力投入的方向和赛道是什么？
should go all in on over the next few years？
您看好哪些？
Which ones are you most optimistic about？
好
Okay
我先讲一下
Let me start
我个人呢
Personally
其实对于未来的年轻人
I'm very optimistic
非常看好
about young people in the future
我对年轻人非常看好 原因呢
I'm very optimistic about young people, and the reason is
很简单 就是 AI 时代
simple: we're in the Al era
所有东西就都会变得很便宜了
Everything is going to become very cheap
唯一值钱的是什么呢？
What's the one thing that stays valuable？
唯一值钱的就是寿命了
Lifespan
现在我看
The way I see it now
就是寿命
it's lifespan
所以年轻就是财富
So youth itself is wealth
因为你老了
Because when you get old
现在呢还是有很多
there are still many things
这个东西是赶不上趟的
you may simply be too late for
因为这个到点了就是得下车 对吧
because at some point you have to get off the train, right？
就是这个 AI虽然进步
Al is advancing
但是还没有进步到
but it hasn't advanced to the point of
就是长生不老
making people immontal
不用死了 对吧
where you don't have to die, right？
永笙确实还没做到
We still haven't achieved immortality
永生确实还没做到
We stillhaventt achieved omortality
但是呢除此之外的所有各行各业
But aside from that, every industry
都会被 AI革命
will be transformed by AI
所以呢就是年轻人在每条赛道
So young people have opportunities
都充满了机会
in every industry
就是我讲几个吧
Let me give a few
对吧 我讲几个这个简单的例子吧
simple examples
就跟我做的行业都无关
that have nothing to do with my own industry
好吧 我做的是金融行业
I work in finance
跟金融行业无关的
so these are examples outside finance
就是被 AI革命的例子
of industries being transformed by AI
我现在都可以举好几个
I can already give several examples
而且对年轻人是具有
with huge
非常大的发展潜力的
potential for young people
第一个 比如说我就是现在
First, for example, I recently
设立的孙宇晨奖的这个数学领域
set up the Justin Sun Prize in mathematics
数学领域之前
In the past, mathematics
是很吃这个
was very dependent on
这个学习很吃这个家学的
your academic lineage and mentors
这很吃家学的
It depended heavily on that background
就比如说为什么北大
For example, why is it that Peking University
比如说你说
Or, say
大家我们经常不是以前有个疑问说
people used to often ask this question
说"北大清华
"Peking Univeraity and Tisinghua
包括中国这高中
and Chinese high-school students
IMO 拿那么多对不对
win so many IMO medals, right？
为什么就是这个菲尔茲奖
So why are there so few Fields Medals
或者是这种顶尖的数学奖拿得少"
or other top mathematics prizes？"
这个可能未来说孙宇晨奖
Maybe in the tuture people wil ask the same about the
Justin Sun Prize
对吧 为什么得主那么少 对吧
Why are there so few winners, right？
其实最简单的一个问题
The simplest answer
我跟你讲一个很简单
I'l tell you something very simple
你一下子恍然大悟了
and it suddenly becomes obvious
最根本的问题就是数学
The most fundamental issue is that in mathematics
解很多东西是需要思路的
solving many problems requires the right ideas
所以呢
So
这个你跟的导师
which advisor you work with matters
如果你跟的哈佛的MIT 的
If you're working with people at Harvard or MIT
你跟的那个巴黎这个学院的.
or with those schools in Paris
那些人的这个思路就上去了
you get access to their way of thinking
你在北大再聪明没用
You can be brilliant at Peking University and it still may not
help
因为你的老师
because your professor
不知道这题怎么解
may not know how to solve that problem
是不是？
Right？
这个很关键
That's crucial
你没到那个圈子
If you're not in that circle
你不知道这个路
you don't know the path
但现在 AI"乱拳打死老师傅"
But now Al can "beat the old master with brute force"
对吧 什么 NS 方程
Take the NS equations, for example
我啪我就给你解 为啥呢
Al can just solve it for you. Why？
因为人家首先靠
Because first
这个抓的这个方法
through its retrieval methods
把全世界的所有的思路
it has already collected ideas from around the world
都已经抓到模型里了
into the model
然后呢
Then
其实 AI 本身也不创造任何东西 对吧
Al itself doesn't create something from nothing, right？
Al 也没有办法平地起高楼
Al can't build a tower out of thin air either
就像我现在问AI"如何
For example, if l ask AI，“How do we
做出可控核聚变？”
achieve controlled nuclear fusion？"
那 AI 也不知道
Al doesn't know either
“因为你们人类没做出来
“Because you humans haven't done it yet
你干问我
why are you asking me？
我也不知道"
I don't know either"
但是
But
就比如说我们人类通向可控核聚变
for something like the path toward controlled nuclear
fusion
其实是有几个思路的
there are actually several existing approaches
以前有这些人提出来
that people have proposed before
那好AI是有能力把这些所有思路
Then Al is capable of taking all those ideas
都帮你抓出来
and pulling them together for you
然后进行分析
then analyzing them
然后往前探路的
and exploring further along those paths
所以呢就是数学这个领域
So in mathematics
就我为什么现在设立这个孙宇晨奖
the reason l established the Justin Sun Prize
就是说设的那些题目
is that for the problems we set
你就直接解就可以了
you can just go solve them directly
是什么呢
What does that mean？
你现在大量的数学研究生
A large number of mathematics graduate students today
你比如说在北大的
for example, someone at Peking University
或者你哪怕是个高中生
or even a high-school student
你都能根据 AI提供的思路
can use the ideas provided by AI
Astra、Claude Code 提供的思路
ideas provided by Astra and Claude Code
直接一步到位
and get there in one step
到数学博士的这个水平
up to the level of a math PhD
数学博士的水平
the level of a math PhD
那个导师给他说
his advisor tells him
他也才知道
and only then does he find out
你是高中生也可以知道
but even as a high school student, you could know it
只要你就是懂他在说什么
as long as you understand what it's saying
就每个方向还不一样嘛
every field is different, of course
你自己可能有一个自己喜欢的方向
you may have a field you personally like
你直接就可以一步到位
and you can jump straight to that level
其实数学领域经常出天才的 很多
math actually produces a lot of young geniuses
你像这个陶哲轩
take Terence Tao, for example
这些出道都是 20多岁
people like that were already making their mark in their
twenties
十几岑出头就是解出非常难的题月
even in their teens, they were solving extremely hard
problems
所以数学并不是夸张
so this isn't an exaggeration in mathematics
就是说我现在“大跃进"好像讲的
it's not like /'m talking about some Great Leap Forward
四十岁才能出的成就
taking achievements that used to require people in their
thirties or forties
说让你二十岁
and saying you should do them at twenty
十几岁做
or in yourteens
这个爱因斯坦你知道做出
Einstein, for example, youknow
相对论来都是很年轻的时候做的
developed relativity when he was very young
所以就是有AI之后
so once you have AI
现在就是我觉得对年轻人
I think young people today
学术界年轻人
young people in academia
比如数学领域
in a field like mathematics
我觉得就彻底解放了
are basically completely liberated
你就基本上
you basically
你根本不用管
don't need to care about
几年级什么升博士
what year you're supposed to enter a PhD
几年级升硕士
what year you're supposed to enter a master's
几年级升本科
or what year you're supposed to enter college
你高中你其实就可以开干了
you can basically start working on it in high school
就是
basically
对吧就像我们经常讲的IMO 的那些人
right? Like the IMO kids we always talk about
原来就是被耽误了
they used to get held back
现在你就有 AI
now you have Al
你直接接轨
you can connect directly
你和 AI两个人可能两天就
you and Al together might, in two days
干出一个世界级成果
produce a world-class result
完全有可能对吧就像
that's entirely possible, right? Like
就像那个
like that
就是前两天不是有这个
there was that thing a couple of days ago
纠纷的这个 OpenAI 的这个事
the controversy involving OpenAI
就是你知道
you know
我给大家简单讲一下什么事
let me briefly explain what happened
就是说这个
basically
有一个数学家
there was a mathematician
纽约大学的
at New York University
他已经在攻克这个 NS 方程了
who was working on the Navier-Stokes equations
就是最难的这个 NS 方程
one of the hardest problems, the Navier-Stokes equations
结果呢他就把他的思路
and then he shared his line of thinking
就大致讲给 OpenAI 听了
roughly, with OpenAI
然后 OpenAI 当然听完之后
and after OpenAl heard it
OpenAI 现在相当于有点
OpenAl was sort of
可能大模型训练吧
maybe training its large model
是尤其这种最前沿的知识
especially on cutting-edge knowledge like this
它是有点
it's kind of
就它一旦学会了就内化了
once it learns something, it internalizes it
它就推给
then it pushes it to
因为 OpenAI 自己肯定有监控的
because OpenAl must have internal monitoring
就把他的想法给偷了
so it stole his idea
故意监控
through its monitoring
他其实不是故意要偷这个
it wasn't actually trying to steal
纽约大学这个教授的想法
this NYU professor's idea
我相信 OpenAI 内部是有智能体
I believe OpenAl has agents internally
相当于每天都在问 OpenAI
basically asking OpenAl every day
就是你对于攻破比如说数学
when it comes to solving, say, mathematics
千禧年这 10 个最难的题目
the ten hardest Millennium-type problems
你这个思路每天
whether your approach, day by day
你有没有进化
has made any progress
因为现在每天不是 OpenAI 都
because every day OpenAl is
吸取大量人类的这个知识嘛对不对
absorbing a huge amount of human knowledge, right？
所以你每天肯定有更新
so of course it gets updated every day
所以它就搞了智能体
so they probably have an agent doing this
结果就碰巧这个纽约大学
and it just happened that this NYU
教授这个提供了个新的思路
professor contributed a new idea
OpenAI 回来自己就去进化 说"喂
then OpenAl came back and evolved on it, saying， "Hey
我有个新方向
I've got a new direction
从这个方向可以攻破"
this direction might crack it
OpenAI一看说“这个东西有新思路
OpenAl looked at it and said， "There's a new idea here
而且很有可能"
and it looks very promising"
那个 AI 前面有可能判断
the Al may have judged beforehand
它说很有可能
that it was highly promising
所以就 OpenAI 就是调集
sO OpenAl mobilized
700 万美金的这个算力
about seven million dollars' worth of compute
几千个智能体
and thousands of agents
连夜就给他把这个思路就做出来了
and worked through the idea overnight
所以就两天就给攻破了
so it Gracked it in two days
但其实当然纽约大学这个
of course, the NYU
教授的这个思路很关键
professor's idea was crucial
他要不提供 OpenAI也不知道
without his input, OpenAl wouldn't have known
但他一提供 OpenAI
but once he gave OpenAl the idea
两天就做出来
it finished it in two days
对吧就
right？
所以现在这个数学领域你想根
so just think about mathematics today
就是这么一个你追我赶
it's become this kind of back-and-forth
的这么一个局面
race to catch up with each other
所以就是年轻人现在进入数学领域
so for young people entering mathematics now
太牛了
it's incredible
你要是懂 AI
if you understand AI
相当于你分分钟15 岁的一个年轻人
，in no time
a 15-year-old kid could，
你把你那个50岁老教授
take on some 50-year-old
分分钟"乱拳打死"
professor and beat him with brute-force creativity
就这么简单
it's really that simple
所以就是
SO
比如说这个 AI
that's one example with AI
这是一个 AI 的例子
an Al example
就数学的例子
a mathematics example
数学例子
a math example
比如说现在其他多的
now there are lots of other fields
比如说现在多的这个生物学
biology, for example
这个包括我还问了
and l also asked
我自己都问了这 AI
lasked Al myself
我说"现在就是哪几个领域
I said， "Which fields right now
可能会取得决定性突破？”
are most likely to achieve decisive breakthroughs？"
还有一个我就是都是讲
another one I'm talking about
我就我自己研究的平常
is something I look into myself
Al 告诉我
Al told me
“天文学会有本质性的进步"
“Astronomy could make fundamental progress"
因为是什么呢
why？
哈勃望远镜那些
telescopes like Hubble
读了很多数据回来
have brought back huge amounts of data
但是呢就是都是大量的
but it's all massive volumes
就是数据但是呢
of data
没有去处理
that haven't been processed
极其枯燥
it's extremely tedious
没有人有时间处理
no one has enough time to process it
现在你要是加一个这个 AI
now if you add AI
在那狂搞
and let it go at it
天文学分分钟取得决定性突破
astronomy could make decisive breakthroughs very quickly
那假设这个年轻人他对
but suppose a young person
学术方面的东西没有那么感兴趣
isn't that interested in academic work
他就是想尽快地实现财富自由的话
and just wants to achieve financial freedom as quickly as
possible
你会建议什么方向
what direction would you recommend？
我觉得也是 AI
I'd still say AI
你就分析嘛对吧
analyze it, right？
你就分析这个太多
there are so many things you can analyze
我跟你讲太多可以挣钱道路了
I'm telling you, there are so many ways to make money
我随便给大家举一个例子吧
let me just give everyone one example
当然都是合法的对吧
all legal, of course
在合法的这个环境下使用
used within a legal framework
举个例子
here's one example
现在这个 AI 领域的这个 API
pricing for APIs in the Al industry
价格其实都不是统一的
isn't uniform
你同样一个用户
for the same user
你在这个
if you subscribe in
阿根廷包月和土耳其包月
Argentina or Turkey
尼日利亚包月
or Nigeria
那是最便宜的
it's much, much cheaper
对吧你要在美国包月的是最少的
whereas if you subscribe in the U.S.
那价格是最高的
the price is the highest
所以做"Token 中转站"
so you can build a "Token relay service"
对
exactly
我当时自己做的一个
that's something I did myself
就 Token 中转站
basically a token relay service
类似这样的 对吧
something along those lines, right？
就是我
basically
当然我觉得这个想法
I think this idea
其实是个很好的思路
is actually a very good one
就这个想法这个思路呢
this idea, this line of thinking
就是我觉得就是大家呢
Ithink everyone should
当然这也是我自己慢慢跟 AI
this is also something I gradually developed with AI
对吧我们俩训练就形成的这种思路
through the two of us training together, so to speak
就是商机
business opportunities
是全球发现
should be discovered globally
千万不要局限于
never limit yourself
就是说"我在我们家门口
to thinking, say， "rIl
开个小卖部
open a little shop downstairs
挣楼底下老奶奶这个钱"
and make money from the old lady in my building"
这个思路
that kind of thinking
那就太小了
is too small
太小了
far too small
就是商机一定要全球性发现
opportunities have to be discovered globally
全球性发现
globally
然后呢
and then
当然结合一下自己的
of course, combine that with your own
长处以及自己的兴趣对吧
strengths and interests, right？
通过全球性发现的
use that global perspective
来发现这个全球性的商机
to find global business opportunities
所以做全球性的生意
and do globa business
对做全球性的生意
right, do global business
就是说你把这个一个尼日利亚人
meaning, take a Nigerian
一个土耳其人
a Turkish person
一个阿根廷人也
or an Argentinian
可以想象为你的客户
and imagine them as your customers too
对吧就是人都是很简单的
people are actually pretty similar
都需求都是差不多的
their needs are broadly similar
所以呢不要受语言
so don't let language limit you
尤其现在还有 AI
especially now that we have AI
你不要受我说"
don't get stuck thinking，"
我如果要去做阿根廷
if l want to do business in Argentina
我不会讲西班牙语怎么办'
what if l don't speak Spanish？"
你可以学呀
you can learn
而且现在这个语言
and now with language
这个 AI就可以帮你搞定对吧
Al can help you handle it, right？
当然你也可以学一些语言
of course, you can also learn some languages yourself
对吧最基本嘛对不对
at least the basics, right？
这个你也可以基本学一下
you can learn the basics
但是我觉得就是你千万不要受限
but I really think you must not limit yourself
去全球赚钱
go make money globally
那您可不可以就是
could you maybe
具体的再多指几个
give a few more concrete examples？
除了这个Token 中转站
besides this token relay service
我觉得是一个很好的想法
which I think is a very good idea
就是可不可以稍微再具体化一点
could you make it a little more specific？
比如说一个年轻人他
say a young person
就是想知道您的看法
just wants to know your view
这样顺着您的思想去想一些别的
so they can follow your way of thinking and come up with
other
方向
directions
对首先我觉得就是商机
first, I think with business opportunities
如果我们是商业
if we're talking business
这个我老本行了 对吧
this is my old line of work, right？
比学术其我还懂得多
l actually know more about this than academia
对
right
商业首先最基本的我觉得呢
the most basic thing in business, I think
就是你要看你有没有创造价值
is whether you're creating value
这个创造价值这个东西
creating value
就是很关键
is really the key
就比方说
for example
还是以先以我们刚前面
let's go back to
这个 Token 中转站这个主意吧
that token relay idea
我们先聊起
and start there
就比如说我在一个地方
say I'm in a place
如果这个 Token不一样
where tokens are cheaper
不管是什么原因
for whatever reason
它可能是因为 OpenAI 的政策呀对吧
maybe because of OpenAl's policies, right？
可能是因为各式各样的原因呐
maybe because of all kinds of reasons
反正它那个地方就便宜
whatever the reason, they re cheap there
然后呢
and then
别的地方就贵
expensive somewhere else
那如果你能让贵的地方人
if you can let people in the expensive place
用上便宜的
access the cheaper option
那你不就体现出你的价值了吗
haven't you created value？
对不对
right？
这是一个最简单的一个
that's the simplest example
当然我觉得就是我的这个思路呢
one thing I think is relatively advanced about my thinking
觉得比较有先进性的
is this：
就是第一度量衡要变
first, your unit of measurement has to change
你千万不能是
you absolutely cannot
只考虑本国
only think about your own country
或者只是只考虑我们本地区
or only your own region
甚至我们本市的一个情况
or even just your own city
你得全球看
you have to look globally
同意
agreed
全球看
look globally
对
right
然后呢
and then
与此同时呢
at the same time
全球范围内
on a global scale
你觉得能不能提升出我的价值
can l demonstrate my value？
对吧能不能把我的价值
can l make my value
体现在我的客户面前
visible to my customers？
我无论做什么
whatever I do
无论做什么
whatever itis
就是你说我能不能把我的
the question is whether I can make my
价值体现在我的客户面前
value visible to my customers
其实在今天的中国
in China today
就是机会遍地都是讲白了
opportunities are everywhere, honestly
我们这个中国是世界级工厂
China is a world-class factory
其实
actually
有一个就是我自己
there's one thing: 1 personally
当然不是做这种传统行业的
don't work in traditional industries
但你就哪怕做传统行业
but even if you do
机会非常多
there are tons of opportunities
因为中国世界工厂
because China is the world's factory
中国产能过剩
China has excess capacity
中国的产能
China's production capacity
嫁接到全世界
can be connected to the entire world
都是赚钱的实际上
and that's money-making, in practice
你只要能把这个东西卖到全世界
as long as you can sell the product worldwide
当然中国我们不就是这么崛起的嘛
isn't that basically how China rose？
其实对吧
right？
帮全世界生产东西
producing things for the whole world
这个就是这么崛起的
that's how the rise happened
就是东西卖到全世界
sell products to the whole world
主意想法卖到全世界
sell ideas and solutions to the whole world
所有东西
everything
你把全世界的人当做你的客户
treat everyone in the world as your customer
只要你能怎么样
as long as you can
体现出你的价值
demonstrate your value
你根本就不用怕愁卖
you don't have to worry about whether it will sell
实话实说
honestly
这个是我就是这么多年吧
this is something I've believed for many years
我觉得一个最重要的一个思想
one of the most important ideas
就是我们
is that we
就这也是为什么
and this is also why
就是我们其实这个节目
our show
当然是个华语的节目是吧
even though it's a Chinese-language show
面向全中国年轻人对吧
aimed at young people across China
4 亿中国年轻人
roughly 400 million young Chinese people
但是呢我觉得我们是
I think
这个节目是希望
the purpose of this show
就是这个4亿年轻人走向世界用的
is to help those 400 million young people go global
我们绝对不是说内卷
we're definitely not talking about internal competition
说这个4 亿年轻人这个想法
where the ideas of those 400 million young people
就是在这4 亿年轻人中消费
are only consumed among those same 400 million people
那自己卷自己没有任何意义
competing only with ourselves is meaningless
去赚外国人的钱
go eam money from overseas customers
赚全球的钱
go earn money from overseas customers
4 亿年轻人呢
those 400 million young people
被 AI 武装 对吧
armed with Al, right？
被我们这个
and armed with
黄毛、薄肌、孙学这个理论武装之后呢
this blond-hair, lean-muscle, Sunology framework
去为全世界的80亿人服务
can serve the world's eight billion people
80亿人未来很快还有20亿 AI呢
and soon maybe another two billion Als
为这20亿 AI 也服务上对吧
serve those two billion Als too, right？
就全世界的这个100亿的
so globally, about ten billion
人和 Al 都需要服务
people and Als need services
我们4 亿人去服务他们
and our 400 million people can serve them
那你想一
think about that
你就不用内卷了
then you don't have to get trapped in internal competition
这个不是卷得很厉害对吧
you're no longer competing in such a narrow pool, right？
因为 80亿人总有空隙对吧
because among eight billion people there are always gaps
这个也其次呢
and secondly
总有机会
there are always opportunities
你今天做这个行业不行
if one industry doesn't work today
明天可以换别的行业对吧
you can switch to another tomorrow, right？
这个总有机会
there are always opportunities
因为他这个需求池足够大
because the demand pool is big enough
这个跳出
you have to break out
一定要跳出你的这个境遇
you have to break out of your current circumstances
因为这个AI 时代
because in the Al era
它所有东西都给你路都打开了
all these paths have opened up
所以有时候呢
so sometimes
也不要我建议
my advice is, don't
还有一点
here's another point
对确实也比较关键
and it's actually pretty important
我不建议年轻人呢
I don't recommend that young people
太早就根据自己的思路去下个判断
make judgments too early based only on their own ideas
"我想做什么"
"What do l want to do？"
你我建议
my advice is
可以多学多听多看
learn more, listen more, and look around more
就是这个呢
that's theidea
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
我还有一个
I have another
举个例子
example
虽然我说这个30岁之前.
even though I say that before 30
不买房不买车
you shouldn't buy a house or a car
不结婚对
or get married, right
我不是
1mean
不结婚有个这个理论好吧
there's a theory about not getting married
但是呢就是比如说咱们这个节目
but let's use our show as an example
我现在说
what I'm saying now
理论都一模一样好吧
follows exactly the same theory
听我们这个节目
people who listen to our show
这个受益良多
can benefit a lot
我现在问你一个问题
let me ask you a question
比如说主播你也可以
as the host, you can
给我讲讲你的想法
tell me your view
如果我们要买房要结婚
if we do want to buy a house and get married
要买车我们怎么做
and buy a car, what should we do？
要怎么做
how should we do it？
就一定要去做
if we definitely want to do it
那我们怎么做
then how？
就是那尽量找可以升值的房
try to find a house that can appreciate
然后保值的车
a car that holds its value
以及尽量找到一个对的伴侣
and ideally the right partner
这样可以维持这个婚姻不要被
so the marriage can last and avoid
就是像您说的离婚
what you mentioned, divorce
之后就财产分一半
where half the assets get split
这样就变成了一个公司倒闭的情况
and it becomes Iike a company going bankrupt
对
right
好我讲一下我的理论
Okay, let me explain my theory
比如说房
take housing
你要想买房了
if you want to buy a house
你做这个决定前
before you make the decision
你先看100套房
first look at 100 homes
你别买你就看
don't buy. just look
对对
right,right
不要做决定
don't make a decision
看100套房
look at 100 homes
这个最关键
that's the key
先别做决定
don't decide yet
你看 100 套房
look at 100 homes
对吧你要买车
if you're buying a car
你先看100辆车
first look at 100 cars
对吧这个房也是一手的二手的
for homes, look at both new and used
什么都看
look at everything
地段各种的你就看
locations, all kinds of things, just look
别急着买看
don't rush to buy, just look
就是我们叫“读书百遍 其义自现"
"Read a book a hundred times and its meaning becomes
clear"
你就看100套房
look at 100 homes
你啥都懂了对吧
and you"ll understand everything, right？
包括别人怎么跟你要价
including how people quote prices to you
这个多少钱
what something costs
大概值多少钱什么的
roughly what it's worth
你就基本有一个形成自己这个理论
you'll basically form your own framework
思路了
your own way of thinking
对
right
所以呢这个
SO
这个数学中
in mathematics
也有一个这个理论
there's a theory like this too
就说呢就是比如说举个例子吧
let me give an example
就是你要买
say you have
你要买一套房
you want to buy one house
一共有 10 套房
and there are 10 houses
10 套房的这个看10套房的机会
you have the chance to inspect all 10
说是你看第几套房做决定
at which house should you decide？
比如说
for example
你看第一套房你就买了
if you buy the first house
那不是后面还有9套你都没看的嘛
there are still nine you haven't seen
对不对
right？
尽量看完
ideally you'd like to see them all
然后呢你
but then
然后如果但是你第10套买
if you wait until the tenth house
你第 10 套前面看过的不许买
you can't go back and buy any of the first nine
所以呢你看到第 10套的时候
so by the time you reach the tenth
是不是你也来不及了对吧
it's already too late, right？
你后悔也来不及了
even if you regret it, it's too late
你说"前面有套房子 好的
you may say， "There was a great house earlier
来不及买"
but now it's too late to buy it"
对
right
我这只是给这个假定条件
this is just a hypothetical setup
数学上是看到第几套房买
mathematically, which house should you buy？
首先是前三套房绝对不要买
first, absolutely don't buy any of the first three
因为前三套房是帮你建立这个基准
the first three help you build a benchmark
第四套到第六套房
from the fourth to the sixth
一旦出现比前面三套房都要好的房
if one appears that's better than all of the first three
你就要立刻买
you should buy immediately
就要立刻买
immediately
当然它为什么到第六套
why around the sixth？
它是有一个黄金分割线 0.618
because there's a 0.618 golden-ratio threshold
它还有一个这个概率
and there's also a probability argument
就是说概率
a probability calculation
就是说到6的时候是最关键的
around the sixth is the critical point
因为它是一个最成熟的
because that's the most mature point
如果你到第六套的是最好
if the sixth one is the best
那是最
that's the
最好的情况
best-case scenario
所以呢
that's the scenario, so
就是我觉得就是这么一套理论
that's basically the theory
所以对年轻人择业也是一样
and the same applies to career choices for young people
我建议就是
my advice is
比如说你是大学生
say you're a college student
我不知道该从事哪个行业
and you don't know which industry to enter
现在有AI了
now you have AI
你可以一夜变身张雪峰
you can turn into Zhang Xuefeng overnight
你就中国
in China
你可以先看 100个专业的就业
you can first look at the employment outlook for 100
majors
通过 AI 看吗
using AI？
未来 10年
for the next ten years
通过AI看
yes, use Al
就一个一个问
ask them one by one
个 个问
one by one
一个个问
ask every single one
而且推导未来10年
and project out the next ten years
你看你觉得有没有意思
isn't that interesting？
不是当时我记得这个张雪峰其实
I remember Zhang Xuefeng
还推荐过有些职业也不错
also recommended some pretty good career paths
其实比如说你可以去考
for example, you could apply to
比如说同样的高考分数线
with the same college entrance exam score
就是你不一定要考清华北大
you don't necessarily have to choose Tsinghua or Peking
University
因为清华北大是这种竞争特别高的
because competition there is extremely intense
对吧
right？
你同样分数你第一名
with the same score, if you're at the top
你可以考个什么中国海关学院
you could apply to something like China Customs College
什么福建海关学院
or Fujian Customs College
你听上好像就是很差
it sounds like it might be much less prestigious
但实际上那个毕业出来就进海关
but graduates can go straight into customs
那个前途是最好的
and the career prospects can be excellent
张雪峰有很多类似理论
Zhang Xuefeng has a lot of theories like that
就这种小众专业其实
these niche majors
这些现在也全部可以覆盖
can all be covered now
所以你就是
SO
我觉得就先不急着下决定
don't rush to make a decision
你可以先看它 100个专业对不对
first look at 100 majors, right？
就有时候我们这个人呐
sometimes people
很多做决定最大以前的一个
make bad decisions mainly because
问题就是受限于信息太少
they're limited by too little information
对吧其实你这个决定也无所谓对错
the decision itself may not even be right or wrong
但你不知道吧对吧
you just don't know enough, right？
就现在我们就先把信息打开
now we can open up the information first
先把地图打开
reveal the whole map
跟我们玩
like when we play games
大家至少我们老的也玩过红警、星际
people my age at least played Red Alert and StarCraft
“开图”把全图打开
"reveal the map" — open the whole map
对
right
“开图”这样就知道怎么玩
once you "reveal the map" you know how to play
开图对吧
reveal the map, right？
我们这个玩游戏里边
in games
一个最基本的一个理论
one of the most basic principles
"开图”"开图"
"reveal the map" "reveal the map"
可以开挂开挂就是开图
you can even "cheat"— and the cheat is revealing the map
所以有了 AI类似于"开挂"
sO having Al is basically like "using a cheat code"
你就有了更多的信息
you have more information
有了信息之后就不需要做决定
once you have information, you don't need to guess
因为你有足够的信息
because you have enough information
你做决定是在
you only need to make blind decisions
没有信息的情況下
when you don't have information
你可以有了信息之后
once you have the information
你就知道该选什么
you know what to choose
你说太对了
exactly
我再给举大家举个例子
let me give everyone another example
玩游戏的人都懂
gamers will understand
是什么呢
what dol mean？
好多人以前我们玩红警玩星际
back when we played Red Alert or StarCraft
以前我们的都同宿舍大家一起玩
everyone in the dorm would play together
有很多人很喜欢闭门造车
some people loved to turtle up
就他自己就在那
they'd just stay at home
一直种田就一直发展
keep farming and developing
你知道就生产兵就去打别人
produce troops and then go attack others
这种其实就是一种稍微笨一点的做法
that's a slightly less intelligent way to play
聪明一点的做法是什么呢
what's the smarter way？
先造一些斥候
first build some scouts
先探图对吧把那个图都探了
scout the map, reveal the whole map
哪里有资源
where are the resources？
哪里有黄金
where is the gold？
哪里有对方的兵
where are the enemy troops？
然后对方的兵他主造什么
what units is the opponent mainly building？
你全部都心里都门清了
you know all of it clearly
然后呢你针对性的造对吧
then you build specifically to counter them
针对性的踩对吧
counter them directly
他如果比如说造这个战象
if they're building war elephants, for example
你就单造长矛兵不就完了吗
you just mass spearmen
对吧一会战争一打
when the battle starts
你的长矛兵打他战象都乘 5 倍伤害
your spearmen do five times the damage to their elephants
一下子战象就给你干死了对吧
and the elephants get wiped out immediately, right？
就这么简单一个道理
it's that simple
就是我觉得的
that's what I mean
不要急着就是造兵
don't rush to build troops
急着造
don't rush
咱们也可以先造几个斥候
build a few scouts first
把这个图探
explore the map
更何况现在探图都是免费的对吧
especially now, scouting is free
我坚信大家就先把图探了
I firmly believe everyone should scout the map first
比什么都强对吧
it's better than almost anything else
就是这个探完图再做决定
make your decision after you've scouted the map
就是这个玩游戏也是这么玩嘛
that's how you play games too
了解了解
got it, gotit
厞常有启发性
very insightful
非常有启发性
就是说类似于
so basically
就是用游戏理解的话
in gaming terms
就是你前期投资一点点钱
you invest a little money upfront
让这个农民去探图
to send a worker out scouting
相当于这个钱就是投在AI 上面
and that money is like what you spend on AI
然后有了这个图之后
once you have themap
你就能够更好地制定战略
you can formulate a much better strategy
对而且还不光是农民了
right, and it doesn't even have to be a worker
你可以先用斥候去探图
you can send a scout
他有一些那个马的那个兵
there are cavalry-type units
移动速度特别快
that move very fast
攻击力很弱的
with weak attack
但是就是可以探图用的对吧 你就先
but they're specifically useful for scouting
用它把整个地图探一遍
use them to explore the entire map
然后把资源该标注的全标注了 对吧
and mark all the resources, right？
这个很关键
that's very important
就是再做决定
then make the decision
再做决定不迟 对吧
it's not too late to decide afterward
我见过有的人
I've seen people
我就玩这个游戏
when I play these games
永不探图
who never scout
就是在家里闷头造兵
they just stay home and mass troops
你知道闷头造兵
you know, just mass troops
然后就是闷头造兵再打
then keep massing troops and fight
他都是很后期的才去探
they only scout very late
开图才去看
only then do they open the map
那资源早都被别人挖光了 对吧 就是
by then all the resources have already been mined by
others
胜率就不高了
so their win rate is low
对
right
所以就是探图很关键
that's why scouting is critical
其实包括打王者荣耀
even in Honor of Kings
大家可能也都对吧
everyone probably knows this
就是其实去看
you need vision
插眼要有信息
you need information from your wards
对
right
对插眼然后呢
yes, warding, and then
包括对方什么时候打这个龙
when is the opponent taking the dragon？
对吧 对方什么时候这个
right, and what's happening
野区打的野的情况怎么样
in the enemy jungle？
你们这边肯定得
someone on your side
有人是负责这个东西的
has to be responsible for tracking this
如果没有负责
if nobody is
大家没有这个信息
and the team doesn't have that information
就是很容易输
it's very easy to lose
了解了解
got it got it
所以我觉得这个探路很关键
sO l think scouting is crucial
好对
okay, right
那当然了
of course
就是应该全力去拥抱 AI
we should absolutely embrace AI
但是很多时候就 AI 的信息很多
but Al gives you a lot of information
有的时候还是会选择性
and sometimes people still selectively
更想去相信一个人
want to trust a particular person more
这个人的可信度它也非常值钱
that person's credibility is valuable too
这也是为什么我非常想要您
that's why I really want you
就比如说可不可以
for example,could you
就是也不用解释为什么
without even explaining why
就指5条方向和赛道
just name five directions or sectors
也不用解释
no explanation needed
就给年轻人指5 条方向赛道
just give young people five directions
看好的大趋势
five major trends you like
五条
five
好五条
okayfive
前面其实
eanlier
我也就随便说些
I was just speaking casually
说一说
saying a few things
这个当然也是有理论的
of course there is a theory behind it
我这个得出来原因也是有原理的
there is reasoning behind how l got there
对吧
right
但如果只是要说
but if you just want me to name them
我觉得
I'd say math
也不是数学吧 就学术界
well, not just math - academia
首先先讲
first let's talk about
学术界
academia
不同的领域
different fields
学术界呢
in academia
我觉得只要是依靠数据
I think anything that relies on data
推导
for inference
都很有机会
has a lot of opportunity
就纯数字不用说了对吧
pure mathematics goes without saying
然后天文学
then astronomy
刚才我讲的数据已经很多了
as l said, there 's already a huge amount of data
就是现在是没人处理
and right now no one is processing it
没人处理
no one is processing it
包括生物 生物也是
biology too
那大量的数据
there are massive amounts of data
没有人做
that no one is working through
而且生物一下这个制药
and biology leads directly into pharmaceuticals
这都不开玩笑的
this is serious business
这一出来这个一个药
once a drug comes out
就是这个"大炮一响 黄金万两"
as the saying goes， "When the cannon fires, gold pours in"
如果你要实验通过了
and passes the experiments
这个生物我也是很高度看好
I'm extremely bullish on biology too
生物这包括我自己可能都会
even I may personally
就是现在去研究一些生物
start researching some biology
生物相关的
biology-related areas
AI 和生物相关的
areas combining Al and biology
就是这个三条吧
that's three areas
但是其他你大家可以类比一下 对吧
but you can extrapolate to others
就只要是有大量数据
as long as there's a large amount of data
实验数据也好
experimental data
观测数据也好
observationaldata
这个理论数据也好
theoretical data
这个
any kind of data
交由 AI处理的
that can be handed to Al for processing
我觉得都很不错
Ithink it's very promising
包括基因呐
including genetics
基因测序
genetic sequencing
现在这个已经都是
now there is already
已经就是相当于这个
effectively
数据很丰富了
a very rich data set
一个人就是测序可以
one person's sequencing can
所有基因都测出来
map out all their genes
这个
and then
然后再加一个分析去预测
you can add analysis to predict
未来的这个健康管理
future health management needs
我是高度看好
I'm extremely bullish on that
高度看好
extremely bullish
然后这个学术界 对吧
that's academia, academia, right？
当然我们基于这个学术界这个领域
then based on those academic fields
就是我觉得就是
I think
产业界对吧
you have industry
赚钱可能相关
things related to making money
对
right
商业板块
in business
我觉得第一也可以
the first category can connect directly
基于学术对吧
to academia
像我刚才讲的都是相互连的
like I said, they're all interconnected
包括制药生物
pharmaceuticals and biotech
基因分析 健康管理
genetic analysis and health management
然后包括
and then
建立在这些一系列上面的金融行业
financial industries built on top of all that
比如说保险
insurance, for example
因为保险直接就跟人寿相关 对吧
because insurance directly relates to life expectancy
保险 这个金融行业 对吧
insurance and finance
就是我觉得就是我都很看好
I think all of those are promising
当然这些算法都要重新被颠覆了
of course, all these algorithms will be overtumned
因为现在的这些算法
because many of today's algorithms
很多都是很落后的
are very outdated
就是都等待我们年轻人
they're waiting for young people to
发明新的这一套逻辑和方法
invent a new set of logic and methods
当然 Crypto 我也很看好
I'm also very bullish on Crypto
因为 Crypto 其实它是个
because Crypto is
全球性的支付
a global payment layer
以及一个支付系统
and a payment system
所以它跟 AI是天然是联系的
so it's naturally connected to AI
而且 Crypto呢可以做这个
Crypto can also handle
很低精度的计算
calculations at very small units
就相当于比如说是API
for example, at the API level
可以按API 级别去读取算钱的
you can meter and charge at the API level
其实
basically
所以它是可以做到精度很低的计算
it can support extremely fine-grained calculations
比如说你传统行业
traditional industries
你根本做不到对吧
can't really do that
你可能最低单位就是1分对吧
your smallest unit might be one cent
你没有办法再做
and you can't go
更低精度的计算了 这个
below that level of precision
Crypto 是可以做很低精度的计算的
Crypto can support much finer-grained accounting
所以就是天然适配 AI 的API
so it's naturally suited to Al APIs
这个这一整套理论
that whole framework
而且是即时结算
and it offers instant settlement
我是很看好
I'm very bullish on it
就是它是跟这个 AI赛道
it's also very close
也是离得非常近
to the Al track
当然你去做本身 Al也还是很牛
and of course, doing Al itself is great too
对吧 这个 LLM
LLMs, for example
数据清洗这些
data cleaning and things like that
数据标注 对吧
data labeling
数据注 对吧
你别瞧不起数据标注的 对吧
don't look down on data labeling
那个 Scale Al 的创始人
the founder of Scale AI
就数据标注的公司
it's a data-labeling company
就都100多个亿卖给 Facebook 了 对吧
sold for over ten billion to Facebook, right？
就是这简直就是 现在就是
right now this is basically
遍地是机会
Opportunities are everywhere
捡钱行情好吧
a money-on-the-ground market
就是现在就是大家
So everyone
一定要珍惜自己
should really value the fact that
现在在这个年代
you're living in this era
处于一个20到40岁的这个年纪
and you're between 20 and 40
这个是最具创造力的年纪 然后呢
which is the most creative age range
遇到了这个最牛的
and you've encountered
人类的这个发明
humanity's greatest invention
遇到人类最牛的这个发明
所以这个就是比我
even compared with me
我都有点觉得我都有点
I already feel a little
落后了我今年都36了 对吧
behind - I'm 36 this year
还剩四年这个黄金时间了
I've only got four years of this golden window left
这个我自己十年前
ten years ago
甚至二十年前
even twenty years ago
我刚进大学时候17岁
when l entered college at 17
那个时候人类的科技
human technology at that time
实话实说是没有什么进步的
honestly hadn't advanced that much
就可能刚刚通网
the internet was only just becoming common
讲白了刚刚通网
basically, we had just gotten online
有点东西可以上网
there were a few things you could do online
但除此之外没了
but beyond that, not much
我们那时候就有一个校内网
we had Xiaonei back then
就上一下
we'd log on
你知道就是同学之间聊聊天
and chat with classmates
其实最多只是增进了一个联系
at most, it improved communication
没有像今天 AI 的这个一个大爆发
nothing like today's explosion in AI
一个大前进
this huge leap forward
太突破了 对
i's a massive breakthrough
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
就是现在真的不夸张
it's really not an exaggeration now
未来是只要你稍微
in the future, if youjust
努力一点
work a little harder
“人均诺贝尔奖"
"Nobel-level achievements for everyone"
真没夸张
I'm really not exaggerating
就诺贝尔奖的这个级别
achievements at the Nobel Prize level
这个成果
that kind of result
就人均就拿到
could become normal
人均拿到了
normal for everyone
这个真不是凡尔赛
and this isn't humblebragging
就会全行业开花
every industry will bloom
对全行业开花
yes, every industry
"人均诺贝尔奖"
"Nobel-level achievements for everyone"
最后诺贝尔奖都发不起了
eventually they won't even be able to hand out Nobel
Prizes
诺贝尔破产了
the Nobel foundation will go bankrupt
因为诺贝尔奖委员会说发不了了
the Nobel committee will say it can't keep paying
如果每个人都发100万美金对吧
if everyone gets a million dollars
那不破产了吗
wouldn't they go bankrupt？
但是就后面的成果
but the achievements that come afterward
绝对是人均诺贝尔奖
will absolutely be Nobel-level across the board
就是一个现在大学生
a college student today
加上AI一起做这个速度
working together with AI
分分钟就超过一个诺贝尔奖得主
could quickly surpass a Nobel laureate
所以就是我觉得就是未来的
so l think humanity in the future
这个人类真的进入
is genuinely entering
一个科技大爆发的时代
an era of explosive technological progress
这个
basically
所以这是为什么我自己
that's why lpersonally
当然很急着就是全部 AI化
am in such a hurry to make everything Al-driven
全部这个
everything
进入一个这个数据清洗
to enter this state of data processing
这个一个状态对吧
this kind of workflow
当然就是我觉得就是
of course, I think
就是最简单的就是练薄肌
the simplest thing is lean-muscle training
其实扣回原题
to bring it back to the original topic
我觉得也很重要
I think it's also very important
因为"薄肌理论”是一个最简单的
because "Lean-Muscle Theory" is one of the simplest things
你可以自己做一些
where you can personally run
最简单的 AI的变量控制
simple Al-controlled variables
然后你看你有没有效果 对吧
and see whether it works for you
如果说前面的那些理论都太
the earlier theories
是还需要一些时间嘛 对不对
still need some time, right？
因为你
because
从这个我刚才讲的
from what | was saying earlier
你看 100 套房
looking at 100 houses
到做出来一些决定
to actually making a decision
对你人生中真正有影响
that truly affects your life
还要一些时间
takes some time
但是”薄肌理论”是你只要上手对吧
but with "Lean-Muscle Theory." once you start
3个月肯定还是
three months should definitely
立竿见影
show results immediately
而且是年轻人薄肌理论是最有用
and "Lean-Muscle Theory" is most useful for young people
为什么对吧 那个70岁这个王石
why? Look at Wang Shi at 70
对吧也练薄肌
he trains for lean muscle too
对吧我看了
Isaw that
但是呢
but
我问了一下 AI
Iasked AI
AI说"70 岁练确实有点晚了"
Al said， "Starting at 7O is genuinely a bit late"
因为那个肌肉这个含量
because muscle mass
它那个最大值是下降的
has a dedlining maximum
从40岁之后
after age 40
所以你就是 70 岁练薄肌呢
so if you start lean-muscle training at 70
可能是勉强能够保证你就是能够
maybe you can just barely make sure
能够不坐轮椅
you don't end up in a wheelchair
你知道吧
you know？
但是就是你这个肌肉总量
but your total muscle mass
在你这个一生中这个
over your lifetime
最大量就是30-40岁就是到顶的
peaks around age 30 to 40
所以呢就是 30-40 岁练这个肌肉是
so training muscle at 30 to 40
是最关键的
is the most critical period
那70岁练
Starting at 70
有点晚了
is a bit late
对所以就是年轻人20-40岁
so for young people aged 20 to 40
我觉得这个薄肌可以说是两个字
I'd summarize lean-muscle training in two words：
“必练” 我觉得千万要练 对吧
“Must train" —I really think you absolutely should
必练必练
must train, must train
因为这个是
because
你这时候练是投资回报比最高的
that's when the return on investment is highest
就是还有一个有点意思的
and there's another interesting thing
我也问了 AI
Iasked Al about this too
我可以把这个答案告诉大家
I can share its answer with everyone
我这个
OS
我相信你就经常做节目
I think when you do shows often
也遇到别人经常问这个问题就说
you probably get this question a lot：
马斯克、巴菲特、特朗普
Elon Musk, Buffett, and Trump
这三个我的校友
all three are fellow alumni of mine
我的校友
my fellow alumni
我宾大的对吧
from Penn,right？
马斯克 巴菲特、特朗普三个校友
Elon Musk, Buffett, and Trump, all three Penn alumni
说他们三个人都反对健身
all against working out？
都没练薄肌
none of them train for lean muscle
都没练薄肌 对吧
none of them do, right？
都没练薄肌
none of them train for it
这个"为什么薄肌理论是对的”对吧
so "why is Lean-Muscle Theory right？"
说“这三个世界级的都不练薄肌”对吧
world-class figures don't train lean muscle" right？
这个 AI 当时给我讲了一个话
Al said something to me at the time
就立刻就把我说服了
and it convinced me immediately
AI 说“你跟巴菲特是吃过午餐的
Al said， "You ve had lunch with Buffett
巴菲特是自己走进餐厅的
did Buffett walk into the restaurant himself
还是别人推轮椅推进餐厅的？"
or was he pushed in in a wheelchair？"
推进的是吧
he was pushed in, wasn't he？
当然是推进的
of course he was pushed in
就这么一个简单的说
it's that simple
比如说你不练薄肌
if you don't train for lean muscle
好那就到80岁
then by the time you're 80
你就是轮椅推进来
you may be pushed in in a wheelchair
你要练了薄肌 80岁你就自己走进来
if you do, at 80 you can walk in yourself
对吧 你不用问
exactly, you don't need to ask
巴菲特 特朗普怎么想的
what Buffett or Trump thinks
你自己想不想80岁的时候
ask yourself, when you're 80
你是走进来还是推进来
do you want to walk in or be pushed in？
对吧
right？
就这么一个简单问题
it's that simple a question
就是说你要是练薄肌
if you train for lean muscle
80 岁你就自己走进来
at 80, you can walk in yourself
而且每天就只花40分钟多吗 对吧
and it only takes 40 minutes a day —is that much？
就是对你的这个人生的这个
the improvement to your
生活质量提升是巨大的
quality of life is enormous
如果 马斯克 不练薄肌
if Elon Musk doesn't train for lean muscle
那也在推进来的路上了 对吧
he's also on the road to being pushed in
就是现在这个
because right now
马斯克71年的吧
Elon Musk was born in '71, right？
还是72年的 对吧
or'72？
就比我大可能 20 岁对吧
he's probably about 20 years older than me
就是现在56可能56、57
he's around 56 or 57 now, right？
那 马斯克 如果保持这个
if Elon Musk keeps
不练肌肉这个状态
not doing strength training
再过二十年就是
then in another twenty years
他AI做得再牛也没用
it won't matter how good his Al is
也得推进来 对吧那
he'll still be pushed in, right？
除非那个时候
unless by then
马斯克 变成钢铁侠了
Elon Musk has become Iron Man
对吧 Neuralink 发明了
Neuralink has been invented
直接意识上传
and he can upload his consciousness directly
然后那直接就是金刚铁甲了
and turn into some kind of metal armor
那这个钢铁侠了
basically Iron Man
那就当我们没说 对吧
then forget everything we just said
如果你这个东西没搞出来你也得
but if he hasn't built that
推进来 因为你的这个的生物的
he'll still be pushed in, because biological
这个理论是不可抗拒的 对吧
laws can't be resisted
所以我当时觉得
so at the time | thought
这个 AI讲得非常对 就是说
Al was absolutely right —it was basically saying，"
马斯克、特朗普、巴菲特
Elon Musk, Trump, and Buffett
也没有办法逆天而行 对不对
can't defy nature either, right？"
你跟这个自然规律作对吗
can you fight the laws of nature？
那不可能的
impossible
你说"我不练〞是吧
if you say， "T'm not training"
你再牛有再多钱 没有用
it doesn't matter how successful or rich you are
对
right
这个自然规律就是这样定好的
the laws of nature are set that way
你跟上帝扳手腕吗 对吧
can you arm-wrestle with God？
上帝给人都设置好了时间
God already set the clock for everyone
你说"我就是逆天而行"
you say， "Im just going to defy fate"
这是绝对不可能的
that's absolutely impossible
所以这个只能顺应这个天命
so you can only go with fate
对吧 顺应这个
follow
已经设计好的这个东西 对吧
what has already been designed
你按照他这个规则来搞
and work according to those rules
所以呢我觉得就是 特朗普 巴菲特
sO l think Trump and Buffett
还包括 马斯克 都不赞成这个练薄肌呢
and Elon Musk, if they oppose lean-muscle training
其实他们是错的
they're wrong
就是我们年轻人别的他都可以学
young people can learn other things from them
思路都很优秀 对吧
their thinking is excellent
对对
right
就是我今天还转发了
l even reposted
马斯克 这个 Neuralink
Elon Musk's Neuralink today
说那个"我爱你”对吧
the one saying "1 love you" right？
但是 我觉得就是这个 马斯克
but I think if Elon Musk
如果不同意健身 这肯定是错的
disagrees with working out, then he's definitely wrong
所以得赶紧练起来
so we need to start training quickly
这个理论自信
this is about having confidence in the theory
我觉得我们现在这个孙学
I think people who follow Sunology
黄毛和薄肌的人还是要有
blond-hair mindset, and lean-muscle training need that
不用看到老登说那些人不练
don't see older guys who don't train
你就不练
and decide not to train yourself
对吧 就是绝对不行 对吧
absolutely not
而且我们不能用
and we can't
自己的身体开玩笑对不对
gamble with our own bodies
我们这个20岁到40岁
from age 20 to 40
现在这个身体是最好的时候
our bodies are at their best
为什么不练
why wouldn't you train？
现在练了
if you train now
你整个40岁到80岁的生活质量
your quality of life from 40 to 80
一个决定性提升
gets a decisive improvement
"薄肌就是风口"
"Lean muscle is the trend"
为什么不练
why wouldn't you train？
"薄肌就是风口"
"Lean muscle is the trend"
风口 绝对风口 绝对风口
absolutely a major trend
你这我跟你讲
I'm telling you
这刚才我们讲了人均诺奖
wejust talked about Nobel-level work for everyone
现在就是”人均薄肌"
now it's "lean muscle for everyone"
如果你现在在20岁到40岁中国年轻人
if you're a young Chinese person between 20 and 40
你没有薄肌 那不行
and you don't have lean muscle, that's not okay
上不了桌的
you can't even get a seat at the table
这上不了桌的
you can't get a seat at the table
课堂要求
it's basically a basic requirement
对你说太对了
exactly, you're so right
我们就是人均要求薄肌的 对吧
lean muscle should be a baseline for everyone
就像后面这个随着 AI发展
and later, as Al develops
人均得拿到诺奖级别
everyone will need Nobel-level achievements
你别以为诺奖级别是一个就高要求
don't think Nobel-level means an impossibly high bar
我们这个就是入门现在就得诺奖
in our era, the entry level is already Nobel-level
对吧 入门就得薄肌
and the entry level is lean muscle
如果你没有薄肌
if you don't have lean muscle
那讲清楚
then explain yourself
你到时候可以把你的
later you can give me
这个 API提供给我
your API
我读一下你到底
T'll read through your logs
在过去这个180天都在干嘛呀
what you ve been doing for the last 180 days
对不对 你到底在干嘛
what exactly have you been doing
导致你没有薄肌 对不对
that left you without lean muscle？
所以我觉得就是
SOlthink
就是这么一个思路
that's basically the idea
现在我觉得就是 AI 时代
in the Al era
真的是没有借口了
there really are no excuses
因为所有东西都准备好了 对吧
because everything is already prepared for you
而且呢
and also
我觉得确实时间很宝贵
I really do think time is incredibly valuable
因为这个AI时代
because in the Al era
就是我现在都是每天
I'm now running, every day
同时十几个智能体
ten or even more than ten agents at the same time
就是同时监控
monitoring things simultaneously
同时工作
and working simultaneously
我就抽出一点点时间
I only need to set aside a little time
就是微调一下这些智能体
to fine-tune those agents
它们就是发挥作用
and then they do their jobs
所以就是人的
So a person's
时间变得更宝贵了
time becomes even more valuable
因为你相当于是指挥
because you're essentially the one directing
安排这些智能体去干活的人
and assigning work to all these agents
所以你一个人可以操控
So one person cah control
成千上百个智能体干活
hundreds or even thousands of agents working
然后呢 你其实你的时间
And then, really, your time
主要就是需要什么呢
mainly needs to go toward what？
练薄肌把身体维护好
Building lean muscle and maintaining your body
就你自己的身体别崩了
Don't let your own body break down
因为现在我们的大脑呢
Because right now our brains
现在有个最惨的地方
have one unfortunate limitation
就是 Neuralink 技术还不够发达 对吧
Neuralink technology still isn't advanced enough, right？
被迫托管在这个碳基肉体上 对吧
in these carbon-based bodies, right？
所以碳基这个肉体的
That means maintaining this
维护是第一位的
carbon-based body comes first
碳基生物是有物理限制的
Carbon-based organisms have physical limits
物理限制
Physical limits
一会你的这个服务器你给搞崩了
If your server crashes one day
那你这边那个硅基
then no matter how well you've tuned
服务器你调得再牛没用 对吧
your silicon-based servers, it won't matter, right？
所以我觉得这个
Solthink our
咱们这个薄肌
lean-muscle idea
其实是维护你的这个碳基的服务器
is really about maintaining your carbon-based server
你得维护好吧
You have to maintain it,okay：？
你这服务器架子不能搭了呀 对不对
The server rack itself can't collapse, right？
这是最重要的
That's the most important thing
然后维护好碳基服务器
Then, once the carbon-based
的前提条件下
server is properly maintained
对这个硅基的 AI进行
you direct the silicon-based AI
一定程度的指挥 对吧
to a certain extent, right？
你要让它干什么
You decide what you want it to do
其实我现在人生
Honestly, my life right now
一天就在干这两件事 对吧
is basically just these two things every day, right？
碳基硅基两边分配好
Balance the carbon-based and silicon-based sides
但现在我毕竟是个人
But I'm still a human after all
所以还是碳基的时间是最关键的
so my carbon-based time is still the most critical
因为这个碳基就像我刚刚讲的
because like ljust said
它具有一票否决性
the carbon-based side has veto power
碳基一会给你一票否决了
If the carbon-based side vetoes you one day
你直接给病倒了
and you get seriously ill
就下线了
you go offline
游戏结束了
Game over
对下线了 那不行 不能
Right, you're offline. That won't work
千万不能下线
We absolutely cannot go offline
我们要超长待机 对吧
We need ultra-long uptime, right？
超长待机 对吧
Ultra-long uptime, right？
所以这个还不能下线
So we can't go offline
所以这个碳基这个第一位
That's why the carbon-based side comes first
在保证碳基的原则条件下
Once that principle is secured
适度归机
you can moderately hand things over to machines
现在我觉得就这么一个思路吧
That's basically how I see it now
我觉得一个"版本答案”和
I think an "optimal build" and
蓝图已经清晰地看到了
a blueprint have become very clear
就是如果你是一个年轻人
If you're a young person
不知道做什么
and you don't know what to do
你就练薄肌
build lean muscle
然后提升你自己的这个健康程度
and improve your health
活得更久一点
so you can live longer
这样
That way: yes
长线你才能够赢
you can win over the long run
而且薄肌它本身就是一个杠杆
And lean muscle itself is leverage
当你有了好的身体
Once you have a-healthy body
好的这个专注度之后
and strong focus
再结合 AI的应用
then combine that with using AI
那遍地是机会
and opportunities are everywhere
但当然了
But of course
首要条件还是薄肌、健康
the first requirement is still lean muscle and health
这是一个非常清晰的蓝图
That's a very clear blueprint
非常清晰了
Very clear
每个人都可以做
Everyone can do it
没有借口的
There are no excuses
对而且我是把这个
Right, and Iwant to take this
薄肌理论稍微再发扬一下
Lean-Muscle Theory a little further
我稍微发扬一下
Let me expand on it a bit
我昨天我还问了 AI
Yesterday l asked Al again
我就说后面这个人的寿命
about human lifespan going forward
很多人不是要问寿命嘛
A lot of people ask about longevity, right？
说想活长点
They want to live longer
当然年轻人可能大家没有这个
Young people may not really have this
概念 就我是超前一点
concept yet. I'm thinking a bit further ahead
包括一些中年人老年人
Some middle-aged and older people
可能比较关心这个话题了
may already care more about this topic
就说怎么才能活得长
How can you live longer？
对吧 因为年轻人二三十岁的
Right? People in their twenties or thirties
可能根本没想过这个问题因为
may never have thought about this because
对吧 且还处于人生前半段
they're still in the first half of life, right？
但是我开始想了
But I've started thinking about it
为什么呢 我36了
Why? I'm 36
对吧 我前面马上我活到40了
Right? I'm getting close to 40
前面一到40岁我都活完了
Once I reach 40
那我肯定要想40到80怎么活 对不对
So of course I think about how to live from 40 to 80, right？
40-80 很正常
40 to 80 is completely normal
活下一个40年对不对
That's another 40 years, right？
那我就是不是想到
So naturally I started thinking about
寿命长的这个问题了
this question of longevity
很自然而然就开始想 对吧
It just happens naturally, right？
好我问了一下：AI
Solasked Al
25 就是这一共100分
There are 100 points in total
一共100分
A total of 100 points
就你这个寿命一共100分
Think of longevity as a 100-point score
25 分是心肺
Twenty-five points are cardiovascular fitness
25 分是肌肉
Twenty-five points are muscle
就肌肉含量
meaning muscle mass
25 分是肌肉
Twenty-five points are muscle
也就是心肺和肌肉呢
So cardiovascular fitness and muscle
天
Wow
这个
that means
占比很大呀肌肉
muscle accounts for a huge share
两个东西就占了50分
Those two together are 50 points
对对
Exactly
就占了50分
That's 50 points
然后呢 咱们这个练薄肌
And when we train for lean muscle
两个都管上了
we cover both of them
因为呢 就是你光跑步
Because if youonly run
掉肌肉 练那个心肺白练
you lose muscle, so training cardio alone misses the point
你呢 如果能练个薄肌
But if you build lean muscle
穿上这么一身
and put on this kind of
就像你刚刚讲的传奇皮肤
legendary skin, like you said earlier
一方面自动帮你烧这个
for one thing, it automatically helps you burn
对烧脂肪
yes, burn fat
它是被动燃脂
It's passive fat burning
睡觉就燃脂
You burn fat even while sleeping
对被动燃脂
Right passive fat burning
然后其次呢
And secondly
就有点像是那个王者荣耀里面
it's a bit like in Honor of Kings
出了一个那个叫做红莲斗篷
there's an item called the Blazing Cape
那个就是
which
它是这个自带法伤
comes with built-in magic damage
贴着别人就扣对方血 对吧
You stand near someone and they lose HP, right？
你就像穿着皮肤 你贴着就燃脂
It's like wearing a skin that burns fat just by being there
对吧 这个多牛
Right?That's pretty great
而这个且不说那个 25的
And that's before even talking about the 25 points
那个肌肉本身起到作用
that muscle itself contributes
就让你不会摔倒
It keeps you from falling
让你不会这个瘫
and from becoming immobilized
让你不会下床
from being unable to get out of bed
就让你不会瘫到床上
It keeps you from being bedridden
不会瘫到凳子上
or stuck in a Chair
然后呢 就是本身还在燃脂 然后呢
And it keeps burning fat at the same time
练薄肌的这个过程
The process of building lean muscle
本身也提升心肺能力
also improves cardiovascular fitness
因为你要呼气
because you nave to breathe hard
要做这个上重量
and lift heavier weights
要这个本身也在提升心肺
That process itself also trains your cardio
所以你就基本靠练肌肉这一个事
So basically, just by training muscle
把这个前面 50分全部拿到手了
you can collect all of those first 50 points
所以就是后面的
Then the remaining part
这个不吸烟不喝酒
includes not smoking or drinking
什么你自己的基因
things like your genetics
会不会得癌症
whether you might get cancer
包括眼 牙 几个
and important areas like your eyes and teeth
比较重要的这个就是器官
and several other key organs
这个查
that need to be checked
这些后面的
Those laterfactors
反而还要花钱有的 对吧
sometimes actually cost money, right？
你有的需要
Some of them require
你就是花钱
you to spend money
像比如说牙科其实挺贵的 对吧
Dentistry, for example, is pretty expensive, right？
有的需要你就是这个运气好
And some depend on being lucky
比如说你父母的基因要好
like having good genetics from your parents
但是你说前面这所有的
But all those other things
东西都没有办法突破的极限
have limits you can't necessarily break through
前面那个50分
those first 50 points
心肺和肌肉
cardio and muscle
通过练薄肌
through lean-musdle training
你可以拿满的
you can max them out
拿满分
Maxed out
而且我这都是我的一些研究成果
And this is based on some of my own research
我前两天我还又跟这个 Claude AI 聊了
A couple of days ago I talked to Claude Al again
就是唯 个就是
The one approach that
不会让你心血管爆表
won't push your cardiovascular system past the limit
还被动燃脂 对吧
also gives you passive fat burning, right？
还有肌肉
And you get musdle
还把你这 50分都给你拉满 对吧
and you max out all 50 of those points, right？
我们讲的还自带美颜特效 对吧
it even comes with a built-in beauty filter, right？
带燃脂特效
Affat-burning effect
带这个泡妞特效
and a dating boost
泡妞特效还提升形象对自信
that also improves your image and confidence
对 提升形象的
Right, it improves your image
唯一就只有薄肌这一条路
The only route is lean muscle
真的真的
Seriouslyr seriously
这是科学
This is science
你知道都不是说什么乱发明的科学
It's not some made-up theory; it's science
尊重科学
Respect science
我就是研究了
I've actually studied this
尊重科学 尊重科学
Respect science, respect science, respect science
真的要尊重科学
You really have to respect science
就是我自己是认真研究了
I genuinely researched this myself
我说“这个一定一定要
I said， "We absolutely, absolutely have to
走向薄肌这条道路
go down the lean-muscle path"
是
Yes
我也坚信我做这件事情是对的
I firmly believe what I'm doing is right
它确实是在
It realy is
就是无论是对这个国力 对吧
good for national strength too, right？
如果一个国家
If an entire country
全部是薄肌小子的话
were full of lean, muscular young men
那是一件非常好的事情
that would be a very good thing
因为薄肌小子首先他长寿
First, those guys live longer
他健康他而且他的执行力各方面
ability to execute is stronger in every way
他就是一个
They're basically
我觉得一个国家的
I think, for a country
薄肌小子多少就是这个国力
the number of lea
非常重要
It's very important
它是战略储备资源
They're a strategic reserve resource
对非常
Yes, very much so
那个而且你讲得非常对
And you're absolutely right
对国家来说
For a country
薄肌小子是战略储备资源
lean, muscular young men are a strategic reserve
对这个人来说
For an individual
我前两天我也就是一个振聋发聩
a couple of days ago I had another real wake-up call
我觉得振聋发聩
I mean, a real wake-up call
就是我决定练薄肌
My decision to build lean muscle
不是大家讲的
wasn't because of what people were saying
我的这个东西呢出问题了
about my recent situation
然后呢 这个不是有个风波嘛
There was that whole controversy, right？
大家嘲笑我
People mocked me
有人说我一米 63 的 是吧
Some said | was only 163 centimeters tall, right？
虽然我其实一米 72
Even though I'm actually 172
不是米 63
not 163
也有人说我很胖 对吧
Some also said I was fat,right？
说我胖导致这个没有生理性喜欢
that being fat meant there was no physical attraction
对吧 就一堆
There were all kinds of comments, right？
网上一堆这些说法
all sorts of things like that
这个其实这些都不是导致
But none of that was actually
我练薄肌的一个关键原因
the key reason I decided to build lean muscle
我练薄肌
For me, training
要练薄肌的一个最关键原因呢
The most important reason I decided to build lean muscle
就是我确实发现这个东西
was that | genuinely realized
一是符合科学的
first, it aligns with science
第二我问 AI
Secona, askeda
AI 又给我讲了一句话
and Al said something else to me
一下子把我震撼了
that really shook me
Al跟我说
Altold me
NN
这个你怎么理解练薄肌这个事呢
this idea of building lean muscle？
就是现在
Right now
N
我可能物质上丰富了
you may be materially wealthy
是一个富人
a rich person
但是身体上
but physically
我是一个穷人
you're poor
因为什么呢
Why？
它给我讲都是有理有据的
It explained it with actual reasoning and evidence
不是乱讲
It wasn'tjust making things up
它说"身体上你现在是个穷人"
I said， "physically, you're poor right now"
练薄肌就是领工资
Building lean muscle is like collecting a paycheck
就是把自己这个工资要调高
It's about raising your own salary
因为为什么呢
Why？
因为你身体的这个肌肉
Because the muscle in your body
很宝贵它不仅负责你每天的支撑
is extremely valuable. It supports you every day
各种东西的使用而且呢
and lets you do all kinds of things. And also
就是一旦要开始扣东西的时候
when your body has to start drawing down reserves
是先扣脂肪还是先扣肌肉
does it draw from fat first or muscle first？
是先扣肌肉
It draws from muscle first
这也为什么这个是
That's also why
有氧运动是掉肌肉
aerobic exercise can cost you muscle
因为它消耗
because it consumes energy
你一旦没有补完全
and if you don't fully replace what you used
它就要掉你的肌肉
your body starts breaking down muscle
对吧 就这肌肉
Right?So muscle
很多程度上
in many ways
就比如说你生场大病
for example, if you get seriously ill
也是先扣肌肉
is also what your body draws down first
就是所有的这个肌肉
All that muscle
相当于是你的一个
is essentially your most
最重要的这个银行账户
important bank account
所以你平常一定要是这个
So whenever you have the chance
时间够的时候多吃蛋白质
make sure you eat plenty of protein
多吃鸡肉
eat more chicken
把这个东西给存起来
and store that reserve
对 有条件的时候先存起来
Right, when conditions allow, build up the reserve first
它是一个战略储备资产
It's a strategic reserve asset
对这个肌肉其就是你身上的现金
Right, muscle is basically cash on your body
你得存起来这
You have to save it up
所以说薄肌会取代美金
So when we say lean muscle will replace the dollar
这个不是开玩笑的
we're notjoking
它是这个是事实
That'sjust a fact
比美金还关键
It's even more important than dollars
因为美金没了可以再赚
because if you lose dollars, you can earn them again
就用薄肌都可以赚 对吧
You can even use your physique to earn money, right？
你扛个大包还赚不上美金吗
If you can carry heavy loads, you can still earn dollars
对对对
Exactly
所以这个薄肌
That's why lean muscle
绝对是要什么
absolutely needs to be something you
取代美金
prioritize dollar
尽早开始
Start as early as possible
尽早储备
Build the reserve as early as possible
对吧 就是非常非常关键
Right? It's extremely important
非常关键
Extremely important
而且其实刚才这个
And actually, what we were just saying
薄肌理论真的是要推行
about Lean-Muscle Theory really should be promoted
因为薄肌理论推行好
because if you promote it well
减少胖子
you reduce obesity
给国家的这个医保
and save the country money on healthcare
社保也省钱
and social insurance too
对吧 否则你说这个90%的疾病都跟
something like 90% of diseases are related to
刚才讲的心血管肥胖有关系 对吧
cardiovascular issues and obesity，
只要这个东西掉下来了
Once those come down
所有问题都解决了
a lot of problems improve
就不生病了
People get sick less often
有肌肉
They have muscle
而且生场大病
and even if they do get seriously ill
恢复速度非常快
they recover much faster
因为它直接从你
because the body can directly draw from
的这个肌肉这边提取
those muscle reserves
修复你各种粘膜
to repair different tissues and membranes
修复各种东西
and repair different things
速度是最快的
It's the fastest reserve to draw on
就是恢复速度也快
So recovery is faster
生病抵抗力也强
and resilience to illness is stronger
所以就是全部
So overall
我最后算一下
when ladd it all up
这个练薄肌太关键了
building lean muscle is incredibly important
就是真的是
It really is
就是对于健康这个领域是一个
In the field of health
基本上我觉得起到
I think it basically plays
决定性作用 决定性作用
a decisive role, a decisive role
就这个中流砥柱
It's a pillar
绝对是中流砥柱
Absolutely a pillar
所以这是为什么我就是高度重视
That's why I take it so seriously
我觉得就是从这个认识上就是
I think my understanding of it has
认知上升级了哈
really gone through an upgrade
绝对升级
Absolutely an upgrade
我振聋发聩
It was a wake-up call for me
AI 对我的话
What Al said to me
我就振聋发聩
was a real wake-up call
因为AI跟我讲说
Because Al told me
你物质上可能是个富人
“Materially, you may be rich
但是你身体上你现在是个穷人
but physically, right now you're poor".
所以您对这方面的好奇
So was your curiosity about this area
这一次的彻底的升级
and this complete shift in your thinking
是不是跟我这一波的
in some way inspired by
薄肌理论的这个创始
me creating this Lean-Muscle Theory？
是不是有一定的启发
Did it have some influence？
绝对有 绝对有
Absolutely, absolutely
我自己呢
For me personally
其实是这样
here's some background to it
我以前呢
In the past
我讲讲我自己对于
let me talk about how l used to think about
这个肌肉的这个认识
muscle
我可能以前
Back then I probably
也经历过
went through
就是很浅薄的年代
a pretty shallow phase
对于肌肉这个认识
in how lunderstood it
我觉得那个时候
At the time
我也是年轻
Iwas also very
尤其年轻的时候
young, especially when | was younger
所以这个错误认知很耽误人
So mistaken beliefs can really set you back
我就是这个错误认知
This mistaken belief of mine
怎么耽误我呢
how did it hold me back？
就是说我也就是想说
I used to think
说
well
这个练肌肉是不是为了泡妞
"Is building muscle just for picking up girls？
那些练肌肉人都不正经
People who build muscle aren't serious people
他们都是想泡妞才去练肌肉
They're only training because they want to pick up girls"
然后这个
And that
这是我第一个
was my first
就是很武断的一个推动
very sweeping assumption
第二个就是说
Second, I thought
这个肌肉 有肌肉的人呢
people with muscular bodies
都是上科技了 对吧
must all be using PEDs, right？
就是打了什么东西
injecting something or other
然后网上也有一些公众号
And there are social-media accounts online
是迎合这个的
that cater to this belief
就说什么谁谁谁又打药练肌肉
saying this person or that person
一下又死了什么的 对吧
and then suddenly died, things like that, right？
有点妖魔化
It demonizes the whole thing a bit
妖魔化
Demonizes it
然肩就是
And then
然后就是
N
我以前也经常受到这些影响
I used to be influenced by all that too
然后想
and think
自己太忙了不用练
I'm too busy, I donit need to train
就说这个
I'd tell myself
而且我有一度也想
and for a while l even thought
就说追求这个健康就行了
all l needed to pursue was health
追求
Just pursue
很搞笑
It's funny now
我给自己定的一个理论叫
I came up with this idea for myself that
把肌肉跟健康反而对立起来了
actually put muscle and health in opposition
对立起来了
I treated them as opposites
说有肌肉不健康
I thought having muscle was unhealthy
错误认知
A mistaken belief
这就是错误认知
That's a mistaken belief
错误认知
A mistaken belief
然后呢 我自己也不重视这个东西
Sol didn't value muscle at all
很不重视这个东西
I really didn't value it
这一次有这个风波之后呢
Then after this recent controversy
全网对我进行了个网暴
I got attacked all over the internet
给你骂醒了
people basically criticized me awake
也不叫骂醒了
Well, I wouldn't exactly say "'criticized me awake"
但是第一个呢 我就
but first of all
我这个人呢
I'm the kind of person who
其实是有则改之
corrects myself when criticism is valid
无则加勉
and treats it as a warning even when it isn't
其实我别人网暴我
Honestly, when people attack me online
我也无所谓
Idon't really care
实话实说
To tell the truth
我已经过了那个就是小心灵 对吧
I've already moved past being that sensitive, right？
就黄毛理论我还是练成了
Ive more or less mastered the Blond-Hair Theory
虽然我自己现在是黑毛 对吧
Even though my own hair is black right now, right？
但是已经被黄毛理论武装好了
I'm already armed with that mindset
所以我不会因为别人的评价
So other people's opinions don't make me
额外想什么
overthink things
但是我觉得大家讲的
But rerdaskswhetbher |
这个有没有一点道理呢
some of what people were saying had a point
我觉得这个
lthought
对吧 这个肌肉问题以及
this muscle issuey and also
我的这个头大四肢小
the fact that my head looks big and my limbs look small
是不是一个问题呢
is that actually a problem？
我深刻思考了一下
I thought about it seriously
当然也跟我自己现在
Of course, it also has to do with
这个 AI 时代有关系
being in the Al era now
所以我呢
So for me
第一个请教我就问一下这个 AI
my first move was to ask AI
然后呢 我就跟 Claude Code 我们俩
Then Claude Code and |
进行了深刻的对话
had a serious, in-depth conversation
深刻对话然后呢
A really in-depth conversation, and then
这个 Claude Code 就给我讲
Claude Code told me
说你这个看法错误的
that mny ve wyas wrong |
然后我们俩进行了一个辩论
So the two of us debated it
我也把我的一些陈旧
Jaso threw some ofmy oid
的理论我就抛给他
theories at it
然后Claude Code给我一一都反驳了
and Claude Code rebutted them one by one
而且就给我树立起了
It also helped me establish
就是这个什么
this idea that
这个肌肉就是你身体的这个储蓄
muscle is basically savings stored in your body
这个最关键
That's the key point
确实是一个认知升级
It really was an upgrade in how I think
很多人不理解
A lot of people don't understand this
我想稍微补充一下
I want to add one thing
就是有一句古话叫四肢发达
There's an old saying： "strong limbs
头脑简单
simple mind"
但我觉得这其实是不对的
But l don't think that's right
我觉得是四肢发达
I think strong limbs
头脑发达
go with a strong mind
因为它是相辅相成的
because the two reinforce each other
对你说太对了 对吧
Yes, exactly. You're absolutely right
而且我觉得呀
And I think
四肢发达头脑简单
that saying "strong limbs, simple mind"
并没有坑四肢发达的人
didn't really hurt the people with strong limbs
把很多头脑发达的人给骗了
It fooled a lot of smart people instead
对对他以为不用练
Exactly They thought they didn't need to train
有很多头脑很发达的人
There are plenty of people with highly developed minds
其实很聪明
who are genuinely very smart
数理化我跟你讲
Great at math and science, I'm telling you
就是很牛的人
really exceptional people
Al 也很牛的人 对吧
people who are also great at Al, right？
AI 也很牛的人 对吧
你像特朗普 马斯克 巴菲特
Look at Trump, Elon Musk, and Buffett
这三个人能说不聪明吗
Could you say those three aren't smart？
那都是世界上最顶尖的聪明人了
They're among the smartest people in the world
对吧 我的校友
Right?My fellow alumni
但他们都是说健身有害
But all three say exercise can be harmful
他们怎么被骗的
So how were they fooled？
我觉得就是刚才讲的
I think it's what we just talked about
这个人呢
Sometimes
有时候屁股決定脑袋
"where you sit shapes how you think"
他没有做出改变之前
Before someone changes
因为他不是薄肌
because they don't have a lean, muscular physique
所以他就会说诶
they'll say
我是胖子
"！'m overweight"
或者我是这个大肚子
or "| have a big belly""
那我要为大肚子说话 对吧
so l have to defend having a big belly, right？
对 对对“屁股决定脑袋"
Exactly—"where you sit shapes how you think"
但这就是
AndIcan
我可以理解
understand that
但这是不客观的
but it isn't objective
这是在不尊重科学和不尊重事实
It doesn't respect science or facts
对这个就有点像是
Right, it's a little like
比如说我是一个穷人
iflim poor
我不想怎么变成富人
instead of thinking about how to become rich
对你就说钱没用
I say money is useless
钱没用
"Money is useless"
我就说钱没用
ljust keep telling myself money is useless
而且说
And Imight say
你看那个钱会导致你
"Look, money can cause
你说很多富人家里因为
problems in rich families
一点钱发生一起凶杀案
people can even kill each other over a little money
全家都被杀了
an entire family can be destroyed"
你看这个钱是严重
Then I say， "See? Money seriously
就是阻碍这个家庭幸福
gets in the way of family happiness
所以我穷是有原因的 对吧
so there's a reason I'm poor，" right？
我是选择不富
"I'm choosing not to be rich"
我告诉你
I'm telling you
我是选择不富 对吧
"I'm choosing not to be rich" right？
就是
That's the idea
而且越聪明的人越有这个呢
And the smarter someone is, the more they may do this
他就越容易受到这个屁股决定脑袋
The more susceptible they are to
对吧 他就说我就是不
They say， "T'm just not going to
就是死活就是不去弄这个事
do this, no matter what"
而且还发明了很多理论
And they invent all kinds of theories
可能还嘲笑这个练的人 对吧
and may even mock the people who do train, right？
就是所以我说为什么
That's why I say
你一练就会遭到嫉妒 对吧
once you start training, you may attract jealousy, right？
因为周边的人就会指责你
People around you may criticize you
而且他们有这个很强
and they can have ven
很强大的这个东西去侵略你
powerful narvatives that push into your thinking
对吧 侵略你
that invade yourthinking, right？
对对
Exactly
所以呢 就是这个
我就觉得就是
think
那我为什么能跳出这个理论 对吧
how was lable to break out of that framework, right？
虽然现在我还是大肚腩 对吧
Even though Istill have a belly right now
现在走在薄肌的路上
I'm on the road to a lean, muscular physique
这才练了一天
I've only been training for a day
思维更新了
but my thinking has changed
思维彻底更新了
My thinking has completely changed
思维就是改革开放
It's like reform and opening up
对吧 中国这个改革开放
China's reform and opening up, right？
邓小平走上这个改革开放之路
Deng Xiaoping put China on that path
改革开放之路也不好走
and that path wasn't easy either
当时的时候就说投机倒把
Back then, people talked about
你做这个生意高卖低买
If you bought and sold goods
属于投机倒把
buying low and selling high was considered profiteering
抓起来的呀
and you could get arrested for it
对吧 要抓起来
Right? You could be arrested
对吧 那有的人说不对
Then some people said, no
说你得这个换这个思路了
we need to change how we think about this
那脑袋不对
The old mindset is wrong
不仅不抓起来
Not only should we not arrest them
还是反的
we should see it the other way around
就说他能够这个低买
If someone can buy low
高卖是他的本事
and sell high,that'sa skill
这证明他能够让消费者 对吧
It proves they can help consumers
能够买到更便宜的东西
buy things more cheaply. right？
因为他只要卖出去证明是便宜嘛
If they can sell it, that means the price works
对不对哎
right？
N
那如果我在美国买一个东西便宜的
Ifl buy something cheaply in the U.S.
我来中国卖
and bring it to China to sell
其实不仅没卖
I'm not merely
赚中国人的钱
making money from Chinese consumers
反而给中国人带来的
I'm also bringing Chinese consumers
科技带来新的东西
new technology and new products
对吧 这个商品是
Right? So commerce like that
就鼓励呢
should be encouraged
不仅不抓起来
Not only should the person not be arrested
还要评为人大代表政协委员
they might even become an
对不对
right？
就这个思路
That's the change in thinking
就是我们对于这个薄肌
And with lean muscle
我前一段时间就是
over the last
可能有这个两周
maybe two weeks
进行了一个认知升级
I've had a similar cognitive upgrade
肌肉不仅不是有害身体健康
Muscle isn't harmful to health
是有益身体健康
it's beneficial to health
咱们这个要多积累肌肉‘
We should build more muscle
不是反的说不练
not avoid training
给肌肉控制住 对吧
or deliberately suppress muscle, right？
我觉得这个思想就是
I think that change in thinking
由这个闭关锁国走向改革开放
is like moving from isolation to reform and opening up
最关键我觉得最关键
That's the key, I think
所以所有人其实听到我们
So anyone listening to
这个 Podcast 都不用急着练肌肉
rush out and train immediately
对 你自己去先
First, go
你自己去问
ask foryourself
不用借我们的结论
Don't just borrow our conclusion
你自己去问
Go ask for yourself
对 一自己去问第二个
First, ask. Second
对一自己去问第二个‘
First, ask Second
First, ask. Second
你先想明白是不是这个理
think it through and decide whether it makes sense
对对对 尊重科学
Exactly—respect
对不对
the reasoning, right？
这个就是我觉得这个
This is something
我以前
lused to
我还提出一个理论
have another theory about
就我自己也是一个思考吧
just part of my own thinking
就是我以前呢
In the past
也是就是好像特地要避开肌肉
I almost deliberately tried to avoid building muscle
就好像很多女生经常健身的时候
It's like when many women go to the gym
不第一个问教练就问题说
and the first thing they ask the trainer is
我一点肌肉都不要练
"I don't want to build any muscle at all
怕练太大
I'm afraid Ill get too big
我要
I want to
既保持身体健康
stay healthy
我又要一点肌肉都没有 好吧
but have no muscle at all, okay？"
就是说这个思路去跟教练讲的
That's the mindset they bring to the trainer
所以我也受这个思路影响
I was influenced by that mindset too
就是误导
and misled by it
就是说不仅不要练肌肉
I thought not only should I not build muscle
所以呢 我以前就是可能多做有氧
but I should probably do more cardio
少做器械
and less resistance training
少做肌肉
less musdle work
N
现在我也就是恍然大悟
Now I've had this sudden realization
这个是完全是害人的
that this was completely wrong
错的错的对
completely wrong
有氧都可以不做
You can even skip dedicated cardio
因为你练肌肉
because when you train muscle
练这个器械
and do resistance work
做抗阻的时候本身就
the resistance training itself
其实提升心肺
also improves cardiovascular fitness
不用专门再去练有氧了
You don't necessarily need separate cardio
而且你需要的 人需要的就是肌肉
And what your body really needs is muscle
拢共就能
Altogether
你自己能做的心肺肌肉就各25分
the parts you can control are 25 points
就一共50分对吧
50 points total, right？
你这个东西你通过练
By training
薄肌全部都拿到了
for lean musdle, you get all of them
你如果练心肺
If you only train cardio
既把肌肉练没了还
you may lose muscle while doing it
你只有心肺那 25分
and only get the 25 cardio points
你肌肉的 25 分还是没有
while still missing the 25 muscle points
对吧 就是我是彻底给我就是点醒了
That really woke me up completely
相当于 你知道吧
You know what I mean？
就是我是彻底就是
It completely
转为薄肌理论的
converted me to Lean-Muscle Theory
那您说的这所有的东西
Everything you ve said
其实都完美符合
actually fits perfectly
完全符合了我那个
with everything in my
薄肌教程）里面的內容 透 邵艾伦Alan．9-1
Lean-Musde Guide
《薄肌教程》里面的内容
Lean-Muscle Guide
所以说您是建议这个大家
So would you recommend that everyone
看一看这个《薄肌教程》
watch the Lean-Muscle Guide？
因为确实
Because it really is
绝对绝对绝对 绝对看
Absolutely, absolutely, absolutely—watch it
我这个节目我非常推荐
I highly recommend it on this show
就是《薄肌圣经》
It's basically the "Lean-Muscle Bible"
这个叫《薄肌圣经》
That's what | call it, the "Lean-Muscle Bible"
《薄肌圣经》对
The "Lean-Muscle Bible" yes
那对那个视频我是下载了
I downloaded that video
我下载了都
I downloaded all of it
我都下载了
I downloaded it
保存下来了
and saved it
而且我逐帧逐句给 AI都看了
leven had Al go through it frame by frame and line by line
逐帧逐句给 AI 都看了
frame by frame and line by line
这个
And
我觉得是非常有用
I think it's extremely useful
这个但是呢
But
我觉得呢
Ithink
唯一一个就是我觉得这个播客
there's one thing this podcast
咱们这个播客聊的有一个点
can add to that material
就是可以弥补这个薄肌圣经的
something that can complement the Lean-Muscle Bible
您说
Go ahead
就是薄肌圣经的人呢
People reading the Lean-Muscle Bible
一定得是
first have to
认识到了薄肌理论是对的
accept that Lean-Muscle Theory is correct
才能读进去
before they can really take it in
否则呢 他就直接就划过
Otherwise they'll just scroll past it
我觉得我们还可以
I think we could also
做一期叫"薄肌问答"
do an episode called "Lean-Muscle Q&A"
我觉得就是挑一些很基础的问题
and pick some really basic questions
就最
the most
就是
common
常见的误区
misconceptions
误导 的问题
and misleading ideas
常见的误区
the most common misconceptions
我们给他解答一下
and answer them
回答一下
Explain them
把这些人都点醒
Wake people up on these points
误导很多人 对吧
They've influenced a lot of people, right？
然后而且我跟你讲
And let me tell you
马斯克 在这个地方就是
Elon Musk in particular
扮演一个很不好的角色什么呢
plays a pretty unhelpful role here
马斯克 自己是胖子
Elon Musk himself is overweight
就是也不说完全胖吧
Maybe not exactly overweight
但跟我的情况是一样
but his situation is similar to mine
就是四肢很很瘦然后呢
his arms and legs are quite thin
主要的那个脂肪
while most of the fat
聚集在这个躯干
collects around his torso
躯干很大
so the torso looks large
然后呢 他呢
Then there's
就是那个
the guy
有一个那个 约翰逊
Bryan Johnson
就是搞那个"不要死"的那个人
the person behind "Don't Die"
"不要死"
"Don't die"
"不要死”的这个人
the guy whose message is "don't die"
他呢 以前 约翰逊呢
Bryan:Johnson used to
其实也是
also have
就是四肢很瘦
very thin arms and legs
躯干很大因为
and a larger torso because
这是我们这个互联网
that's common among us
创业者都是这样的
internet entrepreneurs
然后他呢
Then he
就是奉行的薄肌理论
basically followed Lean-Muscle Theory
去练了一下薄肌
and built some muscle
那约翰逊 你可以看
Now if you look at Bryan Johnson
现在也不敢说薄肌吧
I wouldn't necessarily call him lean and muscular
但至少人家身体是健康的 对吧
but at least he looks healthy, right？
有肌肉有这个
He has muscle and
人家的这个基本是都做了
he's covered the basics
然后 马斯克 反而在 约翰逊 的这个
Then Elon Musk commented under
这个推特下面留言
one of Bryan Johnson's posts
就是也是一个打击薄肌理论
undermines Lean-Muscle Theory
他说什么呢
What did he say？
"你以前看起来更好"
"You looked better before"
因为那个 约翰逊
Bryan Johnson had
把两个照片
posted two photos together
他以前的一个胖的
one from before when he was heavier
就是这个
and
就是不健康的
less healthy
和他练了的
and one after he trained
发在一块
side by side
你知道吧
You know？
就是号召大家去这个健身嘛
He was encouraging people to exercise
去练
to train
然后 马斯克 反而在下面回一个就说
And Elon Musk replied underneath
我现在就是要扭曲你这个认知
basically trying to flip the interpretation
我说"你之前更好"
saying， "You looked better before"
你意思是你这么久就是白练了 对吧
Meaning all that training was for nothing, right？
"屁股决定脑袋"
"Where you sit shapes how you think"
马斯克"屁股决定脑袋”
For Musk too， "where you sit shapes how you think"
马斯克"屁股決定脑袋"
"屁股决定脑袋"对
Exactly
"屁股决定脑袋"
"Where you sit shapes how you think"
真是这样
That's the reality
但是我真的
But really
这个"屁股决定脑袋"
with this " where you sit shapes how you think" effect
马斯克 传播这个错误思想
who loses the most from Elon Musk
吃亏最大的人是谁
He does
自己他自己
Himself
是马斯克 自己
Elon Musk himself
那个 AI 已经跟我讲了
Al already told me
马斯克 就是现在已经比我大20岁
Elon Musk is about 20 years older than lam
现在都 56 57了
he's already in his mid-to-late fifties
马斯克 每过一年再不练薄肌
Every year Elon Musk doesn't start building lean muscle
就又丧失一年的宝贵时光
he loses another year of valuable time
因为每年的肌肉按照
because muscle mass declines
1%2%的这个速度在下降
by around 1-2% a year
就是
So
而且如果你再过60了
once you're past 60
你练都来不及了
it becomes much harder to catch up
因为我们现在这个练
Right now, when we train
可以比如说两天这个循环
we can use something like a two-day cycle
你后面要是这个身体的修复力差了
Later, when your body's recovery ability declines
你可能要三四天
you may need three or four days
四五天才一个循环
or four or five days for each cycle
你那个器械练了你要恢复的
After resistance training, you need time to recover
你又不是
You can't just
对吧 狂上器械
keep hammering heavy equipment, right？
你要练要恢复要这个
You have to train and recover
这个就是
So
后面这个账单会越积越大
the cost compounds as you get older
对 所以一定要练
That's why you absolutely should train
趁早练 对
Start early
对趁早练趁早练
Yes, start early, start early
绝对趁早练
Absolutely start early
欢迎大家加入我们薄肌俱乐部
Everyone is welcome to join our lean-muscle club
那这个薄肌话题可能差不多到这边
I think that's about it for the lean-muscle topic
我还想再稍微推进一下
I want to move things forward a little
我可以推进下一个话题
Can l move to the next topic？
好好好
sure, sure
对那就是
Right,so
对 我想问一个比较个人的问题
I want to ask a more personal question
一个比较个人的问题 对我想间
就是我今年30 岁嘛
Im 30 this year
然后过去十年的战略
and my strategy over the past decade
基本上就是符合孙学的‘
has basically followed Sunology
我的主线就是挣钱投资
My main quest was making money and investing
尽快实现财富自由
to reach finandial freedom as quickly as possible
那到我现在这个阶段
At my current stage
差不多完成了
I've more or less done that
那如果您站在我这个位置
If you were in my position
会如何规划人生的
how would you plan
下—个十年战略呢
the strategy for the next ten years of life？
下一个十年战略呢
好我讲一下我的这个思路
Okay, let me explain how I think about it
我的这个思路呢
My framework
就是我以前还有一个理论
comes from another theory I've had for a long time
也是在孙学里面吧但是
which is also part of Sunology
就是我可以着重讲一下
butI can focus on it here
就是我的这个理论呢
The theory is
就是说什么呢
what exactly？
^
就是说我觉得就是
Ithink
我非常欣赏就是 这个游牧民族
I really admire nomadic peoples
游牧民族
Nomadic peoples
游牧民族呢
就是有一个
have one
他们的一个特点
particular characteristic
就是几个字总结很简单
that can be summed up very simply
就叫”逐水草而居“五个字
in five Chinese characters： "follow the water and grass"
“逐水草而居“是什么意思呢
What does "follow the water and grass" mean？
就是哪里有水
Wherever there's water
哪里有草
wherever there's grass
我们就去哪住
that's where you live
因为游牧民族很简单
For nomadic peoples, it's simple
我放羊嘛
you herd sheep
放羊那羊肯定是要吃水
and sheep need water
要吃草
andgrass
这两个最关键的
Those are the two essentials
所以哪有水草呢
So wherever the water and grass were
匈奴以及这个辽国以及这个金国
groups like the Xiongnu, Liao, and Jin
就去哪
would go there
当然呢 这个辽金
Of course
这个匈奴
the Liao, Jin
在我们中国历史上呢
and Xiongnu
被妖魔化的很严重
Chinese historical narratives
为什么呢
Why？
因为我们还是刚才讲的
Because, like we said earlier
又是“屁股决定脑袋”对吧
"where you sit shapes how you think，" right？
因为我们大家看课本的时候
When we read school textbooks
我们说我们是宋 对吧
we identify ourselves with the Song, right？
我们那个屁股是坐在宋那一边的
Our perspective sits on the Song side
那个辽和金天天来打我们
while the Liao and Jin keep attacking"us"
那能是好人吗
so how could they be good guys？
那是坏人
They must be the bad guys
对对
Exactly
但实际上不可以这样说
But actually, you can't put it that way
因为 是吧
because, right？
今天辽和金也都加入中国了
today the Liao and Jin are also part of China's history
属于中国这个大家庭中的一员
part of the broader Chinese family
那凭什么他们就比宋要低一等
So why should they be treated as inferior to the Song？
你这不可以吧 对吧
You can't really do that, right？
这人人平等
People are equal
中国这个就 56 个民族人人平等 对吧
China has 56 ethnic groups and they are all equal, right？
你也不能其实
So you can't really
但是呢 我们的历史还是存在对这个
But our historical narrative still has
辽金 妖魔化的这个倾向
a tendency to demonize the Liao and Jin
所以呢
So
就是没有分析人家
people don't analyze what they did well
那你想辽和金
Think about the Liao and Jin
人家那么牛
they were very formidable
人家把你宋朝打得哇哇乱叫
they gave the Song a very hard time
那人家总有自己的牛的地方嘛
so they must have had strengths of their own
那好就是吧
So
就是我刚讲“逐水草而居〞
back to what | called "following the water and grass"
"逐水草而居"
"Following the water and grass"
落到我们今天
Applied to us today
就你刚才讲的
and to what you just asked
也是回答你刚才讲的
this also answers
这个十年的这个问题
your question about the next ten years
是什么呢
What does it mean？
我觉得就是“逐水草而居〞
I think it means "follow the water and grass"
首先没有一个固定答案
First, there is no fixed answer
不是说我们就是定到哪
It's not that we pick one place
一住就一辈子
and stay there for life
就是就永远就不改
never changing
我们还是哪
Instead
我个人就是这个“逐水草而居〞
I personally follow a modern version
就新时代这个"逐水草而居"
of "following the water and grass"
我觉得就是哪个地方
Wherever
我能发挥最大作用
I can create the greatest value
我就去哪个地方
that'swhere lgo
就是我就从事哪个行业
and that's the industry l work in
当然我觉得某种程度上赚钱
Of course, to some extent, money
能不能赚足够多的钱就是一个标准嘛
and whether you can eam a lot is one measure
因为你赚多钱证明你在
because earning a lot shows that
这个地方的价值大呀
your value in that place is high
实际上 对不对
in practice,right？
实际上我觉得这个就是我自己
I think this is actually
判断的一个很重要的一个标准
one very important standard I use
就是说我们在一个
Can we create the greatest value
地方能创造最大价值
in a particular place？
钱当然是一个很重要的反馈
Money is an important feedback signal
所以从这个东西
So from that perspective
钱可以 你可以把钱看做数据
you can treat money as data
因为我能赚钱就证明我创造价值大
If l can make money, it proves I'm creating a lot of value
对对
Exactly
而且我能赚钱
And being able to make money
还不光是别人好像给我钱的意思
isn't merely about other people giving me money
我能赚钱证明我们这个
It also proves that
行业在全人类的里面
the industry itself has relatively high value
价值也比较大
for humanity as a whole
对吧 现在比如说
For example
同样的不是说任何歧视
and this isn't meant as discrimination
但是你说同样一个人在 AI 领域工作
if one person works in AI
一个企业在 AI 工作
and one company works in AI
当然就是比可能西贝更赚钱 对吧
it will probably make more money than Xibei, right？
就是西贝这两天都快倒闭了
Xibei has been struggling badly recently
那你说同样一个餐饮
If you compare the restaurant business
你说我做一个焖面
making braised noodles
我做一个这个西贝价值大
or running something like Xibei
还是我做 AI价值大
with building Al, which creates more value？
实话实说
Honestly
那肯定还是做 AI价值大嘛
Al clearly creates more value right now
所以 AI 的企业
Look at Al companies
你看梁文锋才做了几年
Liang Wenfeng has only been doing this for a few years
DeepSeek 马上 对吧
and DeepSeek has already, right？
境内这个上市
People are talking about domestic listings
这个都说要突破万亿美元 对吧
and valuations approaching a trillion U.S. dollars, right？
几万亿人民币 对吧 的公司
trillions of RMB, right？
那才做了几年呢 对吧
And it's only been a few years
那你说西贝可能做了
Meanwhile Xibei may have operated
十几年都要倒闭了 对吧
for more than a decade and is still struggling, right？
所以我就说同样的一个
So with the same amount of effort
你看这个行业中
look at how different industries
国家社会给的溢价
receive different premiums from society and the country
确实也是 AI大多了 对吧
Al clearly geis a much bigger one, right？
所以我觉得从这个角度而言
So from that perspective
我觉得就是“逐水草而居"
I come back to "following the water and grass"
就说我们哪能发挥最大价值
Wherever we can create the greatest value
我就去哪里
that's where Igo
就是我是这么一个理论
That's my theory
所以就是也不是说死守一个地方
It isn't about rigidly staying in one place
或者是搞一个地方
or committing to one location forever
对吧 就是这个
Right？
所以这也是为什么我觉得
That's also why I think
这个孙学黄毛薄肌理论很有用
Sunology, the Blond-Hair Theory，
也是机动性
They give you mobility
很灵活
and flexibility
我想问一下您的这个机动性指的
When you say mobility
个机动性指的 我想问一下您的这
机动性指的
When you say mobillity
我想问一下您的这个机动性指的
When you say mobility
是地理位置还是事业上的选择
do you mean geographic location, career choices
赛道的选择还是 两个都
or choice of industry—both？
还是两者都是
Both ofthem？
全部
All ofit
你看所以我就是为什么
That's why I don't
不建议大家买车买房
recommend that young people rush to buy cars or homes
当然结婚
And marriage, of course
对吧 也是一个点
is another factor, right？
你买房买车结婚都是要定下来
and getting married all tie you down
对吧 一旦买房买车结婚
Once you buy a home, a car, and get married
你就在那个地方定死了
you're basically fixed in that place
就
And
而且你自己有时候都没有这个意识
sometimes you don't even realize it yourself
比如说我给你举个最简单的例子
Let me give you the simplest example
比如说现在
Suppose
明天早晨 OpenAI 说"录取你 来吧
tomorrow morning OpenAl says， "You're hired. Come
来旧金山工作"
work in San Francisco"
你跟 OpenAI讲说“我在北京买了个房
and you tell OpenAI， "I bought a home in Beijing
能不能让我在北京工作？“
could you let me work from Bejing？"
那大概率 OpenAI 不同意
OpenAl probably won't agree
那你就失去这个机会了 对吧
and you lose that opportunity, right？
这个就是 我就讲的
That's what I mean by
是“逐水草而居〞
"following the water and grass"
那 OpenAI那有水草
If OpenAl is where the water and grass are
你就去旧金山就完了
just go to San Francisco
对吧 但如果我们这个
Right? But if
年轻人过早买房买车结婚
young people buy homes, cars, and get married too early
一下就给你定住
they can get locked in immediately
我都是见过很多很优秀的人才
I've seen many extremely talented people
我们想让他来这个大城市
we wanted to bring to a major city
他都得说
and they had to say
"我回去跟我老婆得商量"
"I need to discuss it with my wife"
后来都拒绝了我们的工作机会
In the end, they turned down our job offer
他说他来不了
They said they couldn't come
因为他老婆呢
because their wife
那个单位
had ajob back home
可能那只是个
maybe only
月薪5,000块钱的工作 但他在
paying 5,000 RMB a month, but
他老婆在他们家里面就是说了算
the wife had the final say in the family
然后他可能月薪拿4万
He might be offered 40,000 a month
地位没有他
but his standing in the family was lower than
薪拿 5,000的老婆地位高
his wife's, even though she earned 5,000
然后他老婆说
Then his wife would say
那我不可能辞职的
"I'm not quitting
这个工作我稳定
My job is stable
我要一直待
I'm staying here
你那边有月薪4 万的工作
Even if you have a 40,000-a-month job over there
你不许去
you're not allowed to go"
他就只能待在原地领2万
So he could only stay where he was earning 20,000
没办法
There was nothing he could do
所以我就讲的就是这个
That's why I say
确实我觉得就是机动性要强
you really need strong mobility
机动性要强
Strong mobility
所以我自己你看我很少就是
That's why I personally very rarely
投资于这个机动性不是太强的事业
invest in businesses that have low mobility
机动性一定要强
Mobility has to be strong
然后当然我就觉得这个
And I think
理论就是“逐水草而居”哪里有
this idea of "following the water and grass"
哪里能发挥最大价值
you can create the greatest value
哪里能让我们就是
wherever you can
取得最大回报 对吧
get the greatest return, right？
我觉得就是去哪里
That's where you go
这个就是我的这么一个理论吧
That's basically my theory
算是也是一个理论
You can call it another theory of mine
非常同意
1 completely agree
我觉得是很有参考价值的‘
I think i's very useful as a reference
就是因为真正理解这个理论之后
because once you really understand it
它不只是影响你的事业上的选择
it doesn't just affect your career choices
官也会影响你的投资上的选择
it also affects how you invest
比如说这个时候你就会选择
For example you'll choose
机动性强的资产
highly liquid, mobile assets
而不是把自己绑定在
rather than locking yourself
个被动的环境里面
into a static environment
而且我觉得 AI时代
And in the Al era
因为这个世界变得很快嘛
because the world is changing so fast
所以你一定要有灵活性对
you absolutely need flexibility
对你说得太对了
Exactly, you're absolutely right
灵活性是最重要的
Flexibility is the most important thing
灵活性是第一位的
It comes first
然后这个灵活性的前提条件下
And with that flexibility as the foundation
我觉得就是选择适合自己
I think you choose what suits you
符合自己的一个
what fits your own
一个东西
situation
其实我是这么这样一个理解
That's how I understand it
而且我觉得我们讲的
And l think what we call
孙学 黄毛 薄肌理论也是最好
Sunology, the Blond-Hair Theory，
这都是机动的 对吧
because they're all mobile, right？
你这个薄肌是穿在身上的
Your lean-muscle body goes with you
对穿在身上
You wear it on your body
系统更新是机动的
Your system upgrades are portable
手机里面的 AI也是机动的
and the Al on your phone is portable too
对 手机你不拎了就走了嘛 对不对
You just pick up your phone and go, right？
你手机里面装再多东西无所谓
ft doesn't matter
你一拎了就走了
you can still pick it up and leave
对吧 对吧
Right？
就是所以你看
So look
还有一点
there's another point
我觉得这个是也是
that I think
带有一些时代特色
also reflects the characteristics of this era
你看我也算是创业
I've started businesses too
很多这个也是这个有一些钱
and made some money
然后呢别人也经常有的人就问我
and people often ask me
说对吧
thingslike
就是说
they'll say
你孙宇晨
"Justin Sun
你花六百万美金买了一根香蕉
you spent six million dollars on a banana
为什么不花600 万美金买黄金
why not spend that six million dollars on gold
买这个钻石
diamonos
买珠宝呢 之
orjewelry？"
买珠宝呢
也是这个点
it's the same point
-也是这个点
就是这个香蕉
That banana
它是个概念艺术
is conceptual art
它是在网络上传播的
It spreads through the internet
它这个其实是个流动的IP
It's actually a liquid IP
我孙宇晨只要同意
as long as l, Justin Sun, agree
在全世界任何一个国博物馆
any museum anywhere in the world
明天就可以贴香蕉就可以展了
can tape up a banana tomorrow and exhibit it
对吧 它非常流动
Right? It's extremely mobile
非常这个
It's very
它是个概念艺术
It's conceptual art
但是这个什么不是
But things like
黄金珠宝
gold and jewelry
这些东西是死的
are physical and static
而且呢 这个你在一个地方定了
Once they're fixed in one place
带不走的
they're hard to move
对吧 就是
Right？
而且还容易被人偷了 对吧
And they can also be stolen, right？
就是
1mean
讲实话
honestly
你说这个怎么偷呢
how do you steal this concept？
这个
The
香蕉偷不了 对吧
banana can't really be stolen, right？
这个永远跟我的名字绑在一起
It will always be tied to my name
对它是一个数字资产的投资
Right, it's an investment in a digital asset
对对对
Exactly
但很多人不理解
But a lot of people don't understand that
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
这个跟咱们薄肌理论一样
It's just like our Lean-Muscle Theory
就是很前沿很新
It's very new and very cutting-edge
绝大多数今天的
Most people in China today
中国人接受不了这个理念太新了
can't accept the idea because it's too new
对 但是是对的
But it's right
这就是对的
It is right
但是是对的
It's right
然后呢而且我觉得是这样
And Ithink
我们作为布道者的价值也就在这里
where the value of being an evangelist comes from
如果我讲的全中国人都知道对的
every Chinese person already agreed were true
我天天讲1+1=2也没有意义对不对
if l spent all day saying 1+1=2, there'd be no point, right？
大家说你这讲 1+1=2
People would say， "You're just telling us 1+1=2
也没有什么新意
there's nothing new about that
也没有什么特别的
nothing special
为啥要讲1+1=2呢
why keep telling us 1+1=2？
我们都知道了 对吧
We already know that，" right？
也都这样认为
Everyone already believes it
所以我觉得就是这个理论
Sol think with a theory like this
小众其实好事
being niche is actually a good thing
小众说明是风口
Being niche means you're early
对吧
right？
小众证明是风口
Being niche means you're at the front of a wave
你讲的太对了
You're absolutely right
小众证明是风口
Being niche means you're at the front of a wave
你大众了你没有意义了嘛 对吧
Once it's mainstream, there's no edge left, right？
所以这个反而大家不接受
So the fact that people don't accept it
骂的多 好事
and even criticize it can be a good thing
因为我这给你传播呀
because it gives me something worth spreading
这传播正确理论
I'm spreading what | believe is the correct theory
这才体现出我的价值嘛 对不对
That's where my value comes from, right？
这个让我这个
Wow, that makes me
推广薄肌理论又变得更加坚定了
even more determined to promote Lean-Muscle Theory
行那我想话锋一转
Okay, let me change direction
换一个话题哈
and switch topics
就是说
So
如果让一个完全不懂
if someone who knows absolutely nothing about
Crypto 的人听这个播客
Crypto listened to this podcast
你会怎么介绍 TTRON 以及
how would you introduce TRON and
TRON 它解決了什么问题
what problem does TRON solve？
对我觉得我呢
Right. I think
其实我们做的事情很简单
what we're doing is actually very simple
这个 TRON Crypto
With TRON and Crypto
我们这个
we're
其实就是在做一件事
really just doing one thing
很简单的道理
The idea is simple
就是我们呢
We want
想把这个货币
to take money
翻译成机器以及翻译成
and translate it into something machines
互联网能听得懂的东西
and the internet can understand
其实跟我这个设立的
It's actually very similar to
这个“孙宇晨奖“很类似
the Justin Sun Prize | created
"孙宇晨奖"呢
With the Justin Sun Prize
我稍微讲讲
let me explain briefly
可能对数学感兴趣的人稍微说一下
for people who are interested in mathematics
就”孙宇晨奖"其实也很简单
The Justin Sun Prize is actually very simple
就是说这个
The idea is
“孙宇晨奖"就是把数学的证明
to take mathematical proofs
其实我们鼓励呢
and encourage people
要翻成这个 Lean 的这个形式化证明
to translate them into formal Lean proofs
什么叫 Lean 的形式化证明呢
What is a formal Lean proof？
就是说数学的理论和
It means mathematical theories and
所有这个东西的推导
all of their derivations
要让机器读得懂
need to be expressed in a form machines can read
这也是为
And that's also
当然也是为了铺垫 AI 时代
part of preparing for the Al era
就是这个 AI 也是
because Al itself
Al 只能读得懂机器读得懂的东西
can only understand things that machines can read
如果你这个东西
If something
不是机器读得懂的
isn't machine-readable
它就不懂你在说什么
Al doesn't understand what you're saying
讲实话实说
Honestly
就是那你说
someone might ask
那你说这个招商银行
what about China Merchants Bank
我用的招商银行
or the China Merchants Bank account | use
我平常用的这个 PayPal
or something like PayPal that | use every day？
是不是也是机器读得懂的
Aren't those also forms of money
货币的一种类型 它不是
that machines can read? Theyre not
这个招商银行这个和 PayPal
China Merchants Bank and PayPal
只是这个传统货币的数字化
are simply digitized forms of traditional money
它本身呢
They themselves
不是
are not
器本身读得懂的货币语言
a monetary language that machines inherently understand
二者还是有本质差别的
There is a fundamental difference
本质上取决于什么呢
What does that difference come down to？
就是于看这个
It comes down to
因为金融就有账本
the ledger, because finance relies on ledgers
这个账本的管理
How is that ledger managed？
它是中心化的服务器管理
Is it managed by centralized servers
还是去中心化的服务器管理
or decentralized servers？
它只有在去中心化的
Only when the ledger is managed
服务器管理下面这个账本
on decentralized servers
因为它是完全按照加密
and operates entirely through cryptography
密码学数学的方式在运作 所以呢
and mathematics
机器一下就能明白你在干什么
can a machine immediately understand what's happening
这也为什么就是这个 TRON
That's why
我们这比特币
Bitcoin and TRON
这些都是就是机器一下就能懂的
languages machines can understand immediately
概念语言以及它所有的 API
and all of their APIs
我们天然跟 API
naturally work with APIs
跟这些就是支付方式
and with different payment
就可以完美融合
methods almost seamlessly
就是说我们呢
So what we're doing
是将人类这个过去这个
is taking the ancient concept of money
几千年这个古老的这个货币 对吧
that humanity has used for thousands of years, right？
货币是人类发明的一种
Money is an invention humans created
金融上一个交流的一个工具
as a financial tool for exchange
把它翻译成
and translating it into
Al 和机器能听得懂的语言
a language Al and machines can understand
这个其实就是区块链
That's really what blockchain
和 Crypto 在做的事
and Crypto are doing
就是当然我知道
Ofcourse, 1know
大家很多就不了解的人
many people who don't understand it
天天就喊这个"割韭菜"
keep yelling about "harvesting retail investors"
对吧 就喊这些
right? That's all they say
东西 对吧
right？
当然就跟我觉得是你练薄肌
when you talk about building lean muscle
其实你是讲的是健康
you're really talking about health
讲的是这个 但是呢
but
就是我们人
people
很喜欢妖魔化
love to demonize things
妖魔化你的一个很重要的这个点呢
And a key way they demonize you
就是首先把你这个其实
is by taking what is actually
很正当的一个动机呢
a legitimate motivation
给它自私自利化
and reframing it as selfish
对吧 就比如说
For example
"你练这个薄肌是为了泡妞“对吧
"You're building lean muscle just to pick up girls，" right？
好像你是特别的投机取巧
As if you're being opportunistic
特别这个为了泡妞
and doing all of it just to pick up girls
一个非常猥琐的这个想法 对吧
like it's some sleazy motive, right？
就是说决定了你这个你
They decide
就是你的这个动机 对吧
what your motive must be, right？
当然这个我觉得也是
I think that's
一个错误的一种归因
a mistaken attribution
但很多人容易被这个东西骗
but a lot of people fall for it
因为他就是不看你做了什么
because instead of looking at what you actually did
你说 我练了薄肌是对我身体好
"I'm building lean muscle because it's good for my body"
他不说
they ignore that
讲前面一个你根本没法解释的东西
and focus on something you can't really disprove
就是说"你是为了泡妞才练的"
They say， "You're only doing it to pick up girls"
那你说你
Then how are you supposed to
我为什么要练薄肌这个东西
prove why you're building lean muscle？
当然我们可以讲这个理论讲这个
We can explain our theory
但是其实很难解释
but motivations are hard to prove
别人也很难证伪和证实
Other people can't really falsify or verify them either
因为这个动机它是个主观的嘛 对吧
because motivation is subjective, right？
那说 区块链
With blockchain
他们就归因就说"割韭菜"
people make the same attribution and call it
只要做区块链
If you work in blockchain
那你就是割韭菜 对吧
they say that's what you're doing, right？
你就割韭菜 割韭菜的意思就是说
By "harvesting retail investors" they mean
你把一个没价值东西就是
selling something with no value
用很高的价格卖给别人
to other people at a very high price
讲白了 对吧
That's the plain meaning, right？
然后给大家留下
and leaving everyone else
一个没有价值的东西 对吧
with something worthless, right？
当然他是说你前面你的动机
So they're saying your motive from the start
你就是为了干这件事
was simply to do that
但就不讲这个技术和这个
while ignoring the technology itself
东西对人类带来的这个好处了 对吧
and the benefits it can bring humanity, right？
他就不讲 对吧
They don't talk about that
所以我觉得呢
Sol think
就是这个但是呢
in reality
其实我们在做的事情跟 AI
what we're doing here is the same kind of thing as AI
跟这都是一个事
It's all part of the same process
我觉得就是把所有东西
We're taking everything
包括我设立这个"孙宇晨奖"
including with the Justin Sun Prize
就说把所有的鼓励
and encouraging people
把数学也是翻译成
to translate mathematics into
机器读得懂的语言
machine-readable language
像比如说我跟你讲
For example, let me tell you
就是现在这个
in this
我们这人类时代
era we're entering
其实很面临一个东西
humanity faces a real issue
就是说如果有一个
If there's something
东西机器没有读到
that machines haven't read
那我告诉你
then I'm telling you
这个人或者这件事就毫无价值
that person or that thing effectively
就比如说我举个比较震撼的例子
Let me give a striking example
就前一段时间他们在
Recently people have been working on
做这个 费马大定律
formalizing Fermat's Last Theorem
包括未来要做这个
and in the future they'll work on
庞加莱猜想 的这个形式化
formalizing the Poincare conjecture
其实费马定律呢
Fermat's theorem
庞加莱猜想呢
and the Poincare conjecture
都已经被人类已经证明了
have already been proved by humans
但现在面临一个问题是
But nowthere's a new problem
这个证明机器读不懂
machines can't read those proofs directly
-枧器如果读不懂
I machines canlt read them
机器如果读不懂
I machines can't read them
这个东西就没有办法
then that knowledge can't
被全世界的计算机
be absorbed by computers
被AI吸收
and Al around the world
那么这一个东西就没有价值
and in that sense it loses much of its machine-era value
证了也白证
The proof can't fully propagate
对吧 因为你挣出来了
Right? Because even if you proved it
你全世界你怎么挣的
how did you prove it？
这个思路几个人知道
How many people know the reasoning？
没有人知道
Hardly anyone
你必须把它形式化了传到 AI
You have to formalize it and feed it into AI
让计算机读懂了
so computers can understand it
才算是消化
before it is truly digested
对吧 就是这么一个理念
That's the idea
就是说你如果没有这些东西
If you don't do that
机器没读懂
and machines haven't understood it
其实人类这些发明就没有意义
can't fully carry forward into the machine era
所以我们人类现在处于一个就是
So humanity is currently
从人类向机器的这么一个过渡
in a transition from humans toward machines
从碳基向硅基的这么一个过渡
from carbon-based to silicon-based systems
所以在这个中间你
And in the middle of that transition
充当一个翻译官很关键
being a translator is extremely important
对吧 就是说
Right？
这个机器要读懂
Machines need to understand
你把数学要翻译给机器
so you translate mathematics for machines
你要把货币翻译给机器
you translate money for machines
人类的书
human books
所有这些发明都要翻译给机器
and all our inventions need to be translated for machines
机器懂了就可以上路了
Once machines understand them, they can move forward
所以您的意思就是
Sowhat you're saying is
现在的这个金融系统和‘
our curent financial system and
货币系统它其实是一个就还没有
monetary system still haven't
还没有进行升级和更新的‘
been upgraded and updated
而 Crypto 这门技术就是把这个
and Crypto is the technology that takes
传统的这样一个货币系统
that traditional monetary system
进化到 AI能够读懂
and evolves it into something Al can understand
能够参与
participate in
并且能够去之间交易
and transact through
的这样的一个工具
as a new kind of tool
你说得太对了
Yes, exactly
你想想现在的 SWIFT system
Think about today's SWIFT system
我们跟 SWIFT system 做的是一个事
We're ultimately doing the samejob as SWIFT
就是把钱其实发送到
moving money
全世界的任何一个角落 对吧
to any corner of the world, right？
可以是美元
It can be dollars
可以任何东西
or anything else
SWIFT system 一九五几年发明的
The SWIFT system was invented in the postwar era
二战后用的这个盟军的
using communications infrastructure
这个电报系统做的
that came out of wartime telegraph systems
那个时代没有计算机
That was an era without modern computers
那个时代没有 AI
and without AI
你也不可能指望它跟 AI 和
So you can't expect that old system
计算机做什么兼容嘛
to be natively compatible with Al and computers
对吧 所以是个完全落后的线下的
It's a completely outdated, offline
沉重的这么一个系统
heavyweight system
金融系统
a financial system
我们做的绝对是对的
What we're doing is absolutely the right direction
因为我们把它翻译成机器能读懂的
because we're translating it into a form machines can read
未来没有
In the future
如果没有人把你的东西翻译成机器
if no one translates what you do for machines
你的人生本身就没有任何价值
may become invisible to that ecosystem
这个非常有深度
That's very deep
这个有一点
And there's another point
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
就是这个还有一点
another thing
也是我特别感慨的
I feel very strongly about
就是说现在
Today
任何东西
anything
就是我们一定要把它翻译
we create needs to be translated
放到互联网上
and put on the internet
让它什么
so that itcan
成为 AI的语料
become part of Al's training corpus
成为 AI 的语料非常关键
Becoming part of Al's corpus is extremely important
因为如果一个东西
because if something
未来没有成为 AI的语料
never becomes part of Al's corpus in the future
这个东西就是从来就没有发生过
it's as if that thing never happened
就比如说
For example
我们可以讲500年前
imagine 500 years ago
比如说这里有一个国家有5000万人
there was a country with 50 million people
然后这5000万人如果没有历史记录
and those 50 million people left no historical record
没有这个语料记录
no corpus or textual record
未来没有上着 AI
and nothing ever made it into Al in the future
这个国家人全灭亡了
If that country's people all disappeared
其实他们在地球上
then in a sense, on Earth
就从来没有存在过
it would be as if they had never existed
因为没有人知道他们的存在
because nobody would know they existed
因为 AI没有读到这个记录
because Al never saw any record of them
是吧 那你也不能怪 AI
Right? And you can't blame AI
因为 AI 说你没喂给我
because Al would say， "You never fed it to me"
所以就是所有东西
So everything
就是上网现在很关键
needs to get online now.That's critical
就是一定要让它上网
You have to put it online
让AI读到这个语料
sO Al can read that corpus
就是进入人类
That's how it gets a chance to enter
下一个文明的一个机会
the next stage of human civilization
如果 AI没有读到你的语料
If Al never reads your material
你相当于就白费了
then in a sense it was wasted
所以这个就是
So that's
你知道就是
whatImean
我觉得当然还有一些很多工程
There are many projects
我觉得都很有意义
I think would be very meaningful
当然这个未来都可以做
and could be done in the future
就比如说把中国的历史
For example, Chinese history
中国的文字
Chinese writing
中国的诗歌
Chinese poetry
都要给它数字化
should all be digitized
给它全部免费传到网上
and uploaded online for free
就包括
Including
当然我相信这个说不定 DeepSeek
I'm sure companies like DeepSeek
这些公司就已经在做了
may already be doing this
对吧 字节跳动已经在做了
ByteDance may already be doing it too, right？
我觉得要把中国的历史
I think Chinese history
中国的文化
Chinese culture
中国图书馆所有的书
and every book in Chinese libraries
你得数字化了
should be digitized
得传到网上
and put online
因为你不传到网上
because if you don't put it online
没有做数字化
and don't digitize it
就相当于不存在
it's almost as if it doesn't exist
就类似于我们这段话
It's like this conversation we're having
如果我们没有进行一个录制
If we didn't record it
发到网上的话
and upload it online
其实这段话就没有发生
then in a sense this conversation never happened
就对这个社会没有价值
and creates no lasting value for society
对 如果你是在私底下说的
Right. If you only say it privately
你没有录制
without recording it
你没有说
without publishing it
就这个很有很有可能
there's a very real chance
你的这个灵光一闪就过去了
that a flash of insight simply disappears
对吧 就是我举个
Right? Let me give
再举个例子
another example
就是从那个科学家
From the individual scientist's perspective
个人角度讲可能是个悲剧
it may have been a tragedy
但是我觉得对人人类来讲是件好事
I think it was a good thing
对吧 还是纽约大学那个教授的例子
I'm talking about that NYU professor example again
纽约大学那个教授呢
That NYU professor
自己有个思路
had an idea of his own
结果他告诉 OpenAI 了
and told OpenAl about it
确实他这个主意被 OpenAI偷了
In a sense, OpenAl took that idea
OpenAI 自己给破解了
and solved the problem itself
但是从人类的角度
But from humanity's perspective
人类就锁定了这个
humanity then locked in a solution to the NS
NS方程的这个解 对吧
equation, right？
你千万别小看这个事
Don't underestimate how important that is
你知道费马大定律
You know Fermat's Last Theorem
就是费马提出的时候
When Fermat proposed it
费马就说我能解出来
he said he could prove it
这个地方这个证明太小
but the margin was too small
没有草稿纸
and he didn't have enough space
我写不下
to write the proof down
结果呢 有可能他能证出来
Maybe he really could prove it
他也知道这个思路
and knew the core idea
但他就没有分享给人类
but he never shared it with humanity
结果后面花了人类 100 多年
Then humanity spent more than a hundred years
才找到下一个能证出来的人
before finding someone else who could prove it
你知道吧
You know？
因为费马没时间
Because Fermat didn't write it down
你说但凡有点时间
If he'd had just a little more time
我告诉你
I'm telling you
如果是 AI时代
in the Al era
费马直接把这个思路跟那个 AI 哪怕
Fermat could simply have told the idea to AI
语音对话就好了
even through a voice conversation
记录下来
and recorded it
语音讲两句
Just say a few sentences out loud
AI要记住了
Al would remember it
Al要记住了
Alwould remember it
发给其他数学家
and pass it to other mathematicians
那别人有可能能证出来
who might be able to complete the proof
而他早多多 100年早就证出来了
Then it could have been proved more than a century earlier
你就跟今天这个大家抢的这个速度
Just like the speed of collaboration today
你说出来这思路两天给你证出来
Once you share an idea, someone may prove it in two days
所以给人类的进度
So for humanity's progress
对于本人
even if for the individual
有可能是个悲剧
it might feel tragic
但是在全人类给你
for humanity as a whole
进度条给你拖快了呀 对不对
you've moved the progress bar forward faster, right？
所以我们如果屁股
So if our perspective
大家是站在全人类角度
is the perspective of all humanity
欢迎 AI 多剽窃一点这个
we should welcome Al absorbing more
这个 思路 对吧
useful ideas, right？
哈哈哈 对吧
Right
那自媒体是不是也是风口呢
So is independent media also a major opportunity？
类似于你把信息给它互联网化了
It's similar—you put information onto the internet
数字化了
and digitize it
绝对是 绝对是
Absolutely, absolutely
我觉得自媒体时代
I think the age of independent media
就是说这个媒体时代
or this new media era
为什么叫自媒体
why do we call it independent media？
以前只有媒体才能说
In the past, only media organizations could speak
你有想法
You could have ideas
你自己不能表达
but couldn't express them publicly yourself
对吧 这个媒体
Right? A media outlet
那就是一个媒体里面的几个人
was just a handful of people
总编和记者定的
the editor-in-chief and reporters making decisions
就你知道那个
You know
不知道你在有没有在媒体工作过
I don't know whether you ve ever worked in media
我在媒体工作过
I have
媒体就是一个很简单一个结构
The structure is actually very simple
是什么呢
What is it？
主编定选题
The editor-in-chief chooses the topics
记者做执行
and reporters execute
所以基本是这个主编自己的思维
So basically the editor-in-chief's own thinking
就决定所有人怎么想
determines what everyone covers
因为主编定死了
because the editor-in-chief locks it in
你说但这个其实是错误的
But that's actually flawed
你说这个主编又不是神仙
The editor-in-chief isn't some all-knowing authority
主编所有东西就一定是对的吗
Is everything the editor-in-chief thinks necessarily right？
这就中心化的
That's centralized
对中心化
Exactly, centralized
你其实原则上应该允许自媒体
In principle, you should allow independent creators
允许所有人发言
and allow everyone to speak
因为所有人发言才
because when everyone can speak, you're more likely
大概率能够接近真理嘛
to get closer to the truth
对吧 每个人都发言
Everyone gets to speak, right？
对吧 每个人都表达自己的观点
Everyone expresses their own views
对吧 都辩论
and debates them
但以前没有自媒体时代
Before the independent-media era
那不行了
that wasn't possible
不可以给你说
You couldn't say what you wanted
对吧 不可以给你说
Right? You couldn't speak directly
就是我觉得自媒体时代很重要
the independent-media era is so important
就是给了大家一个什么
It gives
所有人都可以发言的机会
everyone a chance to speak
所以这就是为什么你看这个抖音
That's why platforms like Douyin
YouTube 对吧 推特这些就兴起了
YouTube and Twitter rose, right？
因为这些都上面大家都可以发言
Because everyone can speak on them
那么大概率
And with that broad participation
这个事上面
on many issues
这些平台产出的
the views that emerge from
观点就大概率是对的
these platforms have a better chance of being right
因为它是个市场竞争的结果
because there is market competition
你别的你没有市场竞争
Without that competition
你就很有可能误导
you can easily mislead people
you camesit 線有可熊區晚來店磨參
"Where you sit shapes how you think
很有可能屁股决定脑袋
you can easily fall into
Where you sit shapes how you think
很有可能就是大家没有充分思考
and people may not think things through fully
然后所有人都被误导了
then everyone gets misled
因为他这个报纸
because once a newspaper
媒体一旦说出来
or media outlet says something
那所有人都可能被这个东西误导
a huge number of people can be influenced by it
非常同意
I completely agree
这就是为什么你看
That's exactly why
这就是》什么你看
这就是狗什么你看
That's exactly why
这就是为什么你看
现在很多人他看新闻的信息来源
a lot of people today no longer get their news
都不再是传统的那些
mainly from traditional outlets
比如说 BBC
Iike the BBC
那些电视台
or talevision networks
而是上Twitter 这种网站
but from sites like Twitter
这样有一个更加去中心化的一个
where discussion is more decentralized
盲论结论
and condusions emerge more organically
对 是这个道理
Exactly
就更接近真理
It can get closer to the truth
是这个道理
That's the idea
绝对是绝对是
Absolutely
那我想再聊一下
I'd like to talk about one more thing
就是因为刚 Crypto 讲得比较深嘛
We went pretty deep on Crypto just now
您说是把货币翻译成
You said it translates money into
机器能听懂的语言
a language machines can understand
那这个比如说对于
For ordinary people
我们普通人的生活
in everyday life
那您觉得 Crypto 真正大规模进入
what do you think will be the killer application
我们每一个人生活的这样的
that brings Crypto into
一个杀手级应用会是什么
everyone's daily life at scale？
其实现在已经有不少杀手级应用了
There are already quite a few killer applications
就是这个把这个钱
One is moving money
在全世界范围内发来发去
around the world
其实我们这个波场现在每天
On TRON, for example, we now process
这个交易量就是几百亿美元了
tens of billions of dollars in transaction volume every day
一年可能发送总量都是几个万亿了
and several trillion dollars in total volume over a year
就其实已经都赶上 SWIFT 了
We're already in the same broad range as SWIFT
但是呢 就是还是这个慢
But adoption still takes time
得慢慢来嘛
It has to happen gradually
你就跟这个AI 现在很多人 对吧
It's like Al—now a lot of people
大家都开始大规模采用了
are adopting it at scale
但是还是有很多人没有使用
but many people still don't use it
讲白了就是
Simply put
但是我觉得呢
Ithink
这个是难以阻挡的一个趋势
this is an unstoppable trend
就是未来就是 对吧
In the future
因为 AI 更高效 AI
because Al is more efficient
更这个而且 AI是更大
and Al operates at a larger scale
这个包括这个 Crypto 是更接近终局的
and Crypto is closer to the end-state infrastructure
对吧 你说
right？
比如说最简单一个
Take the simplest
打一个比方
example
你说100年后大家还会有人用纸币吗
A hundred years from now, will anyone still use paper
cash？
不会有人用了
No one will
对已经没人用了
By then, nobody will
就是这个纸币就已经就是不会了
Paper money will essentially be gone
这个数字货币是
Digital money
数字化的货币是绝对是
digitized currency is absolutely
这个整个社会的
where society as a whole
一个未来的方向嘛 对吧
is heading, right？
就是所以从这个角度来讲
So from that perspective
我觉得就是包括 AI 的使用
I think the same applies to using AI
这些 对吧
and these technologies, right？
就是现在都是
Today
就是我们就是这个理论就是讲
another way we describe this idea is
我们另外一个讲法就叫可编程货币
"programmable money"
对吧 就是说这个 Crypto 是可编程货币
Crypto is programmable money, right？
那这个货币可编程不就是这个
If money is programmable
不还是我刚才讲的这个
isn't that exactly what | was saying earlier？
翻译成 AI能听得懂的语言 对吧
You're translating it into a language Al can understand
就把货币翻译成 AI懂懂的语言
translating money into an Al-readable language
所以随着 Al的普及
So as Al becomes more widespread
随着这个东西
this whole process
这些就是我觉得货币
of digitizing money
的数字化就是 Crypto 这个是
through Crypto
是难以阻挡的嘛
is very hard to stop
因为它就是一个更新更高级的科技
because it's a newer, more advanced technology
对吧 你就跟人去
Right? Trying to use
你的血肉之躯去抵抗 AI
your flesh-and=blood body to resist AI
没有任何意义
makes no sense
因为这个 AI它
because AI
这个是一个技术潮流
is a technological wave
它没有办法被改变的
and you can't simply reverse it
我想给就是不太理解这个
For viewers who don't really understand
TRON 做的这件事情的观众稍微讲一下
what TRON does, let me explain briefly
就是 TRON 其实
You can think of TRON
你可以理解为是一个
as
修了一个基础设施
infrastructure
修了一个高速公路
like building a highway
然后所有的车来来往往
All the cars traveling back and forth
都是在TRON这条链上发生
are transactions happening on the TRON chain
然后 TRON 的话就是赚一个这个高速费
and TRON earns the equivalent of highway tolls
所以是一个现金流的生意
so it's a cash-flow business
对是的
Yes, exactly
好了解
Got it
可以这么理解吧
That's a fair way to understand it, right？
对对
Exactly
那大部分普通人生活的杀手级应用
So for ordinary people's lives, the killer application
可能就是这种稳定币之间的支付
may be stablecoin payments
以及人和 AI之间的支付
payments between humans and AI
或者说AI 智能体之间的支付
or payments between Al agents
对AI和AI 之间的支付
Right, Al-to-Al payments
我觉得这个前景是很大的
I think the potential there is enormous
对我同意
lagree
我也认为这是一定会发生的
I also think it's definitely going to happen
是不可逆的趋势
It's an irreversible trend
对因为人有了更效
Because once people have
更高效率的工具之后
more efficient tools
是不可能回到更低效率工具的
they don't go back to less efficient ones
就比如说有了网购之后
For example, once online shopping exists
那就它就是
then
你不可能把网购给
you can't really reverse
给逆这件事情
the shift to online shopping
就网购一定会用越用越多
Online shopping will only be used more and more
对 你说的非常对
Exactly, you're absolutely right
一 所以就是马云
So Jack Ma
先来了
came along
把中国网购做得很快
and helped China move quickly into online commerce
是件好事 对吧
That was a good thing, right？
这个所以我觉得
Sol think
就是还是跟前面这个
this goes back to
我们刚才讲的
what we were saying earlier
这个技术趋势一旦形成
Once a technological trend forms
我们要拥抱它
we need to embrace it
而不能说是我们
rather than trying
把这个技术挡在外面 对吧
to block it out, right？
这个 AI既然来了
Al is already here
我们拥抱它 拥抱它
so embrace it
适应它 对吧
and adapt to it, right？
而不要说是我要把 AI控制住
Don't say. "| want to contain AI
不让AI发展
and stop Al from developing"
这个肯定是错误的
That's clearly the wrong response
因为我们要
because we need to
把这个要适应它
adapt to it
这个要适应它
We need to adapt
当然这个可能从我们
Of course, from the perspective of
年轻人角度来讲比较容易
younger people, that's easier
因为我们年轻嘛 对吧
because we're young, right？
2-40 岁你吸收新鲜
People between roughly 20 and 40 absorb new things
这个速度快
and new ideas faster
对对对
Exactly
你要六七十了
Once you're in your sixties or seventies
你不愿意
you may be less willing
改变因为你这屁股决定脑袋嘛 对吧
because "where you sit shapes how you think" right？
但是我们年轻人
for younger people
我觉得大家如果是2-40岁这个区间的
if you're in that 20-to-40 age range
那更是
then even more so
我要
you should
先吸收 先改变
absorb and adapt first
我觉得就是这么一个理念
That's howI see it
对因为这个东西它
Because this kind of change
它不需要你去接不接受
doesn't require your permission
它一定会发生
It's going to happen
所以如果你不参与的话
If you don't participate
你就会下车
youll be left behind
所以这不是一个可
It's not really optional in that sense
就你不接受
Even if you don't accept it
它也历史还是会进程会推进
history and technology will keep moving forward
不管你上不上车
whether you get on board or not
所以那你作沩个人最大利益的话
So if you're acting in your own best interest
你就是应该上车
you should get on board
就是这么简单 对吧
It's thatsimple, right？
跟其练薄肌也是一个思路
It's the same logiG as buiding lean muscle
那您就是我们都是认
So we both understand
就是我们能理解这个 Crypto 是趋势嘛
that Crypto is a trend
那您个人的
In your own
比如说资产配置投资的话
asset allocation and investing
也会偏向这种 Crypto 类的东西嘛因为
do you also lean heavily toward Crypto-related assets？
对我是全部 Crypto 化
Yes, I've gone completely Crypto
就是
Basically
而且我很早
and I did it very early
我可能2012年以后就全部是 Crypto 化了
After around 2012, almost everything for me was Crypto
所以大家也
So
当然有些人可能眼红我赚了很多钱
some people may envy how much money I made
但是我觉得也没必要眼红
but l don't think there's any need to envy it
其实我当时不是为了赚钱
because at the time | wasn't doing it to make money
我当时就是跟薄肌 练薄肌一样
It was like building lean muscle
我只是为了系统升级
I was just upgrading my system
做自己相信的事情
doing what / believed in
做认知内的事情
and acting within my own understanding
对一做自己相信的事情
First, do what you believe in
第二我是一个就是有点像手机嘛
Second, I'm a bit like a phone
那更新了新版本
when a new version comes out
我就第一波更新
I want to update in the first wave
你知道吧
You know？
iPhone 出了我第一波买的人
When a new iPhone comes out, I'm an early buyer
我当时 比如说
So imagine
后面比如说我跟 iPhone
I'm one of the first people
我第一个买的人
to buy aniPhone
后面 iPhone 涨到 100万美金一个
and later iPhones somehow rise to a million dollars each
你能说我是为了赚钱买iPhone 的吗
could you say I bought the iPhone just to make money？
那不是 我买 iPhone
No.I bought the iPhone
买 Apple 的唯一原因是因为
or Apple products because
我觉得这个东西代表未来
I thought they represented the future
对吧 甚至都不是为了赚钱 对吧
It wasn't primarily about making money, right？
就是因为我觉得这个东西新
I thought the technology was new
我就先更新了
sol upgraded early
我当时就觉得我是最早觉得
I was also among the earliest to think
买房买车
that buying a house or car
什么这东西没什么意义
didn't mean that much to me
因为他们这个旧时代的资产
because those are assets of the old era
这些东西是不会被翻译给机器的
and they don't translate naturally
你说车房能翻译给机器吗
Can a house or car be translated for a machine？
机器根本可听不懂
A machine can't inherently understand
什么东西能被翻译给机器
What can be translated directly for machines？
数字货币能被翻译给机器
Digital currency can
比特币 对吧
Bitcoin, right？
包括我后来做的这个波场
And later TRON, which I built
这些能给翻译去给机器
These can be expressed directly to machines
所以呢 我就第一个更新了这个系统
Sol was among the first to upgrade that part of my system
对吧 我第一个更新系统
I updated early
版本不能回滚
Versions can't go backward
只能往前更新 对吧
you can only keep updating, right？
你说我更新系统 你说
If a system update comes out and you say
"我就扛着不更新"
"I'm refusing to update"
那你扛着不更新
then if you keep refusing
你的后面就是越来越多
more and more things later
东西就不支持你这个东西了
will stop supporting your old version
因为人家就只支持这个新版本的了
because everyone else supports only the new version
对吧 因为其他人也不是傻子
and other people aren't foolish either, right？
所以呢早更新
So update early
早更早超生 对吧
the earlier, the better, right？
所以我当时2012年我就全给
That's why around 20121 moved
更成 Crypto 了
almost everything into Crypto
我就那时候我就更新
Iupgraded at that time
当然那个时候我更新的时候
Of course, when I did
当然就买入价格低吧 对对对
my entry prices were low
因为它这个涉及到一个买入成本
because timing affects your acquisition cost
当然这个其实哪个地方
But every area
都涉及到买入成本
has an acquisition cost
你练薄肌不涉及到买入成本吗
Does building lean muscle not have an acquisition cost？
你70岁再练来不及了呀 对吧
If you wait until you're 70, it's too late, right？
肯定是早买早好嘛 对吧
The earlier you start, the better
所以我觉得就是
Sol think
就是这么一个理论
that's the theory
就我们其实 对吧
Basically
就是早点说
starting earlier
其实不是为了赚钱
isn't necessarily about making money
就像大家想的这个
or approaching things
好像很功利的角度 对吧
from a purely utilitarian angle, right？
其实哪怕就趋势代表未来的角度
Even just from the perspective of following the future
你也应该早点更新 对不对
you should update earlier, right？
就所以 我觉得
Solthink
N
就是包括你看我也是
for example,was also
第一波喊多存存储的人 对吧
among the first to say we should invest heavily in storage
因为那个时候这个
because back then
这个AI嘛
Al
需要用存储
needed storage
永远缺存储对
and storage capacity is always needed
存储 那个时候我为什么喊多
Why was l bullish on storage then？
就是因为也是这个 AI
Because of AI
AI 要用 对吧
Al needs it,right？
就是很多人
A lot of people
觉得这个是不是
thought maybe
就是“孙宇晨自己要做存储了就喊单"
because he wanted to build a storage business
对吧 就是这个骗我们
that Iwas trying to fool people
割又要割韭菜 对吧
or "harvest retail investors" again, right？
叉要割韭菜
"Harvest retail investors" again
就是没有要割韭菜
But that wasn't the point
问题是人家这个趋势就是往那走
The point is the trend itself was going that direction
对不对 你也没有必要硬刚嘛 对不对
Right? There's no need to fight the trend head-on
所以我觉得我的这个角度就说
So from my perspective
这个我们其实做很多东西
we do many things
的原因并不是因为它好像
not simply because
就赚钱多就是副产品
they make money. Making money is a by-product
副产品 因为你在做对的事情
a by-product of doing the right thing
对 你讲的很对
Yeah, youire absolutely right
就为什么赚钱多
Whny dloes it maka more moneyg
因为社会对他的评价高
Because society values it more highly
社会为什么对他评价高
And why does society value it more highly？
随着时间推移
As time goes on
是因为他在社会中
it's because in society
扮演的角色越来越重要
it plays an increasingly important role
太同意了 太同意了
I totally agree, totally agree
而且市场会用脚投票嘛
And the market votes with its feet
对 市场会用脚投票 对吧
Right the market votes with its feet, right？
就是包括我这个风波发生之后
Even after this whole controversy around me
我觉得就挺有意思
I found something pretty interesting
中国很多人呢就是
A lot of people in China
试图去扒我孙宇晨的黑历史
tried to dig up dirt from my past
就说我“孙宇晨是个坏人”
and say. "Justin Sun is a bad person"
当然编造了很多
Of course, they made up a lot of things
从来没有发生的事情
that never happened
比如说什么"我看牙医不给钱
Like， "l went to the dentist and didn't pay
我又去哪家商店买东西不给钱"
or went to some store and didn't pay"
那不给钱这不小偷嘛
If l didn't pay, wouldn't that make me a thief？
那你直接报警
Then just call the police
把我抓起来不就完了嘛 对吧
and have me arrested, right？
这是首先是第一点 对吧
That's the first point, right？
第二呢
Second
他们给我编了很多就是很无厘头的
They made up a lot of absurd stories
就是我不给钱
about me not paying
到处赖账的一些东西 试图呢
or owing money everywhere, trying to
试图好像证明我孙宇晨是个坏人
make it look like Justin Sun is a bad person
所以比如说我做的事也是坏的
So, for example, what l do must also be bad
或者我挣了钱也是坏的
or the money I make must also be bad
这个其实没有任何意义 对吧
That doesn't really mean anything, right？
你就比如说
For example
比如说
for example
举个例子
Let me give you an example
我们最近一个健身博主 对吧
Take a fitness influencer, right？
宣扬要健身
He advocates working out
那我们就去
and then people go
拼命去爆他乱搞的新闻
all out digging up stories about his messy relationships
说他什么”出轨 50个女的"对吧
saying things like， "He cheated with 50 women" right？
证明他是个坏人
to prove he's a bad person
不是 这也没什么意义
But that doesn't mean anything either
那举个例子
For example
就哪怕他出轨了 50个女人
even if he cheated with 50women
是个坏人
and is a bad person
那就能证明练肌肉这个事是
does that prove that building muscle
坏的吗 或大家就别练肌肉了 对不对
is bad, or that everyone should stop training? No, right？
这个逻辑在哪呢 对不对
Where's the logic in that？
因为人家练肌肉
Because training muscle
这件事是健康决定的
is about health
人家健康 25 ％是肌肉
Muscle accounts for 25% of health
你没肌肉 肌无力
Without muscle, you get muscle weakness
你就会躺床上
and you end up lying in bed
就爬不起来了
unable to get up
对不对
Right？
这个事又不是那个肌肉博主定的说
It's not like that fitness influencer invented this idea
对吧 大家必须练薄肌
and said everyone has to train for a lean-muscular body
你说是这道理吧
You see whatI mean？
你说我孙宇晨
Take me, Justin Sun
那能做这个TRON
being able to do this kind of thing
包括做这个 Crypto 能成功的核心原因
including succeeding in Crypto
其实跟我也没有太大关系
actually doesn't have that much to do with me personally
你就说我看牙医不给钱
Say l went to the dentist and didn't pay
那大家后面就不用数字货币了吗
everyone should stop using digital currency？
对对对 这是一个逻辑上的错误
Right, exactly. That's a logical error
不具有同一个
They're not the same thing
对逻辑上的错误
Right, it's a logical error
就是你不要管动机
Don't focus on someone's motive
你要看他的对错
Look at whether what they said is right or wrong
你不要管他
Don't focus on the person
动机不重要
The motive isn't important
你如果要判断
If you're going to judge something
你就得去百分百的理智‘
you need to be 100% rational
那就是看这个事情是不对的
and look at whether the thing itself is right or wrong
而不是他为什么说
not why that person said it
你说太对了
You're absolurtely right
就很多人
A lot of people
就是当然不排除为了蹭热度
and of course some may just be chasing attention
都采用这个逻辑
use tissame loga/
前两天我不是看这个
The other day I was watching this
这个 马斯克 出了
There was something about Elon Musk
一个纪录片叫”马斯克的"
a docu mentanyabouit Musk
是个好莱坞的导演要黑他
made by a Hollywood director trying to attack him
要黑他
Trying to smear him
T⑦
拍了一个
They made afilm
就也是采访了他一堆前女友什么的
and interviewed a bunch of his ex-girlfriends and so on
然后呢就那个前女友也说
Then one of his ex-girlfriends said
"马斯克 是个坏人
"Wow, Elon Musk is a bad person
他做 AI
He works on AI
包括做这些都是为了奴役全人类"
and everything he does is to enslave humanity"
你知道吗
You know？
说"我之前认识他
She said， "1 knew him before
他跟我讲他要奴役全人类
He told me he wanted to enslave humanity
才去做 AI"
and that's why he got into AI"
也是刚才讲的
That's exactly what we were just talking about
就是采取一个动机论 对吧
It's judging things by motive, right？
动机论 对
Exactly, motive-based reasoning
然后包括这个 奥特曼 有一个弟弟
And Sam Altman has a brother
不知道还是一个妹妹
or maybe a sister, I'm not sure
这个跟他关系也不好
who doesn't have a good relationship with him either
然后那个人接受媒体采访经常说
That person often tells the media
“大家千万不要相信 奥特曼
"Don't trust Sam Altman
因为他就是这个做AI
He works on AI
就是为了就是自私自利
just for selfish reasons
只是为了获得
just to gain
对对对
Right, exactly
获得利润"
profits for himself"
但是这个也是这个动机论吧
But that's motive-based reasoning too
因为 奥特曼、马斯克
Because with Sam Altman and Elon Musk
其实本质上他做的什么东西
what they actually build
这个评价是脱离他本人的
can be evaluated separately from who they are
讲白了 对吧
Basically, right？
他这个做的这个东西有没有用
Is what they built useful or not？
那大家其实本质上是跟他人品
That question, fundamentally, has little to do
讲白了也没什么太大关系
with their character
那就类似于就网上很多人说我
It's like how people online have been saying
就最近这些发言是
that my recent comments
推广薄肌理论是"吃黑流量"
and promotion of the lean-muscle theory
但是我觉得你不用
But l don't think you need to
在乎我是不是吃黑流量
care whether I'm farming negative attention
你要管的是我说的
What you should care about is whether what Isay
东西对你有没有价值
is useful to you
它是不是科学
and whether it's scientifically sound
应该对
Right, exactly
不要管我的动机
Don't worry about my motives
而是管这些事情的对错
Judge whether these things are right or wrong
对 是太对了 对吧
Exactly, that's so right
你就包括以前我们
This is like what we used to hear
但是其实动机论
Actually, motive-based reasoning
屁股决定脑袋时候
and the idea that your position determines your thinking
很能说服另外一方
can be very persuasive to the other side
对对对
Right, exactly
就是 对吧
That'sit, right？
就是经常就我刚才讲的 那很多
A lot of the things | was just talking about
我以前也是受这个错误思想影响
I used to be influenced by that mistaken thinking too
就是说
Like saying
"练肌肉就是为了泡妞"
“Building muscle is just for picking up women"
所以好像是很猥琐的一个想法
which makes it sound like a sleazy idea
咱不能泡妞
Like, we're not supposed to chase women
要认真学习 对吧
we should study hard instead, right？
就是这个以前这种思路 对吧
That was the old way of thinking
打压这种
It suppressed that kind of
打压这种想法
that kind of idea
所以说
Sothen
那我这个为了避嫌 对吧 避嫌
to avoid suspicion, right, to avoid suspicion
怕大家觉得我是一个作风不正的人
and keep people from thinking 1 had bad morals
开玩笑讲 对吧
jokingly speaking, right？
我连肌肉都不敢练了
Iwouldn't even dare build muscle
那我不练肌肉不就代表我就是
As if not training muscle proves I'm
好学生嘛 对吧
a good student, right？
代表我远离这个思想
It shows I'm staying away from that mindset
我要一进健身房
The moment | walk into a gym
很多人就说
people say
"你是不是最近又要泡妞了
“Are you trying to pick up women again？
所以你去健身对吧"
Is that why youre working out？"
就不是经常很多人经常讲
People say this kind of thing all the time
就说什么中年人
Like with middle-aged men
就是一健身那就是有可能要出轨
if a guy starts working out，
中年危机了对
that he's having a midlife crisis
他中年危机了
He's having a midlife crisis
而且给你老婆进谗言呐说
They'll even whisper things to his wife
对吧 你要出轨所以健身的
like， "He's working out because he's going to cheat"
这其实人家未必
But that may not be true at all
人家为什么一定要是出轨才健身
Why would someone have to be cheating to work out？
对吧 二者都根本就没关系
The two things aren't related at all
但是就是为了抹黑嘛
It's just used to smear people
为了阻挡你去做这个事
and stop you from doing something
所以就是
Sothen
各种动机论就来了
all kinds of motive-based arguments appear
我想说一下
Iwant to say something
就刚才聊到这个 Crypto 这个东西
About what we were just discussing with Crypto
其实我感觉他跟我很多的认知
I feel like it aligns with a lot of my own thinking
就是你完全强化了
You've really reinforced
我很多的认知和理解
a lot of my views and understanding
那我想问一个还是偏私人的问题
Sol want to ask a more personal question
就是我个人层面问你
from my own personal perspective
那我觉得我个人的我的投资
A large part of my own investments
也是很大方面是在 Crypto 里面的
are also in Crypto
因为这是我的知行合一的体现
because that's how I put my beliefs into practice
但是我的个人能力是在英语
Burt my own strengths are in English
做肉容、个人IP、自媒体
content creation, personal branding, and social media
那我记得您在那个
I remember that you
当年的那个播客里面说过
said on that podcast years ago
就是一个人
that when a person
当你的资源有限的时候
has limited resources
最好把你的能力和你的
ie's best to puit allyour abilities and
资源全部投入在一个地方
resources into one place
这样会拿到更好的结果那就
so you can get better results
你会给我一点建议
What advice would you give me？
那你建议我把这
Would you suggest I combine
两个东西结合在一起吗‘
those two things？
我觉得倒也不一定
Not necessarily
其实如果你自己的
If your own
这个优势是做内容
strength is content creation
其实你也可以投资
you can still invest
这个就完全没有冲突
There's no conflict at all
就我记得到当时我
I remember back then
就是2007年的时候
around 2007
就是我第一次知道了 iPhone
when I first learned about the iPhone
我看到这个东西
I saw it and thought
我说太牛了
this is incredible
就那个年代
Back in that era
对吧 这个乔布斯还在的年代 对吧
when Steve Jobs was still around, right？
就是我说这东西太牛了
I thought this thing was incredible
所以那个时候就我就
So back then
买了很多苹果股票
I bought a lot of Apple stock
但我也没有参与到
But I didn't work there
但不代表你要去 Apple 入职
That doesn't mean you have to join Apple
对是的
Right, exactly
当然如果你
Of course, if you
从事手机行业了
work in the phone industry
去 Apple 入职
joining Apple
那也对
would make sense too
知行合一
Putting knowledge into action
也很好 对吧
That's great too, right？
但是没有也不排除你
But even if you don't
就是说买个 Apple 股票
you can still just buy Apple stock
包括我当时12年的时候买特斯拉
Same with when I bought Tesla in 2012
也是因为这个原因
It was for the same reason
因为我第一见到第一部特斯拉
When I first saw a Tesla
我说“这个绝对是革命”对吧
I said， "This is absolutely revolutionary." right？
绝对是革命
Absolutely revolutionary
就是我就
Andljust
所以呢 但是就是我觉得但是呢
So, what l think is
就是升级操作系统总没有错
upgrading your operating system is never wrong
无论是投资还是任何领域
whether in investing or any other field
你升级自己的操作系统
Upgrade your own operating system
你看到一个更先进的东西
When you see something more advanced
你就先升级它
upgrade to it first
我觉得这个是绝对没毛病的 是吧
I think there's absolutely nothing wrong with that, right？
就是说我
Basically, if1
就是说我 Basically， 许f1
就是说我
Basically, 7f1
就是说我 Basically， 汗f1
觉得这个东西更先进
think something is more advanced
我就要升级到这个东西去
I want to upgrade to it
就是所以我平常就是自己
So in my daily life
我是一个其实挺追时髦的东西
I'm actually someone who likes following new trends
所有东西就是新出的我都会去买
Whenever something new comes out, I'll buy it
都会去用
and try it
当然就是也付出一些时间成本
Of course that costs some time
但我觉得值得的因为
but l think it's worth it because
新的东西我觉得就是对的 讲白了
to put it simply, I think new things are usually right
其实就是这么绝对
I'm really that absolute about it
就是这个
That'sjust how I see it
因为很多人就是
Because a lot of people
我包括我的一些观点
including someof my own views
可能在当初看的很极端
may have looked extreme at the time
但事实证明就是对的
but later proved to be right
就比如说我就说
For example, I said
“这个决策都要交给 AI"
decisions should be handed over to AI
很多人就说这个
A lot of people said
"你这个太极端了 对吧
"That's way too extreme, right？
要自己做决定
You should make your own decisions
要自己做什么"
and do things yourself"
这个
But
但是你说这个
when you look at it now
随着 AI 现在越来越强大
as Al keeps getting more powerful
这个就是AI做的决定就是对的
Al's decisions are increasingly the right ones
你要听 AI的决策 对吧
You should listen to Al's recommendations, right？
就是这个很多东西都要问 AI
There are a lot of things you should ask Al about
所以我就是也是最早做AI化的
Sol was one of the earliest to go fully Al-driven
对吧 全部 AI化
Right,make everything Al-driven
包括所有东西都要做AI化
Everything should become Al-driven
所以我觉得就是新的东西
Sol think when something new appears
确实就是要拥抱
you really should embrace it
就是这个是我的一个
That's one of my
我觉得这个符合
I think it aligns with
符合"黄毛思维"
the "yellow-hair mindset"
就是有时候比如说
Sometimes, for example
大部分人不同意你
most people disagree with you
但你看到了
but youlve seen something
你那你就要坚定一点
then you should stay a little more firm
因为很可能你是对的
because you may very well be right
而且你如果用逻辑判断完
And if youlve reasoned it through logically
你觉得是对的
and you think i's right
相信自己一点
believe in yourself a little more
这就是"黄毛思维"
That's the "yellow=hair mindset"
对 就是做 对吧
Right, just do it
坚持住 坚持住
Stick with it, stick with it
千万不要被大家一劝你就觉得
Don't let everyone talk you out of it
对对
Right, right
然后而且为了要合群
And don't give it up just to fit in
你就说这个我就放弃 对吧
and say， "Fine, I'll quit" right？
这个千万不要
Don't do that
大胆做个异类
Dare to be different
因为异类才能拿到大结果嘛
are the ones who can get outsized results
对 就是这样
Right, exactly
对就按这样是
Yes, that's how you do it
就是这个道理 对对对
That's the idea, exactly
那您觉得 Crypto 自媒体有搞头吗
Do you think Crypto content has potential？
我觉得首先自媒体其实就不错
First, I think content creation itself is a good field
其实我觉得
I really think
这个时代我觉得是一个
this era is
就是其实是做多
an era where you should do more
自媒体的时代
independent media and content creation
其实
actually
我举个举简单例子吧
Let me give you a simple example
你就看美国的情况 对吧
Look at the U.So, right？
你像这个就是 罗根
Take Joe Rogan
这些就是 罗根
Joe Rogan is one of those examples
对 就是已经就是做得很大了
He's already become huge
对吧 这个在美国具有这个
In the U.S，， he has
绝对的播客影响力
tremendous podcast influence
他控制了选票
He can influence votes
其实就带了影响力在里面
so there's real power in that influence
你讲的太对了就是
You're absolutely right
但是你说 罗根 是
But do you think Joe Rogan
为了控制选票才做 罗根 Show 吗
started the Joe Rogan Show to influence elections？
那不可能的对吧
Of course not, right？
他就是说想做自媒体
He simply wanted to do media
就是你说现在就是
But now
你看罗根 这么一个节目
a show like Joe Rogan's
就可以就是影响力达到 CBS
can reach the level of influence of CBS
整个电视台这么大级别
a whole television network
对吧 那什么原因
Why is that？
就是因为这是自媒体的时代
Because this is the era of independent media
其实你还别说
And actually
你看 罗根 也是健身的对吧
Joe Rogan works out too, right？
真是
He really does
他绝对是搏击（薄肌）
He's definitely into combat sports
他是练搏击的
He trains combat sports
罗根 练搏击的
Joe Rogan trains combat sports
当然前两天有一个
And a few days ago there was someone
美国被抓起来的
who got arrested in the U.S.
但是呢 也是挺出名的一个
but he's also pretty famous
一个人叫什么呀
What was his name？
他也是一个练肌肉的一个
He's also a muscular
网红
influencer
练肌肉网红
a fitness influencer
在美国被抓了
who got arrested in the U.S.
前两天在佛罗里达被抓了
He was arrested in Florida a few days ago
确实有一些做错
He definitely did some things wrong
对泰特 也是这个
Right, Andrew Tate is also part of this
薄肌论
combat-sports mindset
也是薄肌论了 对不对
He's in that combat-sports world too, right？
对吧 就是
So, right
我觉得这个其实薄肌论
I think this lean-muscle idea
我把它再升级一点
can be upgraded one step further
讲个更高大上的
into something bigger
我觉得就是一下大家就懂了
and then everyone will get it
这个其实未来我觉得就是加上AI
In the future, add Al to it
就是就这个叫什么呢
What would you call that？
叫做主动健康管理
"Proactive health management"
将会成为人类的一个
will become one of humanity's
就是最关键的一个东西
most important things
主动健康管理
Proactive health management
就是你不是生了病才去医院
means you don't wait until you're sick to go to the hospital
这个是生了病再去医院就晚了
If you wait until you're sick, it's already late
就是不生病天天去医院
You go to the hospital even when you're not sick
你知道吧
You know？
就是我最近就是这个
That's what I've been doing recently
不生病天天去医院
Going to the hospital while I'm not sick
是怎么了
What does that mean？
我就是这个 AI 就告诉我
Al tells me
要测什么东西 测什么东西
what l should test, one thing after another
我呢主动去医院
Sol proactively go to the hospital
我就跟医生直接进去
and go straight to the doctor
我就说我要测这几个东西
and say l want these things tested
因为我最近有点胖嘛
because I've gained a little weight lately
我不知道健身之前
Before Istarted working out
AI
Al
就跟我说
told me
先帮你把雷排一下
let's first rule out the major risks
你会不会有什么高血糖高血脂
Do you have high blood sugar or high cholesterol？
什么你的这个
What are your
好的这个胆固醇有多少
good cholesterol levels？
坏胆固醇有多少
What are your bad cholesterol levels？
这所有东西他就帮我先摸一遍底
It first helped me establish a baseline for everything
然后再指导我健身嘛
and then guided my training
所以我就去了一趟医院
Sol went to the hospital
测这些所有的东西
and had all of these things tested
然后我测医院这个东西
When I went in for those tests
那个医生就看了一眼我
the doctor took one look at me
他说"你是不是最近用了 AI"
and said， "Have you been using Al lately？"
然后我跟他说"对对对"
Itold him，"Yes, yes, yes"
我是用了 AI
I have been using AI
这些东西 AI叫我过来测的
Al told me to come get these tests
医生说"你太牛了"
The doctor said， "That's impressive"
就是为什么呢
Why？
医生说他看过这么多病人
He said he'd seen so many patients
我现在是第一个来给他看病
and I was the first person to come in
是本身身体没有症状没有病
without symptoms or an illness
但是自己主动要求
but proactively ask
监控这些数据的人
to monitor these health metrics
他说他见到其他病人还都是 对吧
He said his other patients usually
得自己是
only came in themselves
出症状那就晚了
after symptoms appeared, when it was already late
才来看的
That's when they came
他说
He said
"你居然都用 AI做主动健康管理"
you're already using Al for proactive health management
当然他还跟我聊了一下
Then we talked a little more
发现我也是做这种科技的他说
He learned that | also work in technology, and said
“对你走在这个正确的道路上”他说
"Yes, you're on the right path"
“我作为医生都觉得你做的是对的"
"Even as a doctor, I think what you're doing is right
所以就是我觉得未来就是这种
Sol think in the future
其实这种很多东西就是这个
this kind of thing
主动健康管理是会成为一个主流
proactive health management will become mainstream
而且就是你说就是
And as you were saying
包括我们这个薄肌理论也是这样
our lean-muscle theory is the same way
就是说你现在看的
Right now, as you can see
这个薄肌还是少数
lean-muscle training is still a minority thing
很多人都是不练肌肉的
A lot of people don't train muscle at all
但未来我觉得会成一个标配
But l think it'll become standard in the future
是的 成功男人的标配
Yes, standard for successful men
对因为你没有肌肉就证明你
Because if you don't have muscle, it shows
没有做主动健康管理嘛 讲白了
that you haven't practiced proactive health management
那其实是一个认知上的缺陷
That's really a gap in your understanding
如果没有薄肌
If you don't have lean muscle
你说的太对了
Exactly, you're absolutely right
这太对了
That's so true
一是认知上缺陷
First, it's a gap in understanding
第二就是你就不懂这个
Second, you don't understand
未来这个健康的一个
this future model of health
因为你 我是要做主动健康管理
because proactive health management is what we need
那我一看 25 心肺
Ilook at it as 25 for cardio
25 肌肉你肌肉这个 25你不补吗 对不对
25 for muscle. Aren't you going to fill that 25-point gap？
一定要拿到满分
You have to get a full score
一定要拿到满分 对
Everyone should aim for a full score
要对自己的健康负责嘛 对不对
You have to take responsibility for your health
你健康负责
Take responsibility for your health
所以你就得去练
so you have to train
就自然而然就练
Then training becomes the natural thing to do
就接触这些理论
Once you encounter this theory
你就走上这个健康的康庄大道了
you're on the broad road toward better health
所以我觉得这个东西
Sol think this
也是一个就是一个认知
ultimately comes down to cognition
所以这个核心你看最后我们
The core point is that in the end
觉得还很多就是认知决定命运
so much of this is that cognition determines destiny
其实都是认知
i's all about cognition
这就是黄毛、薄肌、Crypto
The yellow-hair mindset, lean muscle, and Crypto
都是认知
all come down to cognition
你讲太对了
You're absolutely right
都是认知
it's all cognition
对我觉得就是怎么说
Right, how should Iput it？
再把我们这个节目提炼一下
Let me distill our show one more step
就是说今天能看到我们
Anyone watching
这个节目的听众就非常幸福
this episode today is very fortunate
就你就相当于
It's like you've
开图了开图了
unlocked the map
就听到我们这个
Just by hearing this
你就是绝对就是赶紧点保存 对吧
you should absolutely save this episode right away
然后如果你的周围
And if someone around you
人给你发这个节目你就是
sent you this episode
要千恩万谢
you should be incredibly grateful to them
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
就是每年过年得去他家拜年
you should visit their home every Lunar New Year
就是说“太感谢你发给我这个视频了"
and say， "Thank you so much for sending me this video"
对吧 这改变了我的人生
because it changed your life
绝对
Absolutely
就是孙学绝对起到这个作用
Sunology can absolutely have that effect
就什么呢
Why？
就为什么呢
因为这个东西 一是对的
First, because this is right
第二就早点改变你的认知
Second, because it upgrades your thinking earlier
就其实我们大家
A lot of us
很多人有一个错误的
have a mistaken
还是个错误认知
understanding of this
就是很多人就是都觉得呢
A lot of people think
我要有钱
"I need to have money
有资源或者我一定要什么
or resources, or I need something first
就是我好像是要变成巴菲特那样
I have to become someone like Buffett
我才能怎么怎么样
before I can do this or that"
其实根本就不是这样的
But that's not how it works at all
这个社会包括现在这个AI 时代
In society today, especially in the Al era
完全是认知决定命运
cognition completely determines destiny
还是认知决定命运
It still comes down to cognition determining destiny
对吧 你说
Right, think about it
比如说我12年的时候我买比特币
When I bought Bitcoin in 2012
-枚比特币就一美元
one Bitcoin cost one dollar
你说现在七八万美元
Now it's seventy or eighty thousand dollars
10 万美金了
close to a hundred thousand dollars
那我买的时候就一美元
When I bought it, it was one dollar
那个时候并没有讲
Back then
我劝巴菲特苦劝
I tried hard to persuade Buffett
那不买呀
but he wouldn't buy it
巴菲特不买
Buffett wouldn't buy
对不对 我那个时候巴菲特
Back then, if Buffett
一美元的时候如果杀进场
had jumped in at one dollar
巴菲特就用一个小拇指的
he could ve used pocket change
这个钱就把所有比特币都买了
to buy all the Bitcoin
但是巴菲特不买嘛
But Buffett didn't buy
这不也是认知问题吗 对不对
Isn't that also a cognition problem？
我们如果劝巴菲特早点练薄肌
And if we'd convinced Buffett to train lean muscle earlier
当然我没法了
I couldn't do it by then
因为我那时候跟巴菲特吃饭的时候
because when I had dinner with Buffett
巴菲特都已经90岁了 对吧
he was already around 90 years old
89 了
我 29跟巴菲特89 吃的饭 对吧
I was 29 and Buffett was 89 when we had dinner
我那个时候我劝已经来不及了
By then, it was too late for me to persuade him
但是巴菲特如果早点跟我吃
But if Buffett had met me earlier
那我劝巴菲特练薄肌
would've told him to train for lean muscle
巴菲特人生也生活质量顶顶提高
and his quality of life would ve improved tremendously
不用坐轮椅 对不对
He wouldn't need a wheelchair, right？
这个我觉得你就
And I think that's where you
所以你看从这个角度讲
So from this angle
你这个首富都会犯错 就是
even the richest people make mistakes
就是这个
SO
所以我就是
So for me
随着我这个日常生活的越来越
as lve gone through more and more in daily life
我就后来觉得就这认知是最关键
I've come to feel that cognition is the most important thing
千万不要看社会地位
Don't look at social status
看多有钱
or how rich someone is
看什么就这个认知是最关键
Cognition is what matters most
对对 我非常同意
Yes, I completely agree
我想说一下
I want to add something
就我感觉这
I feel this
是一个人性的一个弱点
is a weakness in human nature
以及就是历史经常有这种重复
and history repeats this pattern all the time
就是一般来说一个版本的神
Usually, the god of one era
他都会不愿意接受下个版本
doesn't want to accept the next era
这个版本的当局利益者
The incumbent beneficiary of the current version
屁股决定脑袋
thinks from where he sits
所以他不想
so he doesn't want to
所以他就不愿意接受
and therefore refuses to accept it
他有很大的自我在
His ego is too big
对你说太对了
Yes, exactly
就是这个也是张一鸣不是就提出
Zhang Yiming has talked about this too
我经常看这个企业家成功学
l often read entrepreneurs' success philosophies
我觉得讲的也是挺好
and I think he explains it well
就张一鸣讲就是字节跳动
Zhang Yiming said ByteDance
能够一直这个
has been able to keep
赢对吧
winning, right
我们现在字节当然很牛 抖音 对吧
ByteDance is obviously huge now, TikTok and all that, right
这个各种 App 不都他做的 对吧
All these apps were built by them, right
新时代又做了豆包 对吧
And in the new era they built Doubao, right
都是抢在前面
They're always getting out in front
重要一个
One important thing is
张一鸣当时讲他这个企业
Zhang Yiming once said the company's
这个秘诀就是一个"小我"
secret was having a "small ego"
很关键
That's crucial
就不管张一鸣多成功
No matter how successful Zhang Yiming becomes
他永远是什么
he always
就是愿意去听年轻人讲什么
remains willing to listen to what young people are saying
愿意去学什么东西好
and learn whatever is good and new
不是说
It's not like he says
"我字节跳动牛
"ByteDance is amazing
我天下第一
I'm number one in the world
你们都是傻 对吧"
and all of you are idiots，" right
他不会这种想法
He doesn't think that way
他会说是
Instead,he'll say
有新的我就得学
"If there's something new, I need to learn it"
有新的我就得干 对吧
"If there's something new, I need to do it，" right
他是这个"小我"的状态
He stays in that "small ego" state
他就能不断赢
and that's how he keeps winning
对吧 你要是自我很大
Right? If your ego is huge
比如说百度比如这
take Baidu, for example
你就会被时代甩下
the times can leave you behind
你虽然前面你做得不错
Even if you did well before
但后面这个你就赶不上
later on you may not be able to keep up
所以我觉得这个"小我"很关键
So lthink having a “small ego" is critical
但这个就是你刚才讲的
Burt this goes back to what you just said
而且这个其实跟认知还成反比
and it's actually inversely related to cognition
你越有钱越成功
The richer and more successful you get
其实理应来说
in principle
你的这个自我应该更小才对
the smaller your ego should become
因为你这个才能保证你
because that's what allows
的下一个版本成功嘛 对不对
your next version to succeed, right
但是往往这个是一个诅咒
But often it becomes a curse
就是你越有钱
The richer you get
你越成功
the more successful you become
你的自我越强
the stronger your ego becomes
因为你觉得我这么成功
because you think， "lim this successful"
那不就更证明我想的是对的吗
"Doesn't that prove my thinking is right？"
对不对 你这么失败
Right？"You're this unsuccessful"
那你东西是错的
"'so your ideas must be wrong"
对吧 他会有这么一个思路 对吧
That's the mindset people can fall into, right
你就像
It's like
比如说我当时给巴菲特推销
when I was pitching Buffett
我说可以投资这个
on investing in
马斯克的时候
Musk
马斯克
马斯克 比特币
Musk and Bitcoin
对我都给他推荐
Right, I recommended both to him
他可能会说他说 对吧
He might have said, right
你要是 马斯克 这么牛
"If Elon Musk is really that great"
那是我当首富吗
"why am Ithe richest man？"
那不应该是你当首富了吗 对不对
"Shouldn't he be the richest man？" Right
虽然这个东西是个回旋镖 对吧
Although that ended up becoming a boomerang, right
现在16年之后
Sixteen years later
那真的马斯克变成首富了 对吧
Musk really did become the richest man, right
你下去了 对不对
and Buffett moved down, right
对吧 但是那你想
Right, but think about it
那你那个时候要是提前布局马斯克
if you'd positioned yourself around Musk early
在马斯克不是首富
before Musk became the richest man
的时候布局马斯克
and backed him back then
但现在你
then now
马斯克成首富了
that Musk is the richest man
你不更成首富了吗 对不对
wouldn't you be even richer too, right
你搭了马斯克的顺风车呢
You would've ridden Musk's tailwind
对吧 所以我觉得就是这个理论
Right, so I think the theory is
就是说就是
basically that
越是成功
the more successful you are
其实越要避免这个大的
the more you need to avoid the damage
这个自我给你带来的坏处
that a big ego can bring you
对吧 就跟今天很多人经常喷 对吧
Right? Just like how people criticize
就是这个薄肌理论
this lean-muscle theory today
但是我呢
But for me
赶紧我说
Iimmediately thought
这个得赶紧学习
I need to learn this fast
那我有个问题
I do have a question
那就是说
So
那您和巴菲特吃饭
when you had dinner with Buffett
属实是巴菲特占便宜了
Bufiett clearly got the better end of the deal
这个我100%同意
I agree with that 100%
那您现在和”薄肌教父"对话
the godfather of lean muscle
是不是您占便宜了呢
are you the one benefiting this time？
这一波
In this round
你还真别说
You know what, actually yes
这波肯定是让我占便宜
I'm definitely the one benefiting this time
为什么呢
Why？
因为这个薄肌理论被我吸收了
Because I absorbed the lean-muscle theory
你要实话实说
-Honestly
确实是这样
that's exactly what happened
就是 我呢当时
Back then
我一看这个"薄肌理论"
when I first saw the lean-muscle theory
我就认真学了一下
Istudied it seriously
跟AI一起认真学了一下
and studied it seriously with AI
我发现这个理论确实就是对的
I realized the theory really was right
对的就得赶紧开始实施 对吧
If it's right, you implement it immediately, right
我就花了两周时间
I spent two weeks
又是测血
getting blood tests
又是干嘛
and doing all kinds of things
又是张罗这个张罗那个
arranging this and arranging that
我给他全部张罗起来
I got all of it set up
我把它全部张罗起来之后
Once 1 had everything arranged
我现在就未来40年44年
I felt like the next 40, 44 years
稳了
were basically secured
主要就靠这个理论了
mainly because of this theory
身体上 对吧
physically speaking, right
至少这个心肺前面
At least in terms of cardio, earlier
25 分和这个肌肉 25分
Twenty-five points for cardio and twenty-five for muscle
我就都靠这个薄肌理论
I got all of that from the lean-muscle theory
我就拿下了
andInailed it
对吧 就是这个
Right, this whole thing
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
绝对占大便宜了
I benefited hugely from this
我这个相当于我这个健康这个事
It's like my whole health situation
体重只要控制住
as long as I control my weight
薄肌有了
and buileh leam musdle， |
帮你就是多少踩多少坑
it helps you avoid so many pitfalls
你是不知道这个胖
You don't realize how many problems excess weight causes
因为我自己都有点感觉
I've felt some of it myself
其实我不是特别胖的人
and I'm not even particularly overweight
这个胖
Being overweight
导致太多问题
creates so many problems
三高就不说了
We dont even need to get into the "three highs"
然后包括这个胆固醇高
including high cholesterol
所有带来的这个问题我就不说了
and all the problems that come with it
其实会让你的睡眠也变差
It can also make your sleep worse
然后呢会让你有呼吸暂停
and tause Sleen apnea|
这个睡眠间呼吸暂停
apnea during sleep
就是一堆事
It's a whole chain of issues
包括心血管供氧不足
including inadequate cardiovascular oxygen supply
一系列的东西
There are so many consequences
而且肥胖率确实是在升高的
And obesity rates really are rising
所以这个时候练薄肌
so this is exactly when training lean muscle
就是在就是版本答案
becomes the meta answer
真的就是版本答案
It really is the meta answer
对绝对是版本答案
Yes, absolutely the meta answer
所以我就讲
That's why lkeep saying
就是咱们经常讲
what we often talk about is
这个孙学 薄肌 黄毛
Sunology, lean muscle, and the yellow-hair mindset
就是其实呢
And really
别人看到你可能是更容易泡妞了
other people may see that it's easier for you to date
可能更有钱了
or that you're richer
就是可能更嫉妒你了
and they may become more jealous of you
但是呢其实
But actually
你是走在一个正确的道路上
you re on the night path
你就跟我把钱都换成Crypto
It's like when I converted my money into Crypto
那我赚钱是因为我早升级了
made money lbecause lupgraded earlier
其实赚钱泡妞是个副产品 讲白了
more easily arejust by=products, honestly
对对
Right, right
本质上是我们是什么
Fundamentally, what are we doing？
追求未来
Pursuing the future
追求健康
pursuing health
然后呢只不过这个追求未来
And it's just that pursuing the future
追求健康副产品带来了
and pursuing health brings side effects like
泡妞更容易了
dating becomes easier
更有钱了 对吧
and you make more money, right
当然可能别人就会从你
Of course, people may attack you over
的泡妞和赚钱上攻击你 对吧
your dating life and your money, right
那我攻击我的人不
Isn't that why the people attacking me
就是因为这个原因嘛他
attack me in the first place？
如果光看到我孙宇晨推广 Crypto
If all they saw was Justin Sun promoting Crypto
可能他也就无所谓了
maybe they wouldn't care
但看到你推广 Crypto
But then they see you promoting Crypto
怎么福布斯都
and somehow Forbes
给你排到前100了
puts you in the top 100
你这就不行了吧 这得
and suddenly that's unacceptable to them
开始编我就是个去
so they start inventing stories about me
"看牙医不给钱”的这个事了 对吧
like that dentist story where | supposedly didn't pay, right
就不是一个道理嘛 对吧
Right, i's the exact same logic, isn't it
你要达到薄肌
Once you reach the lean-muscle ideal
T口
其实你也会被人攻击
people will attack you too
但是我觉得你要坚信是什么
But I think you have to stay convinced of one thing
就我是本质上也是追求健康嘛
fundamentally, I'm pursuing health too
对不对
Right, isn't that true
这个你其实也该练
You should actually train too
你与其攻击我
Instead of attacking me
不如你呢
you'd be better off
也开始早练薄肌
starting your lean-muscle training early too
对对 打不过就加入
Right, if you can't beat it, join it
因为时代趋势不可逆
because the trend of the times is irreversible
对 打不过就加入 对
Exactly, if you can't beat it,join it
那我觉得我
I think l
我还想说一个小点
Still want to add one small point
就是说站在我的视角来看的话
From my perspective
就是我看到这么多
when I look at so many
至朝或者说成功的人
dynasties or successful people
他都很难跨过自我这一关
they all struggle to get past the ego barrier
那您现在接受这个"薄肌理论"
The fact that you've accepted the "lean-muscle theory"
说明您现在还是处于一个
shows you're still operating with
“小我"的运行状态
a "small ego"
但是那您的认知这么高
But with your level of cognition
以后越来越成功
and as you become more successful
那说不定以后 真的是世界首富了
maybe one day you really will be the world's richest person
那我希望您也可以保持这个"小我"
Ihope you can still keep that "small ego"
因为如果没有的话
because if you don't
这个历史会不断的重复
history will keep repeating itself
你说太对了
That's exactly right
我这个一代版本一代神
I wrote an article called "A New Version, A New God"
不是发过一篇稿子嘛
didn't|
就说这个王思聪以前嘲笑我 对吧
about how Wang Sicong used to mock me, right
以前王思聪以前嘲笑我 但说
Wang Sicong used to mock me back then, but
我现在比王思聪他爸都有钱了
now I'm richer than even his father
对吧 这个就是我就讲
Right, that's what I mean by
这个一代版本一代神
"'a new version, a new god"
其实在别人看来好像是这个
To other people it looks like
很大的变化
a huge change
其实在我自己看来
But to me personally
没什么变化
not much has changed
我就还是以前那个孙宇晨 对吧 就是
I'm still the same Justin Sun | was before, right
只不过那
It'sjust that
恰巧呢这个社会他就现在就
society happens to
更认可这个认知嘛
recognize this way of thinking more now
讲白了 对吧
That's all, right
认可这个认知嘛 对吧
It recognizes this cognition more, right
所以咱站在我的角度
So from my perspective
我是这样思考
this is how I think about it
就是说这个认知要不断升级
Your cognition has to keep upgrading
就没有人就是说你的一个认知
Nobody can have one fixed set of ideas
你就说
and just say
吃 50 年跟算命先生一样
you can live on it for 50 years like a fortune-teller's script
对吧 吃吃 50年没有
Right? You can't use the same thing for 50 years
每个人的认知要不断升级
Everyone's cognition has to keep upgrading
everyone's cognition has to keep upgrading
这个他有的地方认知对
Someone can be right in one area
不代表别的认知就是对的 对吧
without being right in every other area, right
就比如说我刚才讲这个 马斯克 为例
Take Elon Musk, like Imentioned earlier
对吧那马斯克 确实很牛
Elon Musk really is exceptional
他所有的创业这个认知都是顶级的
His entrepreneurial thinking is top-tier
但他健康薄肌这个认知是不如我们
But when it comes to health and lean muscle，
错误的对
He's wrong there, yes
都不如我们
He's not as good as us on that
其实 讲白了
Honestly
其实讲自了
对都不如我们对吧
no. he's not as good as us there, right
这个 马斯克 现在不仅不练薄肌
Elon Musk not only doesn't train for lean muscle now
还嘲笑练薄肌的人
he even mocks people who do
然后 马斯克 自己呢
And Elon Musk himself
可能就是因为超重
probably because he's overweight
马斯克 绝对超重
Elon Musk is definitely overweight
所以他不是 马斯克 自己就是
so Elon Musk himself has
都是打替尔泊肽 开始打那些
used tirzepatide and started taking those
司美格鲁肽打这些降重
semaglutide-type weight-loss drugs
但是其实我们也知道这个打
But we also know that when you take
这个司美格鲁肽替尔泊肽
semaglutide or tirzepatide
最大的问题就是还掉肌肉
the biggest issue is that you also lose muscle
对吧这降重的时候
Right? While you're losing weight
对吧这降唾的时候
双杀
it's a double hit
再给你掉一层肌肉
you lose another layer of muscle
你不练又掉一层肌肉
and if you don't train, you lose even more muscle
让你的这个降重
So during weight loss
这个脂肪肌肉一起掉
you lose fat and muscle together
然后让你的这个肌肉更低了
and your muscle mass gets even lower
对吧 后面就带来一系列的
which then brings a whole series of problems
因为肌无力
because of muscle weakness
肌肉少带来一系列的问题
Low muscle mass causes all kinds of issues
比如说你摔一跤都很有可能骨折
You could fall once and easily break a bone
一下就上床就下不来了
and end up bedridden and unable to get back up
因为你的这个骨头愈合不了
because your bones can't heal properly
肌肉愈合不了
and your muscles can't recover properly
所有东西都来了
then all the problems pile up
我觉得马斯克需要听这一期播客
I think Musk needs to listen to this episode
绝对绝对绝对需要
Absolutely, absolutely, absolutely
就他而且我跟你讲
And I'm telling you
这个如果他这个认知没拐过来
if he can't shift his cognition on this
叫忠言逆耳
it's a case of good advice being hard to hear
你知道吧
you know
越是对的话
The more correct the advice is
就是越听
the harder it can be to hear
你听起来
it sounds unpleasant to you
如果他认知没有转过来
if your cognition hasn't shifted
屁股决定脑袋
because where you sit shapes how you think
他反而觉得你们这些人是错的
you may actually think everyone else is wrong
就跟那个 约翰逊嘛 对吧
Just like Bryan Johnson, right
他推广他的这个 Don't Die
He's promoting his Don't Die idea
其实没有任何问题
and there's nothing wrong with that
也没有惹到 马斯克
He didn't do anything to Elon Musk either
马斯克 就是要咬死了说他
Yet Elon Musk insists on saying
前面这个肥的时候更好
Bryan looked better when he was heavier before
对吧 就是一给你搞一个认知扭曲
Right? That's a kind of cognitive distortion
对吧 就是所以我就说
Right, which is why Isay
经常这个东西就是
these things often come down to
自己这个
your own mindset
所以我跟你讲
Sol'm telling you
这个就是节目
this program is really
就是这叫做良言呐
what you'd call good advice
只能劝这个有心人
but it only works on people willing to hear it
就如果你自己就是往那个方向想
If your mind is already fixed in the other direction
这个 100头牛都拉不回来
a hundred oxen couldn't pull you back
对 其实那些想
Right, actually
被救的人才会被救
only people who want to be saved can be saved
对 认知决定命运
Yes, cognition determines destiny
就还是认知决定命运
It really is cognition that determines destiny
对吧 就是如果你不想
Right, if you don't want to change
那别人真的是怎么说服
then no matter how others try to persuade you
摆多少证据事实
or how much evidence and facts they show you
如果你不同意
if you refuse to agree
那就过不了嘛
you simply can't get past it
那就跟我跟巴菲特
It's just like me and Buffett
我苦劝巴菲特投资特斯拉
I tried so hard to persuade Buffett to invest in Tesla
投资比特币
and Bitcoin
那跟价格也没关系
It wasn't even about the price
那巴菲特就是觉得
Buffett simply believed
比特币 特斯拉不行
Bitcoin and Tesla were no good
不符合他的投资逻辑
and didn't fit his investing logic
他就不投资
so he wouldn't invest
哪怕那个钱对于巴菲特
even though that amount of money was
来说是无关紧要的
insignificant to Buffett
巴菲特我苦劝的时候
When I was trying to persuade Buffett
那个时候账上3000亿美金呢
he had $300 billion on the books
对吧 比特币就随便用个
Right?He could've used
300 亿美金就买光了 对吧
$30 billion and bought up all the Bitcoin back then, right
但巴菲特不肯买 对吧
But Buffett refused to buy, right
那个时候
Back then
我继续跟你讲
let me keep going
那个时候我们波场也
TRON itself
才二三十亿美金估值
was only valued at two or three billion dollars
对吧 那我就在巴菲特对面吃
Right？| was sitting across from Buffett at dinner
巴菲特直接说
If Buffett had simply said
“宇晨我给你10亿美金"
"Justin, I'll give you a billion dollars"
"波场给我币"
"'give me TRON tokens"
"波场币分我一半"
"'give me half of the TRON tokens"
对呀 对呀
Right, exactly
我说不定真会同意
I might genuinely have agreed
因为我觉得那时候巴菲特
because I felt that having Buffett
当股东对我的这个社会声誉
would ve had a huge effect on my reputation
什么就很大
and everything around it, yes
扩张我都同意
I would 've strongly agreed to the expansion
强势加持
It would've been a massive endorsement
那我们现在
And now
我们现在都已经干到 330亿美金了
we've grown to a $33 billion valuation
对吧 340亿了
around $34 billion, right
最近都340亿美金了
Recently it's been about $34 billion
那巴菲特投资我的 10亿美金
So if Buffett had invested that $1 billion in me
吃完饭之后
after our dinner
短短可能也就是7年就
in just seven years or so
干到 150亿200亿美金了 对吧
it could ve become $15 or $20 billion, right
对吧 就是所以我跟你讲
Right, so I'm telling you
就是认知决定命运
cognition determines destiny
所以就是还是要
That's why you still have to
就是只能劝懂的人
persuade only people who can understand it
你要不劝懂的人
If the person can't understand it
再怎么也没用
no amount of persuasion will help
对吧 实话实说
That's the truth
就是这个理
That's really the principle
只能救会找过来看的人对
The people who understand will come and watch
对对对 太对了
Yes, exactly, exactly
所以这个理论呢
So this theory
包括我自己
applies to me too
你看我过去 36 年并没有练薄肌 对吧
Look, for the first 36 years of my life
也是被大量的错误信息
I was also affected by a lot of wrong information
我 Crypto 领域我可能是个专家
I may be an expert in Crypto
但是我健身领域我不懂
but I don't understand fitness
这个包括这个健康领域我不懂
and l don't understand health either
因为我也没学生物
because I never studied biology
也没学这些
or any of this stuff
我不懂
I didn't know it
但是我这个
But for me
就第一
first of all
大家对我的网暴其实是救了我 对吧
the online attacks actually saved me, right
大家对我网暴是让我第一次意识到
They made me realize for the first time
我可能身体上确实是一个穷人 对吧
that physically, I might actually be "poor，" right
以前我觉得我也正常
Before that, I thought | was normal
可能穷人是那些肥仔 肥仔不正常
and that only really obese people had a problem
平常人也没有人跟我说
Nobody around me normally told me anything
但这波网暴
But during this wave of online attacks
小仙女们因为要给我挑刺嘛 对不对
the "little fairies" were trying to find flaws in me, right
叫放大我的缺点进行攻击
magnifying my weaknesses and attacking them
让我发现了我自己一个缺点
and that made me discover one of my own weaknesses
我说 这个真的还是个缺点
I thought， "This really is a weakness"
必须改 必须改 对吧
"I have to fix it, absolutely have to fix it，" right
所以“小我“让您
So having a"small ego" let you
在一个看似不好的情况
take what looked like a bad situation
就比如说被全网嘲笑被攻击
like being mocked and attacked by the whole internet
你从中得到了一些好东西
and actually get something good out of it
你从中
You were able to
你升级自己了
upgrade yourself
那其实赚了
so in the end, you gained from it
你说太对了
Exactly
就是大家不是都嘲笑我嘛
Everyone was mocking me, right
就是放了两张图片
They put up two pictures
一张我这个头大
one showing me with a big head
这个四肢小
and skinny limbs
然后放了一张这个张继科那个
and another photo of Zhang Jike
腿比那个河马还粗的那个照片
with legs thicker than a hippo's
不是对比全网热热播嘛 对不对
The comparison went viral across the internet, right
确实让我意识到
It really made me realize
第一要开始练 第二呢
first, I needed to start training; second
还让我意识到一个问题
it made me realize another issue
要先练深蹲
I needed to start with squats
因为腿部肌肉
because the legs have
肌肉是最多的
the most muscle mass
对对对
Right, exactly
Exactly
我立刻我像AI一样
Iimmediately, like an AI
就把张继科这张图片转化了
converted that Zhang Jike image into useful information
立刻就是练为自己所有 对吧
and immediately made it my own, right
所以我觉得这个是非常重要
So I think this is extremely important
就是"小我"
having a "small ego"
然后能够把别人的理论
and being able to take other people's theories
把别人的东西的迅速
and other people's ideas
转化为你自己的一个思路
and rapidly
我觉得是很重要
turn them into your own thinking
更不能说是我还
I think that's very important
不听别人的 对吧
You definitely can't say
我想分享一个概念
I want to share a concept
不知道您觉得 对不对
and see whether you agree with it
就是我之前看一个
I once watched a
YouTuber 叫 霍尔莫齐
YouTuber named Alex Hormozi
他说一个概念就是说一个人的智商是
He talked about the idea that a person's
可以人为改变的
intelligence can be deliberately changed
就是说一个人
Meaning that
比如说你根据信息
based on information you receive
你做出了那个行为上的改变
you make behavioral changes
就比如说信息是下面的分母
Information is the denominator
然后行为上的改变是分子
and behavioral change is the numerator
如果你人为的控大你行为上的改变
If you deliberately increase
根据信息的改变的话
in response to new information
其实你就是在提升你的智商
you're effectvely raising your intelligence
也就是说
In other words
当你获得了新的信息
when you receive new information
你真的去做出改变
and genuinely make a change
真的去做
actua ly act on it
其实就是一件聪明的事情
that's an intelligent thing to do
你说的非常对
That's absolutely right
我给你
Let me explain it
举一个最简单的例子
with the simplest example
你一下就明白了
and you'll understand immediately
世界上不存在智商这个东西
There really isn't such a thing as fixed IQ
实话实说
honestly
不存在智商这个东西
There isn't such a thing as fixed 1Q
只存在信息的多少
What exists is how much information you have
这个其实就是这个
This is basically what
就在 这个
《Attention Is All You Need》
the paper "Attention Is All You Need"
Transformer 这个模型就讲清楚了
and the Transformer model made clear
是什么呢
What is it？
就你觉得大模型很蠢是不是
You thought large models were stupid, right
GPT-3、GPT-4 很蠢 是不是
GPT-3 and GPT-4 seemed stupid, right
你还笑话人家是不是
You even laughed at them, right
GPT-5.6
你笑不出来了吧
isn't so funny anymore, is it
GPT-10 你更笑不出来了
And GPT-10 will be even harder to laugh at
那 GPT-5.6 和 GPT-4 和未来的GPT-10
So GPT-5.6, GPT-4, and a future GPT-10
主要区别在哪里
what's the main difference between them？
就是灌的信息
The information fed into them
对吧 这个本质上就是灌的信息
Right, fundamentally i's the information you feed them
灌信息的方式当然
Of course, the way information is fed in
是通过学习的这个方式
is through learning
m口
灌信息就是通过学习的这个方式
You feed information through learning
训练
through training
有预训练
through pre-training
有推理 对不对
and inference, right
但是所有东西其实都是灌信息
But all of it is fundamentally about adding information
给它灌更多的信息
giving the model more information
所以就是本质上就是
So fundamentally
大模型这一件事就讲清楚了
large models make this point very clear
就是这个绝对是个智商的差距
People see it as an intelligence gap
在一般人看来是个智商的差距
To an ordinary observer, it looks like an IQ gap
因为3.0的时候跟个弱智一样 对吧
seemed almost intellectually disabled, right
就是别说人工智能了
Forget artificial intelligence
人工智障
people called it artificial stupidity
现在 GPT-5.6 都已经把 NS 方程给你破解了
Now GPT-5.6 has already cracked the NS equations for you
对吧 这个大家一看
Right? People look at that
你所有人
and everyone
大家会感觉是个智商的差距
feels like it's an intelligence gap
但本质上从后台看
But if you look under the hood
就是灌信息
it's about feeding in information
灌得更多了
feeding in more of it
对吧 现在的 5.6 可能是
Right? GPT-5.6 today may have
我没有仔细数据
I don't have the exact data
但我相信就是之前的数据的1000倍
but I believe something like
就是
And that
那就会带来显著的智商的提升
produces a significant increase in apparent intelligence
对吧 那从我们人
For us as humans
可能我们大家没有这个
we may not literally be
训练大模型的这个问题
training a large model
但是我觉得有一个问题
butl think there's a related issue
就是认知决定很多东西
cognition determines a lot
对吧 认知会导致你行为模式有变化
Cognition changes your behavior patterns
然后你这个行沩模式
and those behavior patterns
然后你这个行为模式
会导致很多东西的变化
change many other things
比如说我再举个例子
Let me give another example
对吧 也是
using a publc figure, righnt
用公众人物来看
Let's look at a public figure
你看那个韦神
Take "Wei Shen，" wei Dongyi
数学当然很好
He's obviously very strong at mathematics
我们讲的这个 NS 方程
The NS equations we were just discussing
其实全人类有个主攻破解的人
have one major person working on them
就是韦神
and that's Wei Shen
韦神就是在那破解
He's been working on them
那韦东奕也我们北大的
Wei Dongyi is also from Peking University
就在那破解 NS 方程
and has been working on the NS equations
但是韦神别的东西我不了解
I don't know much about him outside mathematics
但我只看那个照片
but just from photos
有个最大问题
I see one major issue
韦神牙医不懂
he doesn't seem to understand dental care
年纪轻轻牙齿都掉光了
His teeth are already largely gone at a young age
这个很严重
That's serious
没有早点看牙
He didn't see a dentist early enough
肯定是有牙周疾病
He likely had periodontal disease
但是没有认真去看牙
but didn't seriously get dental treatment
牙齿上至少韦神是不懂的
At least when it comes to teeth，
那这个牙齿很恐怖
Dental problems can be terrifying
因为这掉了之后不可逆
because once you lose teeth, it's irreversible
你知道吧
You know
你就算掉了之后
Even if after losing them
你再装上那个牙齿
you put in replacements
那个假牙的这个功能比
dentures don't function nearly as well
你原来的牙齿差太多了
as your original teeth
所以就是我就讲这个
So that's why I say
我们现在要当六边形战士
today we need to become well-rounded，
你得所有东西都吸收
absorbing knowledge from every direction
全方面提升认知
and improving cognition across the board
全方面
across the board
非常同意
Totally agree
而且你不能觉得
And you can't think
老是觉得"我是韦神
"I'm Wei Shen"
我研究数学就行"
"l only need to study math"
那你牙齿全没了
If all your teeth are gone
肯定给你带来很多不便吧
that's obviously going to cause a lot of inconvenience
对不对
Right？
不能傲慢
You can't be arrogant
你就像你 马斯克
Same with Elon Musk
你这胖
if you're overweight
给你带来很多不便
it causes a lot of inconvenience
你寿命会缩短
and can shorten your lifespan
给你带来很多不好的东西
It brings a lot of negative consequences
也会拖慢你的数学进展
and can even slow down your mathematical work
是不是这道理
Isn't that the logic？
对对对 影响状态
Yes, it affects your state
磨刀不误砍柴工
Sharpening the axe doesn't delay the chopping
千万我们不要想说是
Never think
我就为了砍柴
"ljust need to chop wood"
刀都不磨了
"'so l won't bother sharpening the blade"
这绝对是不行
That absolutely doesn't work
所以我就觉得就是所有这个
Sol think all of this
你像比如说我都
Like for me
后面为什么我提出
why did Hater introduce
主动健康管理的概念
the concept of proactive health management？
很多有钱人都是
A lot of wealthy people
老是觉得"我有钱
always think， "l'm rich"
我就是要医生帮我去提升寿命
"'so doctors should improve my longevity for me"
要医生帮我去什么"
"Doctors should take care of everything"
这个其实不对
That's the wrong mindset
你的健康就你自己要管的对不对
is something you have to manage yourself, right
你说医生能干嘛
What can a doctor really do？
每次冲进医院急救室的时候大喊说
Every time you rush into the ER, you shout
"不惜一切代价抢救过来〞对吧
"Save me at any cost，" right
那个时候都晚了 对吧
By then, it's already too late, right
你早干嘛去了
What were you doing earlier？
而且好多东西你要健康
With health, there are many things
这个事你要你自己干的
you have to do yourself
你不能让别人管
You can't hand responsibility to someone else
因为健康这个东西
because health
对吧 都是你自己定的嘛 对不对
is shaped by your own choices, right
你自己如果都没有一个
If you don't even have
主动健康管理的概念
the concept of proactive health management
你还能让别人帮你去管健康吗
how can you expect someone else
这个不靠谱
That's not realistic
所以这个所有这个东西
So all of these things
这个认知就是我是逐步迭代
my understanding evolved gradually
逐步升级
and upgraded step by step
就像你刚刚讲的 很对
Just like what you said earlier
就是说 认知 信息
cognition and information
本身就是決定智商的
themselves determine intelligence
本身就是决定智商的
智商只是认知和信息的一个外显
IQ is only an outward manifestation
讲白了
basically
对吧 对吧
Right, right
现在这个互联网流行这个显化显化
People online now talk about "manifestation"
你的这个认知显化就是智商
The manifestation of your cognition is your intelligence
而不是倒推
rather than reasoning backward
好像是智商是个本质的东西
as though IQ were the fundamental thing
它是认知
N
Cognition
其实是更本质的东西
is actually more fundamental
对非常非常同意
Yes, I completely agree
这个版本要全方面
You need to upgrade this whole version
升级做六边形战士
across the board and become a well-rounded player
那关于 Crypto 这个话题
On the topic of Crypto
我想最后再问一下
I want to ask one last question
就是 您认可
Do you agree
就您认为"Crypto 将吞噬世界"
Do you believe "Crypto will eat the world"
以及比特币将会是最终的价值储存吗
and that Bitcoin will ultimately
对 我当然同意
Yes, of course lagree
我当然同意这个观点
l absolutely agree with that view
就是因为
Because fundamentally
我觉得就大家就是不用太想太多
I don't think people need to overthink it
就是因为比特币
Bitcoin
没有跟任何人抗衡的 对吧
isn't competing with everyone, right
那很多人就是说
A lot of people say
说比特币不好
Bitcoin is bad for this reason or that reason
这不好那不好
this is bad, that is bad
比特币也没有跟你抗衡的
But Bitcoin isn't competing with you
比特币跟谁抗衡呢
Who is Bitcoin competing with？
比特币跟黄金抗衡的
Bitcoin is competing with gold
那黄金能抗衡的赢比特币吗
Can gold beat Bitcoin in that competition？
那不可能的嘛
Of course not
因为它跟比特币
Compared with Bitcoin
那比特币有的时候都没它呢 对不对
gold lacks many of the things Bitcoin has, right
那能抗衡的赢吗
So can it win that competition？
抗衡的不赢
It can't
就是我觉得 就是这个
Solthink
一个很简单的一个道理
it's a very simple principle
AI 包括这些东西
Al and things like that
就是新的这些东西
these newer technologies
我都是很看好
Im very bulish on allof them
为什么呢
Why？
因为它竞争的对象太老
Because what they're competing against is too old
对吧 比特币每个版本还升级呢
Bitcoin upgrades with every version, right
那黄金升级吗
Does gold upgrade？
对吧 你要是买到黄金那边
Right? If you buy gold
对吧 那个永远不升级
it never gets upgraded
那不根本没有什么这个什么了
so there's fundamentally no comparison
那这个软件
With software
我们最讲的就是一个版本 对吧
one of the biggest concepts is versions, right
更版本
updating versions
对不对 更版本
Right, version updates
更版本就是说你是不是
Updating a version means
你这个东西
that if something
你今天差
is bad today
明天不一定差
it doesn't have to stay bad tomorrow
你版本更上去了
Once the version improves
你就上去了
the product improves
当然这个也是一个非常
This is also a very
互联网这个新的这个
internet-era
一个程序员比较用得比较多的理念
programmer-oriented concept
但是你看都随着这个程序员后来做
But as programmers and software became more important
就这个就是之前最早
it goes back to the old phrase
讲的“软件正在吞噬世界"
"'software is eating the world"
对不对
Right
就是说随着这个软件的发展
As software developed
很多软件的这个词
a lot of software terminology
被年轻人学习了
was learned by younger people
你看都进入一些人生指导领域了
and even entered the language of life advice
我们刚才讲的所谓的
Like what we just called
“一代版本一代神"
"a new version, a new god"
你说年纪大一点的都听不懂
Older people might not even understand that phrase
对这是软件用语
Right, it's software terminology
软件用语
It's software language
而且是什么用语
And how did that language
什么怎么普及的呢
become popular？
最早软件用语大家也都不明显
ordinary people didn't really notice software terminology
因为那你这个软件
because software
版本号大家都自动更新的
version numbers updated automatically
后来是随着王者荣耀普及
Later, Honor of Kings became popular
大家比较在乎了
and people started caring
因为王者荣耀更版本的时候呢
because when Honor of Kings updates versions
它会改那个英雄的强度
it changes the strength of different heroes
所以那你今天练李白 玩的挺牛的
Maybe today you've gotten really good with Li Bai
那下一个版本砍李白 大砍呐
and then the next version heavily nerfs Li Bai
加强别的英雄
and buffs another hero
一下这个版本更到你的痛点了
a version update hits exactly where it hurts
你不就较真了吧
and now you care about it
你说
You start asking
这个版本怎么回事
"What happened in this version？"
这个版本
"This version.."
你就会认真去看它
and you seriously check
那个版本号的那个版本
the version number
哪个号哪个号哪个号 对不对
which number it is, right
你全部就开始关心了
You start paying attention to all of it
所以这个用语呢
So the word "version"
版本这个词呢就
gradually
普及到年轻人领域了
spread into youth culture
然后大家就懂了
and people started understanding
"版本很重要"
that versions matter
大家开始
People began to realize
其实也是人生普及
this also teaches you something about life
给你首先普及了一个新的道理
It introduces a new principle
很多人没有玩王者荣耀之前不懂
Before playing Honor of Kings，
说什么呢
What principle？
大家以为就是什么
People used to think
就到一个游戏里就是先问
when you enter a game, you just ask
玩王者荣耀的时候
when playing Honor of Kings
先问哪个英雄强势
which hero is strongest
我就比如说乱讲的后羿强势
Say, just as a random example, Hou Yi is strong
射箭 咣咣咣射好
he shoots arrows nonstop
好像我就苦练后羿
sOl grind Hou Yi
然后我此后我王者荣耀我就通吃了
and then I can dominate Honor of Kings forever
其实根本不是这么玩的
that's not how it works at all
王者荣耀是个动态版本
Honor of Kings has a dynamic meta
所以呢你得先玩王者荣耀的时候
So when you start playing
先学习什么呢
what should you learn first？
你得先学习整套王者荣耀的机制
You need to learn the entire game system
然后你就开始会理解
Then you start to understand
什么发育经济打野
development, economy, jungling
一系列动态的情况
all these dynamic factors
然后你再挑一个英雄
Then you choose a hero
或者挑一个类型的英雄
ora iype of hero
你就开始布局
and start building your strategy
那么从来没有说是
There's never a situation where
王者荣耀让你能做到就玩
Honor of Kings lets you just play
一个英雄就是能大杀四方
one hero and dominate everyone forever
你要玩一个英雄能大杀四方
If one hero lets you dominate everyone
它马上就给你砍了
they'll nerf it immediately
明天早上就给你砍了
They'll nerf it by tomorrow morning
对吧 其实这有时候又不是
Right? And in a way
就像我们这个人生是一样的嘛
life works the same way
你这个"地球 Online"
This game of "Earth Online"
这个游戏也是这样的
works the same way
你没有说是一个方向
There's no one direction
一个英雄
or one hero
一招吃到黑的
that you can rely on forever
那个你要那个什么
If you try that
马上上帝更个大版本
God pushes a major update
就给你就
and suddenly
砍了 削弱英雄 对吧
your hero gets nerfed, right
2018版 说"地球 Online"2017版、
"Earth Online" version 2017, version 2018
大版本更新
major update
房地产砍50% 对吧
real estate gets nerfed 50%， right
对对 就是打了这个补丁嘛
Exactly, that's the patch
Ai 这边加100%生产力
Productivity over here gets a 100% buff
然后砍房地产
while real estate
一更这个版本
once that version changes
马上房地产就不行了 对吧
real estate immediately stops working, right
如果我是王健林 对吧
If| were Wang Jianlin, right
火速更到 Al大版本
I'd upgrade into the Al version immediately
火速更到 AI大版本
一看你们要给AI大版本
Once I saw the Al version coming
万达火速更到 AI
I'd move Wanda into Al immediately
那不是如果我王健林没有这个认知
If | were Wang Jianlin and had that cognition
我可以投 DeepSeek
I could invest in DeepSeek
我可以投
I could invest in
Kimi 我可以投这个智谱嘛 对不对
Kimi, I could invest in Zhipu, right
我给你们都投上嘛 对不对
I'd invest in all of them, right
你有没有看有一个新闻
Did you see that news story？
就是说碧桂园以前就是
Country Garden previously
因为都在合肥什么做产业开发
was doing industrial development around Hefei
莫名其妙就投上长鑫存储了
and somehow ended up investing in CXMT
结果碧桂园什么
Then Country Garden
长鑫存储才赚了几倍
made only a few times its money on CXMT
火速就给卖了
and sold it almost immediately
你知道吗
You know
就没握住
It didn't hold on
就认知没握住
The cognition wasn't strong enough to hold on
但是这个我就说
That's why I say
就是每个大版本地球也会更新
Earth gets major-version updates too
你这个版本就削弱房地产
This version nerfed real estate
你前面房地产强
Real estate was strong in the previous version
你后面削弱 AI有加成
then it got nerfed while Al got a buff
对吧 有可能再过10年
Maybe in another ten years
我也不知道会出什么新的
I don't know what the next thing will be
AI 可能还削弱呢 对吧 就是
Al may get nerfed too, right
但是保持学习
But keep learning
保持更新
and keep updating
对 所以就是
Exactly, so
当然我们今天谈的其实挺深奥的
what we're discussing today is actually pretty deep
就黄毛 薄肌 孙学
the yellow-hair mindset, lean muscle, and Sunology
其实就是我们什么
are really about
就是打王者荣耀的时候
the same thing as playing Honor of Kings
你得先领悟整个
You first have to understand the entire
王者荣耀这个游戏的规则
rule system of the game
我们并不是说让你
We're not saying you should
一上来就是苦练后羿
start by grinding Hou Yi
你就哒哒哒
and just spam shots
咣咣咣的狂射箭 对吧
firing arrows nonstop, right
你狂射箭没用
Spamming arrows won't save you
你一会给人抓了
Someone will catch you in a moment
一刀就那个刺客就给你
and an assassin will hit you once
就是给你嘎了 对不对
and youre gone, right
因为你没有学习
because you never learned
整个王者荣耀的东西你得
the whole system of Honor of Kings
先学整个王者荣耀
You have to learn the whole game first
然后整个王者荣耀的
And the whole game
它就没有固定答案给你
doesn't give you one fixed answer
说你说我要练哪个英雄怎么练
like exactly which hero to train and how
怎么搞我怎么手速拼手速 对吧
It's not about how to compete on hand speed, right
不是这样的
That's not how it works
你得先搞清楚整个事
You first have to understand the whole system
搞清楚的时候
And while you're figuring it out
版本还在不断更 对吧
the version keeps changing, right
然后你再不断学
so you have to keep learning too
只不过呢
The only difference is
唯一的差别是“地球 Online"这个版本呢
with this version of "Earth Online"
更的这个速度可能慢一点
updates may happen more slowly
论年更 对吧 两年更三年更
maybe yearly, every two years, every three years
王者荣耀的版本快
Honor of Kings updates much faster
那个一个季度就是
every quarter
几个月就是一个版本 对吧
every few months there's another version, right
而且你这个练
And if the hero you've trained
这个英雄不强势的
isn't strong in the current version
你得马上一打你就知道
you find out as soon as you play
立刻就死了麻
and die immediately
对吧
Right
这个可能现实生活中
In real life
你还是需要一些时间
it may take longer to show up
它有滞后性
There's a lag
它比如说版本更了之后
After a new version arrives
你可能3年后才破产
you may not go bankrupt until three years later
对对对
Exactly
对它有滞后性
Right, there's a lag
但是这个什么
But still
虽迟但到
it may be late, but it will arrive
对一定会发生对
Yes, it will happen eventually
对不对 你就
Right
N
这个也是我刚才讲到这个
This goes back to what I said earlier
这个成功人士他不一定对 对吧
successful people aren't necessarily right, right
那马斯克 一直坚持说"我不健身”
If Elon Musk keeps insisting， "I don't work out"
那等 马斯克 这个肌肉
and keeps losing muscle
掉到无可挽回的地步
until it reaches an irreversible point
可能要个15年呢 对不对
that may take 15 years, right
要个10年15年对不对
maybe 10 or 15 years
但是
But
我们知道
we know
就是你如果这样扛下去你不动
if he keeps going like that and stays inactive
绝对会发生
it will absolutely happen
而且现在已经进入恶性循环了 对吧
And now he's already entering a vicious cycle, right
你越胖越打药
The heavier you get, the more medication you take
打药越掉肌肉
the more medication you take, the more muscle you lose
掉肌肉越容易出事
the more muscle you lose, the more problems you have
对吧 越容易出事越胖
the more problems you have, the heavier you get
因为不练嘛
because you don't exercise
越胖越没肌肉 因为没
You get heavier and lose more muscle
你掉肌肉你也掉你的代谢 对吧
and as you lose muscle, your metabolism drops too, right
你默认的这个代谢你不就降嘛
Your baseline metabolism goes down
包括我这么胖
One of the main reasons I got this heavy
一个核心原因就是因为我
is that
20岁的时候我也很瘦
when l was 20, I was very slim too
我也很帅
I was handsome too
我还是杰尼亚中国区代言人呢
I was even Zegna's ambassador for China
你知道吧
you know
我这是很牛的
That was pretty impressive
那时候也是帅哥
I was a good-looking guy back then too
那为什么我到30岁就胖了呢
So why did I get heavier after 30？
我没动为什么就胖了呢
I didn't change much, so why did I gain weight？
肌肉少
Less muscle
就不是因为肌肉掉了
because I lost muscle
就代谢就掉了嘛
and my metabolism dropped
对吧 我就
Right,sol
自然就吹起就胖
naturally started filling out and gaining weight
就喝水就长胖了对
It felt like even drinking water made me gain weight
喝水也长胖了
even water made me gain weight
因为你们不动嘛你
because you aren't moving
对吃一样东西你也胖
Eat the same food and you still gain weight
对所以就是 马斯克
So Elon Musk
只不过是孙宇晨的什么 加强版
is basically an amplified version of Justin Sun
但是我呢
ButI
赶紧36岁
woke up at 36
醒悟了
and realized it
提升 更新
Iupgraded
打补丁了
l installed a patch
打补丁
patched it
对吧 赶紧将这个版本
Right, I quickly updated the version
将这个 bug 就修复了
and fixed this bug
我后面就没有马斯克这个 问题
So later | won't have this error anymore
马斯克 就这个版本扛住不修复
If Elon Musk keeps running this version without fixing it
那就黑客就反复攻击 对吧
hackers will keep attacking, right
那我无论多少钱都被偷光了 对吧
and no matter how much money ! have，
最后他命都没了 对吧‘
eventually even his life is gone, right
其实这个 马斯克
For Elon Musk
如果尽早修复 还来得及
if he fixes it early enough, there's still time
但是呢我觉得 马斯克 很难了
But I think it's difficult for Elon Musk
就是除非
unless
因为 马斯克 已经
because Elon Musk has already
他这个 到他这个层级
reached his current level
只能是靠自己说服自己
only he can persuade himself
对别人的意见他不会听了
Other people's opinions won't get through to him
你说任何人给他说
No matter who says it to him
除非他自己思想扭过来
unless he changes his own mind
否则就是
otherwise
N
但是我觉得马斯克很难的
I think itl be very hard for Elon Musk
因为他这个屁股决定脑袋
because where he sits now shapes how he thinks
已经先入为主了
He's already formed a strong prior view
你让他实现一个180度的这个大转弯
Getting him to make a 180-degree turn
除非就是他得达到
would require
这个伟人的这个级别
almost a great-man level of character
或者 我觉得我觉得有一个场景
Orl can imagine one scenario
就他受一个情伤
maybe a major heartbreak
他受一波情伤
one serious heartbreak
应该可以 可以醒悟
might wake him up
我觉得也很难
I still think it's difficult
因为马斯克自我很大
because Elon Musk has a big ego
我觉得他自我很大了
Ithink his ego is very big
就是他很难去承认说我前面
It would be hard for him to admit
明确表态反对的一个东西
that something he explicitly opposed before
对对
Right
180度大转弯
deserves a 180-degree reversal
能做到这种东西的人
People whocan do that
我告诉你
I'm telling you
就是一般
usually
如果他加上那么强的能力
if they also have that level of ability
这就是伟人级别了
are truly great figures
你觉得你能做到吗
Do you think you can do it？
我觉得我现阶段还是可以做到
I think at this stage I still can
我现阶段可以做到
At this stage, I can
第一个原因
The first reason is
我还不够成功
I'm not successful enough yet
如果我到 马斯克 那个时候
If l ever reach Elon Musk's level
可能自我大到
maybe my ego will be so big
就是没办法转投了
that | won't be able to pivot anymore
有可能
That's possible
这是第一个情况
That's the first possibility
第二个情况
The second is
我觉得就是这个自我大到
but can still make a 180-degree turn
能 180度转弯的人
is definitely a great figure
绝对是属于伟人
That's the kind of thing you rarely see
这种东西只有就中国谁能做到
In China, Deng Xiaoping was like that
邓小平以前就是这样
He could move completely
就能从这个完全
from a planned economy
计划经济 转到市场经济
to a market economy
就说原来这个本来要扔监狱里的
People who originally might've been thrown in prison
我是现在是让他当人大代表
could instead become people's congress representatives
让他开始搞经济
and start building businesses
你这个领导人的
For a leader
这个 180度转弯
to make that kind of 180-degree turn
这是太难了 对吧
is incredibly difficult, right
尤其在他这种语境下
Especially in that context
他这种语境下
in his political environment
在他这种绝对权力的这个面前
in the face of that level of absolute power
很少人能有这么大的个转弯
very few people can make such a big turn
所以我就觉得这个
Solthink
但是这个其实
but actually
就是 讲白了
put simply
对于年轻人来说是个机会 对吧
this creates an opportunity for young people, right
马斯克 就是因为这个
Elon Musk can't make that turn anymore
东西转不过弯了
on this issue
所以 马斯克 待机时间就变短了
so his remaining runway gets shorter
对因为上一个版本的神
Right, because the gods of the previous version
如果他们不那么自我
if they weren't so ego-driven
他们不就是大意然后
and didn't get careless
没有这种弱点的话
or have these weaknesses
那年轻人就没有机会了
young people would have no opportunity
所以说这个世界很公平
So in that sense, the world is fair
这只有这样才会给年轻人机会
That's how opportunities open up for young people
对 就是这个道理
Exactly, that's the logic
然后你知道年轻人为什么
Do you know why young people
天然容易避免这个大自我吗
naturally avoid a huge ego more easily？
有个很简单的原因
There's a simple reason
就是因为他是零起步
they start from zero
所以有时候也不要
So sometimes don't think
觉得我们年轻零起步
starting from zero when you're young
你没钱是坏事
and having no money is a bad thing
好事啊 峰哥讲的 好吧
It's a good thing, as Feng-ge says
峰哥互联网学
Feng-ge's internet philosophy
这好事
says it's a good thing
好事啊 这是好事
It really is a good thing
"听你们讲完”是吧
After hearing you guys, right
"我起点很低"
I start from a very low point
“现在啥钱都没有"
with no money at all
就是明天早晨睡马路 峰哥说
maybe sleeping on the street tomorrow morning，
“这是好事啊”对吧
That's a good thing, right
这是更新孙学黄毛薄肌的最好时机
the yellow-hair mindset, and lean musdle
好事
A good thing
因为没有包袱
because you have no baggage
马斯克 我们给他讲
If we explain Sunology
说 孙学黄毛薄肌 瞧不上我们
and lean muscle to Elon Musk, he looks down on us
巴菲特瞧不上我们
Buffett looks down on us
拒绝更新
They refuse to update
你再怎么也比不上拒绝更新
No matter what, that's worse than being willing to update
孙学、黄毛、薄肌
Sunology, yellow-hair mindset, lean muscle
大家一听
People hear it
年轻人一听
young people hear it
我就安装
and say， "T'll install it"
一键安装
one-click install
那你就一键
Then with one dick
你只要练了薄肌
as long as you train ean muscle
你就一键跑到马斯克前面去了
you're suddenly ahead of the Elon Musk
是的
Yes
对孙哥
Right, Sun-ge
那我再稍微推进一下
let me move us forward a little
我可以推下一个话题
and go to the next topic
就是说那个《财富自由革命之路》
mThe Road to the Financial Freedom Revolution"
这个播客 10年过去了
has been out for ten years
我想问一下
I want to ask
您现在对财富自由的理解有变化吗
has your understanding of financial freedom changed？
就是什么是真正的财富自由
What is true finandial freedom？
对我觉得没有什么变化
I don't think it has changed much
其实我觉得就是
Actually
相反我们这个理论 对吧
if anything, our theory
随着这个十年
has evolved over these ten years
毕竟确实十年了
It really has been ten years
16 年的一个节目
the original episode was from 2016
我们其实是有
and we've had
不少更新的 对吧
quite a few updates, right
包括我们这个
Including
对吧 这个2016年这个9月版 对吧
from the September 2016 version, right
现在又把薄肌这个补丁
we've now added the lean-muscle patch
打上了
installed it
当然那个时候2016年可能我们没有
Back in 2016, of course
那么重要要打薄肌那个理论的补丁
we may not have needed
因为那时候我肌肉量也很大对吧
the lean-muscle-theory patch as urgently
这个你年轻人正常
because I had more muscle then, right
对吧 这个代谢也很高
When you're young, that's normal
所以吃没有问题 对吧
your metabolism is higher too
但是我现在36岁了
But now I'm 36
我就赶紧这个版本大更新
so l had to push a major version update
把薄肌理论也打到这个补丁里了
and patch in the lean-muscle theory
打到这个补丁里了之后
After installing that patch
又可以管 44年
it can carry me for another 44 years
对吧 这个身体上这个
At least physically
补丁至少打进去了
that patch is now installed
而且我们还在薄肌论上发扬了
And we've expanded the lean-muscle theory further
对吧 健康主动管理
with proactive health management
这些所有的这些这些东西 对吧
and all these other ideas, right
然后我觉得就是我们
And Ithink our
对这个世界的理解
understanding of the world
就是更深刻了
has become deeper
其实更深刻了
genuinely deeper
而且你看也有新的工具了
And now we have new tools too
我16年的时候没有 AI对不对
In 2016, we didn't have Al, right
现在你看我们这个主动健康管理
Now proactive health
跟所有这个东西跟财富自由
management and everything related to financial
这一个系列绑定 AI
freedom can all be tied to AI
绑定这个训练
tied to training
让它这个成本前所未有的降低
which brings the cost down to an unprecedented level
所以我觉得就是
Sol think
全部都是绑在一起的
all of it is connected
而且我就是
And there's also
还有一个就确实就是让我挺震撼的
something that genuinely shocked me
就是我自己去医院
When I went to the hospital myself
我要查这个东西
and asked to test these things
医生惊了
the doctor was shocked
医生说
The doctor said
"看你这个样子绝对是用了AI
"Looking at what you're asking for, you definitely used AI"
否则一般人不可能
"Otherwise an ordinary person would never".
一见我面就说要查什么"
"walk in and immediately ask to test this"
查这个 查这个
"and this, and this, and this"
对对
Right
对吧"你们都不懂的嘛
Normal patients don't understand these things
那就只有我这个医生才懂
only the doctor usually does
这些数据是代表什么意思
and knows what these data mean
你一推门就要查这个
So if you walk in asking for those exact tests
你绝对用了 AI"
you definitely used AI
然后我跟他说"对对对"
And I told him， "Yes, yes"
"我就是用了 AI"
"l used AI"
医生说"你太牛了"
The doctor said， "That's amazing"
因为医生那边是能看得到
because doctors can see
多少患者是这个样子
how many patients actually behave like this
对对对
Right
其实医生心里很清楚
Doctors know very dlearly
你怎么做是对的
what the right thing to do is
但是呢他可能也不说了
But sometimes they stop saying it
因为说也没用
Decause saylng it doesnt help
别人都不听他的嘛 对吧
people don't listen to them, right
其实医生也很无力
Doctors can feel powerless too
他想推主动健康管理
They want to promote proactive health management
但患者都是出事了才来找他
but patients only show up after something goes wrong
那就是我想聊就是说孙哥
So Sun-ge, what | want to ask is
可不可以就是简单的就是介绍一下
could you briefly explain
就什么是财富自由
what financial freedom is
就你的理解
in your understanding
因为可能有的人没有
because some people may not have
听你十年前的播客
heard your podcast from ten years ago
那对一个从来没有概念的人
For someone with no prior concept
什么是财富自由
what is financial freedom？
对财富自由
Financial freedom
我呢其实呢 这么讲吧
Let me put it this way
我升级一下
Ill give you an upgraded version
比我 16 年讲的还深刻
deeper than what | said in 2016
财富自由
Financial freedom
其实还是先自由后财富
is still freedom first, wealth second
得先自由了
You have to become free first
财富它是一个伴生品
Wealth is a by-product
它是个伴生品
It's a companion product
很多人可能是想要财富自由
A lot of people say they want financial freedom
想没 都没想通
without really thinking through what that means
来的这个节目但是呢
They come to this program
到了这个节目想听了
wanting to hear about it
我们给他一讲
and once we explain it
彻底懂了
they understand it completely
就跟刚才跟那个王者荣耀
It's like the Honor of Kings example
举的这个例子一样
wejust used
很多人可能只是想
A lot of people may just want
带妹嘎嘎乱杀
to carry girls and dominate the game
还有可能是甚至是个泡妞的
Maybe they even started playing Honor of Kings
这个一个思路来学的王者荣耀
because they thought it would help them date
但是呢后来他就发现带妹嘎嘎乱杀
But later they realize that carrying girls and dominating
如果你不懂前面那个我跟你
doesn't work if you don't understand
讲的整套王者荣耀的理论的
the full game system I described earlier
你光是搞一个英雄在那练
If you just grind one hero
效果不行
the results won't be good
就是财富自由革命之路也是这样
The Road to the Financial Freedom Revolution is the same
就是很多人是以为
A lot of people think
就是很多人是以
我要有钱了我才能自由
"I need money before l can be free"
其实恰恰相反
But it's exactly the opposite
是你自由了你才能获得财富
You need freedom before you can obtain wealth
对吧 当然这个就是要看我那个
Of course, for the full explanation
《孙学：财富自由革命之路》这个
"Sunology: The Road to the Financial Freedom Revolution"
要认真看
carefully
就是里面就讲得很详细 对吧
because it explains this in detail, right
就今天我们也其实谈到一点
Today we've touched on part of it too
就逐水草而居
"follow the water and grass"
你要尽可能的灵活
You need to stay as flexible as possible
你才能踏入这个领域
so you can enter a field
才能进入这个风口
get into the next tailwind
才能获得这个社会与
and obtain the wealth society offers
这个风口相匹配的财富
in proportion to that opportunity
就是它是一系列是很复杂的
It's a whole complex system
但是就是我要简单在
But if l had to summarize it simply
播客上面很简单去总结
on this podcast
我觉得就财富自由财富自由
financial freedom
是先自由后财富
means freedom first, wealth second
但是呢这个是个好事 好事
And that's actually good news
为什么呢
Why？
自由是不需要门槛
Freedom itself has no entry barrier
自由是个主观的东西
Freedom is subjective
你说我要给自由
If you say， "| want to give"
自己自由
"myself freedom"
那就你就拥有了自由
then you already possess freedom
尤其是年轻人
especially when you're young
我可不可以理解为这个
Can l understand it as
自由是认知上的提升
freedom being an upgrade in cognition？
对就是认知上的提升 对吧
Yes, an upgrade in cognition, right
认知上的提升
an upgrade in cognition
就是你愿意自由
If you're willing to be free
你就能拿到自由
you can obtain freedom
然后呢你拿到自由之后
And after you obtain freedom
财富是你自由之后呢
wealth is something that
伴生的一个后果 当然呢
comes along as a consequence
它是有两个东西是有一个加强的
And the two actually reinforce each other
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
它是有个加强的
there's a reinforcing effect
是什么呢
What is it？
你自由一点
If you're a little more free
你就更容易获得财富一点
it's a little easier to create wealth
你更容易财富一点
If you have a little more wealth
更自由一点
you become a little freer
就更加强了你的自由
which strengthens your freedom
自由就更加强了财富
Freedom then strengthens your ability to build wealth
然后就是一个
And it becomes
螺旋上升了哈飞轮
an upward spiral, a flywheel
螺旋上升了
an upward spiral
对吧 就跟这个
Right, just like
我们前面讲的这个理论
the theory we discussed earlier
练薄肌你身体就更好
Train lean musde and your body gets healthier
睡得就更好
so you sleep better
睡得更好
Better sleep
更省时间
saves time
更有时间练 练
and gives you more time to train
带来这个成果
which produces better results
你的健康也是个这个螺旋上
Your health becomes an upward spiral too
而且更自律
and you become more disciplined
更有主控感
and gain more sense of control
然后就会更去研究 AI
then you study Al more
然后就赚更多的钱
and make more money
然后更多的钱就有更多的钱
More money gives you more
去吃营养的东西 营养师
resources for nutritious food and nutritionists
它就是一套正循环
It's an entire positive feedback loop
所以年轻人的第一步
So the first step for young people
进入这个正循环就是薄肌
into that positive loop is lean muscle
你讲太对了
Exactly
N
-就是我跟你讲
I'm telling you
就是我跟你讲
你看刚才讲的
like we just said
我讲马斯克
take Elon Musk
他这个负循环胖
He's in a negative cycle: overweight
打司美格鲁肽
taking semaglutide
打替尔泊肽干预
using tirzepatide as an intervention
掉肌肉 掉肌肉更容易损害健康
losing muscle, which damages health further
更掉这个 更变胖
and makes it easier to gain more weight
然后 马斯克 可能自己还觉得不错
Elon Musk may even feel like it's working
然后 马斯克 可能自己还觉得不错 Elon Musk 而ay even feal
it's working
说我打司美格鲁肽这个还降重呢
saying. "Im taking semaglutide and losing weight"
但他没意识到的是肌肉也降了
without realizing he's losing muscle too
肌肉降了这个这不是
Once muscle drops
所谓的这个叫什么东西
what's that thing called
那个新陈代谢
metabolism
就那个 新陈代谢
yes,metabolism
新陈代谢下降
metabolism drops
对新陈代谢更低
Right, your metabolism gets lower
更低更容易变胖 对吧
which makes it easier to gain weight, right
更变胖更大
More weight means a bigger body
更大肌肉更少
bigger body, less muscle proportion
更少更变胖
less muscle, easier weight gain
然后最后就是肌无力
and eventually muscle weakness
导致就坐轮椅了 对吧
leads to a wheelchair, right
所有东西都来了 对吧
then all the problems arrive
容易骨折
fractures become easier
得病也恢复不了
and serious illnesses are harder to recover from
所有东西都来了
everything starts piling up
所以就是我觉得就是这个
Sol think
财富自由和这个东西也都是一整套
financial freedom and this health framework
比如说
For example
你进入这个负循环也是循环加强的
once you enter a negative loop, it reinforces itself
对对对对
Exactly
你不自由就要烧钱
Lack of freedom makes you burn money
就比如说我刚才举个例子
For example, like I said earlier
你买了个房子
N
you buy a house
-你买了个房子
你买了个房子
这个房子的维护要花你时间
maintaining that house costs you time
花你的钱
and money
然后呢他买了这个房子
And because you bought the house
导致你更多的机会你失去
you lose more opportunitles
然后更多的机会你失去
Losing more opportunities
更少的钱
means less money
导致你钱更少 对吧
which leaves you with even less money, right
状态更差
and in a worse state
就无限循环
It's an endless loop
螺旋循环下降
a downward spiral
我觉得人生真的它没有保持的
I think life doesn't really stay flat
它就是要么往上
you're either moving upward
要么就是往下
or moving downward
没有保持
there's no real staying still
你说得太对了
Exactly
这个就是 AI
This is like AI
我们里面有一个 LLM
There's a concept in LLMs too
一个挺出名的一个模型
from a fairly well-known model
是什么呢
What is it？
它就是这个 AI 的这个线
It has to do with the trajectory of AI
就是最早的模型
the initial model
以及信息输入的差距
and differences in the information input
对于后面这个 AI
For later Al systems
由于这个 RSI 的原因
because of RSl
就是 RSI 就是自我递归更新
RSl means recursive self-improvement
后面导致你们俩就是出现
the two systems start to diverge into
螺旋上升和螺旋下降的这个情况
an upward spiral and a downward spiral
就是你知道就越聪明的 AI 越能 RSI
The smarter an Al gets, the better it can perform RSI
RSI就越聪明
the better its RSl, the smarter it becomes
越聪明就越更新
The smarter it gets, the more it can update
越更新越聪明
the more it updates, the smarter it gets
越聪明喂越多
the smarter it gets, the more data you feed it
喂越多越聪明
the more you feed it, the smarter it gets
然后你的笨的呢
But with a weaker system
就 RSI 的方向也错了
the direction of its RSl may be wrong too
越错越离谱
and every wrong step takes it farther off course
你们俩之后就这个差距越拉越大
Eventually the gap between the two becomes enormous
所以呢就是一开始的一点点
So a tiny difference at the beginning
很重要
is very important
不一样
even a small difference
都会导致后面有很大结果的变化
can produce a huge difference in the final outcome
所以从这个角度来说
So from that perspective
我觉得就是这个年轻人的这个
I think improving young people's
认知这个提升
cognition
其实是非常非常关键的
is incredibly important
它要比这个
I's more important than
我觉得要比大家日常生活中
the things people normally see
看到一些显化的东西
as outward manifestations in daily life
比如说钱具体有多少
like exactly how much money you have
对吧 这个学历
your academic Cteaentas
这个什么
or
智商
yourIQ
一些我们大家看到很外在的东西
these obvious external markers
对吧 是不是有车有房
whether you own a caror a house
这些外在的东西其实
Those external things
都要更 要深刻得多
are far less fundamental
要深刻得多
You need to understand these deeper things
其实你要是得理解这些东西才能
to understand
我觉得是理解
whatlthink is
最根本的财富的来源 核心
the most fundamental source of wealth
这些东西
those underlying things
了解了解
Got it
对 对可以理解
So could we understand it as
对 对可以理解为
薄肌是财富自由的第一步
lean muscle being the first step toward financial freedom
然后不练薄肌就是
and not training lean muscle being
失去财富自由的第一步
the first step toward losing financial freedom
然后认知提升非常的重要
and cognitive improvement being extremely important
而且我继续讲一下
Let me add one more thing
我补充一下薄肌
to the lean-muscle point
就讲讲我自己的学习的心得 对吧
just sharing what I've learned myself, right
其实薄肌也不光是练薄肌你得先
Lean muscle isn't only about training lean muscle
构筑整个身体健康的一个基础理论
You first need to build a basic theory
认知 现在看圣经
You need that cognition; read the bible now
认知现准着堂鏊
You need that cognition: read the bible now
现在看《薄肌圣经》
read "The Lean-Muscle Bible"
对对对 对对对
Right, exactly
一些最基础的理论 对不对
some of the most basic principles, right
一些最基础的理论
the most basic principles
这些理论你都建立了
Once you've built those principles
其实薄肌只是你具体
lean muscle is just one concrete
主动健康管理的一个
manifestation of your broader
显现对
proactive health management
显现
a manifestation
太有道理了
That makes so much sense
它是一种
It's a kind of
对所以说我一直说
Exactly, that's why l always say
薄肌是一种认知的体现
lean muscle reflects cognition
高智力的体现和自控力的体现
high intelligence and self-control
它不是一个单纯的表面的肌肉
It's not simply superficial muscle
对你讲得太对了
Exactly-you saiditpertectly
你知道这概念吗
Do you understand the concept？
就是我再举个例子
Let me gveanother example
我觉得就是大家就理解更深刻了
I think itll make it even clearer
就比如说这个农民工也有薄肌
Construction workers can have lean muscle too
但是农民工呢
But their lean muscle
和我们的薄肌不是一样的
isn't the same as ours
因为农民工的那个薄肌是被动练的
because theirs is built passively
所以很多农民工可能
Many construction workers may
在城里当建筑工人的时候有薄肌
have lean muscle while doing construction in the city
回家就很快就吹肥了
then quickly gain fat after going home
因为他这个薄肌只是
because their lean muscle
他的一个工作带来的
was simply a result of their job
你知道他搬砖带来薄肌
carrying bricks gave them muscle
但是呢
But
为什么这个给农民工没有带来
why doesn't that muscle necessarily give workers
相应的寿命的提升的什么提升
the same improvement in longevity and health？
第一个他回去可能就没薄肌了
First, once they go home they may lose the lean muscle
因为他没有想过这个主动健康管理
because they never developed the idea of
没有想过这个热量缺口
They never thought about a calorie deficit
没有想过这个
or these other concepts
对他不懂营养学
They don't understand nutrition
这些
any ofit
营养学他不懂的
They don't understand nutrition
因为蛋白质这也不懂
or protein supplementation
他只是可能被动的那个练肌肉
They're just passively using their muscles through work
对吧 其实蛋白质补充也不充分
and may not get enough protein
只不过他是这个
It's just that
肌肉也是练了一点
they built some muscle
然后那个脂肪肯定积累不了嘛
and can't accumulate much fat while working that hard
暴露出来
so the muscle shows
但是他营养学这背后东西都没有
Burt they don't have the nutritional framework behind it
但是跟我们这个孙学薄肌
But with Sunology, lean muscle
黄毛理论的就不一样
and the yellow-hair theory, it's different
我们是最早就悟了
We understood the underlying logic early
是有架构的
We have a framework
它地基很稳
the foundation is solid
地基稳
而且我们最早就悟了
and we understood it early
然后我现在
So now
比如说我现在可能
for example, Imay
当然我也得看我自己的执行
still need to see how well l execute
但我现在就可以说
but l can already say
我6个月后就将拥有薄肌
in six months Pll have lean muscle
可能这个没看我们这个节目的人
Someone who hasn't watched this program
看我现在大肚子还嘲笑我呢
may look at my belly now and laugh at me
但我告诉你
But I'm telling you
我6个月以后就会有薄肌
six months from now I'll have lean muscle
他可能说
They may say
"肌肉怎么可能〞对吧
"How could you possibly have muscle？" Right
在他眼里
In their eyes
有肌肉和没肌肉
having muscle and not having muscle
两个人就是两类
are two completely different categories of people
但是在我看来
But from my perspective
我可能6个月前我就有肌肉了
I already had the muscle six months before it appeared
为什么呢
Why？
因为我悟了
Because I understood the principle
这个也是
It's the same
我16年的时候也没什么钱
In 2016 I didn't have much money either
但是我那时候我悟了
but by then I'd understood the principle
我前面可能
Actually
这个当然我也不是16年那一刻悟的
it wasn't that | suddenly understood it in 2016
因为 16 年我这个理论已经写出来了
because by 2016 I'd already written the theory down
我可能这一二年就开始积攒
I'd probably been accumulating it for a year or two
11年我就开始悟 对吧
I started figuring it out around 2011
16 年我理论成型了
By 2016 the theory had taken shape
但我理论成型那一刻呢
But at the moment it took shape
我也没什么钱
I still didn't have much money
实话实说
honestly
至少是比现在的差远了
nowhere near what | have now
可能差一千倍一万倍的财富
maybe a thousand or ten thousand times less wealth
但是我那个时候就悟了
But l had already figured it out then
那个时候我跟王思聪可能差得很远
At the time Wang Sicong and I were very far apart
对吧 那王思聪甩我100条街 对吧
He was a hundred streets ahead of me, right
但是呢我那个时候就悟了
But I'd already understood the principle
但时间会证明孙学
and time would prove it
对时间证明
Yes, time proves it
这点很关键
That's the key point
因为他悟了和没悟
Whether someone has understood the principle or not
其实并不是光看肌肉光看钱
isn'tjust about looking at their muscles or money
他是悟了没悟这个
It's about whether they understand
背后是有一套理论的 对吧
the theory behind it, right
本质上还是脑子
Fundamentally, it's still the brain
大脑认知决定一切钱 肌肉
Cognition in the brain determines everything：
都是显现
those are just manifestations
都是认知的显现
manifestations of cognition
对对认知的显化 对不对
Exactly, manifestations of cognition, right
是不是都是认知的显化的结果
Aren't they all results of cognition becoming visible？
对吧你
Right
否则你说这个农民工也有肌肉
Otherwise, a construction worker may have muscle too
但他跟我们这个肌肉两回事
but it's a completely different kind of muscle from ours
因为我们这个肌肉呢
because behind our muscle
他懂的 就像你刚才讲的
we understand, as you just said
他是懂营养学
nutrition
懂主动健康管理
proactive health management
懂这些所有东西
and all these concepts
渐进超负荷
progressive overload
他们就不懂渐进超负荷
They don't understand progressive overload
对渐进超负荷
Right, progressive overload
这些所有东西加起来
All of these things together
因为他不知道渐进超负荷
because progressive overload
它是一个概念
is a concept
是什么呢
What does it mean？
就是肌肉是什么
Muscle
不断的是
continually adapts
肌肉变大的原因是因为
It gets bigger because
消耗肌肉
you stress the musdle
TR N
给它加然后这个肌肉断开
create small breakdowns under load
然后蛋白质补充
then replenish with protein
肌肉变更大
and the muscle grows back larger
它是这么一个正循环嘛
It's a positive cycle like that
对吧 然后你存更多的肌肉
Right, then you store more muscle
然后身体呢
and your body
未来这个肌肉可以
has that muscle available in the future
你身体要用的时候
when your body needs it
它就可以赶紧就是
it can immediately
支付这个费用
pay that cost
它其实背后有一整套理论 对吧
There's a whole theory behind it
农民工他不知道
A construction worker may not know any of that
他就是生练的那个肌肉
He just builds muscle through hard labor
可能他那时候碰巧了
maybe he happens to
对吧 代谢
have a high metabolism
代谢比较高
a relatively high metabolism
没有这个脂肪 对吧
and not much body fat, right
然后又因为搬砖
plus he's carrying bricks
有点肌肉
so he builds some muscle
但是他跟我们这个
But that's different from
主动管理起来的肌肉
muscle built through proactive management
这是两回事
they're two different things
所以我们这个肌肉只是个外化
Our muscle is only the outward expression
它所带来的主动健康管理的理念
of the proactive-health philosophy behind it
带来的认知的提升
the cognitive improvement behind it
带来的这个所有东西
and everything else that comes with it
它都不是简简单单一个肌肉能
It can't all be explained
能说清楚的
by just saying "muscle"
就很多人可能是为了泡妞
A lot of people may come to this episode to date more
为了获得肌肉来看的这个节目
or to build muscle
但是后来就跟我这个
but later it's like my
《财富自由革命之路》
Road to the Financial Freedom Revolution
很多人是想学怎么赚钱
A lot of people came to that program
来看的这个节目
wanting to learn how to make money
进来学通了
Then they came in and understood the whole framework
当然有一部分人不懂 就出去了
Some people didn't understand and left
对吧 太深奥了
because it was too abstract
但有一部分学通了
But some people understood it and thought, wow
一下悟了
suddenly it clicked
就根本就不是肌肉
It's not really about muscle at all
根本就不是钱的事
and it's not really about money
一下
Suddenly
一通
one prindiple
太营养
opens up everything
百通
one insight unlocks a hundred others
太干货了
That's so substantive
对不对
Right？
太干货了
So much substance
是不是一通百通了
Once one thing clicks, everything clicks, right
而且我觉得这一期播客
And I genuinely think this episode
应该真的是能帮到很多人
can help a lot of people
这是实话
That's the truth
对一通百通了
Exactly, one insight unlocks everything
真的是一通百通
It really does
所以我觉得就是这个认知的提升
Sol think improving cognition
对吧 就我们其实
is what we're really doing
我觉得讲
I think we
先讲一些世俗大家很关心的东西
first talk about worldly things everyone cares about
但是吸引过来
to bring people in
然后解决认知
then solve the cognition problem
然后他自己用认知
and let them use that cognition
解決自己生活中的一切
to solve everything in their own lives
对对对 就而且我们这个
Exactly, and our framework
可不是为了抽象而抽象
isn't abstract just for the sake of being abstract
就确实就是
It genuinely
你知道吧
you know
它是一个认知的这么一个体系
forms a coherent system of cognition
你就跟最早的
It's like how
你知道他这个就是这个
in physics
物理学也是全部都可以收到
everything can be reduced to
几个最核心的大一统理论
a few core unifying theories
你知道吧
you know
然后这个东西可以指导你
And those theories can guide you
在物理学中发明更多的东西
to discover more things in physics
这是一样的
This is the same
就是他这个认知是上收的
The cognition sits at a higher level
如果你不具备这个认知
If you don't possess that cognition
这个地基
that foundation
你即便各种各样的机缘巧合
then even if, through luck and coincidence
你获得了这个财富
you obtain wealth
获得了这个肌肉
or obtain muscle
会失去的对
you'll lose it
最后不知不觉的就没了 对
Eventually it'l disappear without you realizing it
所以中彩票的人
That's why lottery winners
他们只要给他一点时间之后
if you give them enough time
大概率下场都不好
often end up in bad situations
这个是真实数据
That's supported by real-world data
你说的太对了
Exactly
这个中彩票不就跟突然上帝一响
Winning the lottery is like God suddenly
一打响指
snapping his fingers
你就获得了一身薄肌
and giving you a full set of lean muscle
但是如果你没学过薄肌理论
But if you've never learned the lean-muscle theory
你没学过这个
and never learned
主动健康管理这套思路
the proactive-health-management framework
你每天还是麦当劳炸鸡
and you still eat McDonald's and fried chicken every day
这个每天呼呼大睡也不练
Sleep all day and never train
最多6个月
within six months at most
你的那个脂肪肥膘不
your fat
马上立刻就恢复了嘛 对吧
will come right back, right
是
Yes
就跟这个
It's like
你刚才讲太对了
what you just said
就中彩票不就是
winning the lottery is simply
其实一次性的一个干预
a one-time intervention
就是一下让他没有
You suddenly give someone wealth
财富自由这一整套思想
without the whole philosophy of financial freedom
没有孙学这一套思想
without the Sunology framework
突然一下获得财富
and they suddenly become rich
而且这个就是突然一下获得财富
That sudden acquisition of wealth
其实是一个催命符
can actually become a death sentence
是诅咒
a Curse
是诅咒哈 诅咒
a curse, literally a curse
甚至变成诅咒了
It can become a curse
为什么是诅咒
Why is it a curse？
因为他好多不懂的这些人
Because people who don't understand these things
不仅不可能用于再生产
don't use the money to create more value
用于很多这个自己自律什么的
or to build discipline and structure
他很快就转化为吸毒
It can quickly turn into drug use
转化为这些乱七八糟的一下就
and all kinds of destructive behavior
其实没这些事还能活到 80
Someone who might' ve lived to 80 without it
有这东西一下就 60就死了
could die at 60 after getting the money
因为钱是放大器嘛
because money is an amplifier
它就会放大他的错误
It amplifies their mistakes
放大他的坏习惯
and their bad habits
对你说的太对了
Exactly
对你说的太对了 卜
对你说的太对了
Exactly
对你说的太对了 卜
对你说的太对了
Exactly
就一下把这些所有东西都放大 对吧
It amplifies everything, right
他如果没有薄肌理论
If someone doesn't understand the lean-muscle theory
也就炸鸡原来一天
maybe before they could afford
原来只能吃得起一桶
only one bucket of fried chicken a day
现在就吃 10桶了
now they can eat ten buckets
就更糟糕了
which makes things worse
放大了给放大了
It amplifies everything
对吧 就是个概念嘛
That's the concept
他获得财富放大了
Wealth amplifies what was already there
对吧 就是反而成催命符了
and can actually become a death sentence
所以这个就是为什么
So that's why
就是我觉得就是一切
I think everything
就是确实是认知的显化
really is a manifestation of cognition
你认知要是到位了
If your cognition is right
你就全部往上
everything moves upward
对吧 你认知没到位
If your cognition isn't right
你即便获得了薄肌
then even if you obtain lean muscle
获得了财富
or obtain wealth
就是偶然
by accident
获得这些东西
and get those things
对你来说是坏事
they can actually be bad for you
相反就是一个负循环
and create a negative loop instead
直接就给摧毁了
that destroys you
所以这个所有东西
So all of this
就是其实就是一个
really comes down to
认知版本
the version of your cognition
其实这个我们其实今天我觉得
I think today
不仅就是聊薄肌这个东西
we haven'tjust talked about lean muscle
我们这个访谈就聊到了
this conversation has reached
很多"地球 Online"这个游戏
many of the deepest mechanics of "Earth Online"
最本质的了
the most fundamental
运行规则
operating rules
运行的最基本的逻辑
the most basic logic of the game
其实这些东西是最根本
These are the most fundamental things
其实你像
For example
就是我们今天这个
what we're discussing today
你别看薄肌 孙学 黄毛这个理论
lean muscle, Sunology, and the yellow-hair theory
好像在开玩笑
may sound like jokes
但实际上触达了很多
but they actually touch on many
“地球 Online"这个游戏很本质的东西
fundamental mechanics of the game "Earth Online"
这个东西甚至连巴菲特
Things that even Buffett
马斯克都未必想通了
and Elon Musk may not have fully understood
王思聪王健林都没有想通
haven't fully understood them either
都没有想通
They haven't figured it out
都没想通
haven"t figured it out
但我觉得咱俩想通了
Burt I think the two of us have figured out a lot of it
也要不断更新
Our version still needs constant updates
版本答案 对
keep updating the answer
不能太自我
Don't let the ego get too big
对自我太大
Right, don't let the ego get too large
但是我不敢说咱俩想通了
But l don't dare say we've figured everything out
但我能说一点
Whatl can say is
是咱俩至少比 马斯克
at least our cognition is one step ahead of
和巴菲特的认知
Elon Musk and Buffett's
特朗普的认知要往前走了那么一步
and Trump's on these particular issues
要高 要高
a little higher
要高
higher
真的要高
genuinely higher
千万大家别觉得好像
People shouldn't automatically think
我们要对自己还是要有点自信
we can't have confidence in our own understanding
比如说这个
For example
以前古时候的人不知道
ancient people didn't know
个地球绕着太阳转的 最基本的
the most basic fact that Earth revolves around the Sun
最基本的一个地球绕着太阳转的
好多人以为太阳绕着地球转 对吧
Many thought the Sun revolved around Earth, right
地心说 日心说
geocentrism versus heliocentrism
那你只要懂日心说
If you understand heliocentrism
你就比地心说的人就强
someone who believes geocentrism
虽然后面对于这个来说是常识了
Even though today that's common knowledge
对吧 但是那古时候的人
people in ancient times
就孔子都没你懂
even Confucius didn't necessarily know it
孔子以为是这个
Confucius may not have known
地球太阳谁绕着谁转都不一定呢
whether Earth went around the Sun or
所以这个认知的更新是
So when cognition updates
大家千万不要觉得
don't assume
我好像一定要比孔子的认知低 对吧
your cognition must be below Confucius's, right
对对
Exactly
学了就能超过
If you learn, you can surpass old understanding
对吧 马斯克 特朗普 巴菲特
Elon Musk, Trump, Buffett
都不如我们的认知
can all have worse cognition than us on a specific issue
只要我们这个薄肌学会了
If we learn the lean-muscle framework
就超过他们了
we can surpass them on that issue
对 你今天看这个播客
If you watch this podcast today
你今天学了
and leam today
你今天开始看《薄肌圣经》
and start reading "The Lean-Muscle Bible" today
今天开始去健身房吃蛋白粉
start going to the gym and taking protein today
你就超过了 特朗普
then on this specific issue you're ahead of Trump
马斯克 和巴菲特
Elon Musk, and Buffett
这是科学
That's science
尊重科学
respect science
就是这样
That's how it is
对吧 千万别觉得我们夸张了
Don't think we're exaggerating
这也没夸张
We're not exaggerating
因为你不会
because if you don't know it
对对对
Exactly
那孙哥
Sun-ge
我想继续往下推
I want to move us forward
就是对
Right
那下一个问题就是说
The next question is
当真正有钱之后
once someone is truly wealthy
有什么东西是您
what have you found
发现钱解决不了的
that money still can't solve？
其实也还是咱们俩刚才讲的
It still comes back to what we've been discussing
就是我觉得认知
cognition
认知真的就只能靠看我们这个播客
including listening to programs like this
然后自己下功夫
and putting in the work yourself
自己感兴趣 认真学
studying seriously because you're interested
光给钱没用
Money alone doesn't solve it
就跟我们其实刚才咱们强调了 对吧
Just like we've emphasized, right
光给钱
simply giving someone money
中彩票又有什么用呢
what good is winning the lottery？
那不就也是一夜归零吗 对吧
You can end up back at zero overnight, right
这个抖音最近就是
Recently on Douyin
那个什么红果短剧我看
I saw some Hongguo short dramas
而且我就是看那个 Taptap
and some games on TapTap
上面有一些游戏也挺有意思
that were pretty interesting
我觉得大家就可以玩一下
I think people could try them
那个有个游戏那个短剧
There's one game or short drama
就是说什么"你突然中了 500万"
where you suddenly win five million
什么“中了3000万之后"
or thirty million
"你的人生会发生什么变化"
and it shows what happens to your life
如果大家缺钱的人
If you're short on money
可以先玩一下这个游戏
you can try playing that game first
中了3000万后
"| won thirty million"
我的人生会怎么样
"what happens to my life？"
如果你玩那个游戏
If you play that game
最后玩到破产
and eventually go bankrupt
那说明认知不够哈
that means your cognition isn't there yet
你的认知根本没达到
Your cognition simply hasn't reached
能掌控 3000万的地步
the level required to manage thirty million
那就先提升认知
So improve your cognition first
不要想去挣钱
and stop thinking only about making money
因为挣钱甚至你就算发横财
because even if you make money or get a windfall
对你是催命符
it can become a death sentence
对 真是这个道理 对吧
That's genuinely how it works
不是我们
It's not that we're
并不是说大家好像
saying people are bad
不配拥有这个财富
or don't deserve wealth
但道理真的
It's simply
这个是个原理吧
a principle
讲白了 是个原理
just a principle
不是我们说是好像才歧视任何人
We're not trying to discriminate against anyone
它这个原理
It's how the mechanism works
你可以去玩一下那个游戏试试
You can try that game yourself
就那个玩
Play the one where
如果你玩那个
"| won"
"我今天中了 3000万"那个游戏
"thirty million today"
你玩了之后
If you play it
后面是破产的
and end up bankrupt
那你真的要想一下
you really need to ask yourself
我现实生活中中了3000万
iflwon thirty million in real life
可能也是这个结局
would the result be the same？
对吧 那你就讲的话
Right? Then you're talking about
这个是认知问题 对吧
cognition
就前面我讲的
like l said earlier
先自由后财富
freedom first, wealth second
对 那就是财富 事业 投资 对吧
Right, wealth, career, investing
很多东西是可以靠战略解决的
many things can be solved strategically
但是对于我们就是
But for us
对于我们年轻人来说
for younger people
婚姻和家庭好像没有那么容易
marriage and family don't seem as easy
那您现在是如何看
How do you now view
婚姻和家庭这个事情的
marriage and family？
其实这个东西
Honestly
实话实说
to tell the truth
我也在摸索
I'm still exploring it too
如果我不是
IfI weren't
我自己在摸索
still exploring it myself
我有固定答案
and had a fixed answer
我也不会 对吧
I wouldn't have, right
上个月有这个风波 对吧
had that controversy last month
就这个记者也采访我
Reporters interviewed me too
我也很实话实说
and I was very honest
我很多东西我都不知道是对是错
I don't know what's right or wrong
所以这个为什么我叫
That's why I ask
Claude 对吧
Claude, right
就是我还问 Claude 对吧
Iask Claude too
怎么处理
how to deal with things
对吧 我自己都不知道
because l don't know myself
而且这个
And
我其实那个文章很多人
after people read that article
看了之后第一反应说
many had the immediate reaction
“孙宇晨又是要蹭热度"
"Justin Sun is trying to chase attention again"
蹭热度
"chasing attention"
“这个孙宇晨就疯狂想蹭热度"
"Justin Sun is desperately trying to get attention"
因为 这个其实也都是
But those are actually
一些胡扯的理论
pretty baseless theories
但是很多人就相信了
and many people believe them anyway
我不知道有人为什么就这个相信
I don't understand why people believe
说"孙宇晨那个币就是靠
that Justin Sun's token only rises
孙宇晨的这个热度涨的
because of Justin Sun's popularity
这个孙宇晨的币没有任何用
or that Justin Sun's token has no utility
就是靠多少人知道
and people buy it only because
他这个币就过来买"
they've heard of him
你这首先就胡扯
That's nonsense from the start
这第一个我也没有知道
First, I don't even know
谁知道我这个
who these people are
我就按着他的头会买我币吗
Dol force their heads down and make them buy my token？
没有嘛 我没有过做过任何这样的事
No, Ive never done anything like that
我相反呢
On the contrary
这个文章包括巴菲特这个
those articles, including the Buffett story
都是我人生探索路径上
are all part of my own path of exploration
我真的不明白
I genuinely didn't understand
我表达引起社会共鸣
and when l expressed that
我表达引起社会共呜
confusion and it resonated socially
之后的一个结果
this was the result
就是对感情
It's about relationships
对婚姻以及对当下的这个契约
marriage and the current social contract
确实是一种混沌和就看不懂的状态
It's genuinely a state of confusion that
对确实看不懂
Ireally don't understandit
我要看得懂
IfI did
我也不会
Iwouldn't have
发出这个世纪之问了 对吧
raised this "question of the century， " right
就是比如说大家有一个
For example, people have
当然现在互联网上
many different answers online now
大家各自有各自的答案 对吧
everyone has their own answer, right
就是一个世纪之问
Its a question of the century
就说我那个 5000万如果给了
"IfI had given the fifty million"
她还会不会走
"would she still have left？"
我觉得会
I think she would
你讲得非常对
That's a very fair answer
现在的答案
The answer now
因为互联网上太多这个
because so many bloggers online
博主讨论这个问题了
have discussed the question
我觉得正确答案是会
Ithink the correct answer is yes
而且有的博主已经推导出来了说
Some bloggers have even worked it out and said
这个5 个亿也走
she'd leave even for 500 million
50 亿也走
she'd leave even for 5 billion
500 亿也走
she'd leave even for 50 billion
我同意
lagree
甚至有的博主已经发明出来了
Some bloggers have even invented a formula
说这个巴菲特来接盘
for what happens if Buffett takes over
什么时候走
when would she leave？
对吧 能坚持多少天
How many days could it last, right
他有个算数
They actually have a calculation
你知道吧
you know
孙宇晨能坚持200多天
Justin Sun could last over 200 days
巴菲特能坚持300天
Buffett could last 300 days
马斯克坚持 400 天
Elon Musk could last 400 days
什么美联储坚持600天
the Fed could last 600 days or something
你知道吧 但是
you know,but
就这个理论很有意思
the theory is pretty interesting
但是呢这个就是 我觉得就是
But honestly
这个东西当然我现在不完全懂
I don't fully understand this yet
否则今天我们就会讲这个话题
otherwise we'd be talking about it today
就是这个其实也很核心的一个理论
This is actually a very fundamental theory too
我们不一定领悟
We may not fully understand it yet
但是我觉得就是也是
But I do think
但是我可以讲出一些思考
I can share some of my current thoughts
就首先一
First
第一感情这个事跟有多少钱没关系
with how much money you have
真是这个理论
That's genuinely a principle
真是这个道理
a real truth
是的
Yes
就说你不要试图在感情中
Don't try to solve relationship problems
尤其这种爱情中
especially romantic ones
试图用金钱解决问题 没有用
with money. It doesn't work
其实也是这个认知
This also comes back to cognition
刚才我们讲这个认知
what we were discussing earlier
这个理论
that framework
就是金钱其实它就是这样讲的
Money works like this
它可能也是一个放大器
It may simply be an amplifier
它爱和不爱它有个前面有个
Love or lack of love has an underlying
本质性的一个输入输出
fundamental input-output relationship
你后面这个金钱它是个放大器
Money comes later as an amplifier
爱就可能更爱
If there's love, it may amplify the love
不爱就不爱
if there isn't love, there still isn't love
它但是你说 你能不能说我
But can you use money
前面把这个结果彻底改了
to completely change the underlying result？
可能改不了
Probably not
这是第一个
That's the first point
我这第一个
That's my first
我觉得一个想法
thought on it
就是它感情这个东西
relationships
它可能跟钱确实关系不大
probably don't have much to do with money
感情跟钱关系不大
Love and money arenit strongly related
第二个就是说
The second point is
怎么说呢
how should lput it
感情这东西
relationships
我觉得是特别特别
are extremely
主观的一个东西
subjective
D
所以这个是 就是更让你是看不清
which makes them even harder to see Clearly
就比如说
For example
比如说很多我们经常讲的
we often joke about
对吧 开玩笑讲
this kind of thing, right
说经常那个情感大师自己给
a relationship guru can analyze
别人分析的时候头头是道
other people's relationships perfectly
对对 当局者是非常
but once they're personally involved
他的视角是受限的
their perspective becomes constrained
他不是在一个更客观的角度去看
They aren't looking from an objective angle anymore
对 情感大师给别人分析
A relationship expert analyzes other people
头头是道
and everything sounds perfectly logical
然后情感大师自己呢
But then the expert himself
最后进入那个感情之后呢
enters a relationship
情感大师自己都被搞得
and ends up
就是五迷三道的 对吧
completely confused, right
也出不来
unable to get out of it
完全有可能
That's entirely possible
因为它这个感情这个东西非常主观
because relationships are extremely subjective
这个所以这就为什么我们中国
That's why we have the Chinese saying
有古话说是"清官难断家务事“嘛
"Even an upright official can't settle family affairs"
就你再聪明的人
No matter how smart someone is
再聪明的官
or how wise an official is
你去断别人的家务事
when you try to judge another family's affairs
你很难断
it's extremely difficult
因为家务事很主观
because family matters are subjective
但是主观不意味着没有规律
But subjective doesn't mean there are no patterns
这个规律
Those patterns
还是要学习
still need to be learned
还是要摸索
and explored
虽然我现在也没完全想通
I haven't fully figured them out myself
实话实说
honestly
因为我自己
because personally
我也不能说装 不懂装懂
I can't pretend I know what | don't know
因为我没结过婚
I've never been married
对吧 我在这个婚姻边缘摸索了一下
I've explored around the edge of marriage a little
但我没结过婚 对吧
but I've never been married, right
我也没有成立家庭
I haven't formed a family either
我现在还没小孩呢
and l don't have children yet
所以我也不敢贸然去说
sO l don't dare speak too confidently
因为我这肯定没有
because I definitely don't understand it as well as
有婚姻有家庭的人懂
people who are married and have families
因为他们人家更懂 对吧 就是
They have more direct experience, right
但是我呢
Butl
自己也得摸索
still need to explore it myself
这也是为什么我后来给
That's why later, in the letter I replied to
胡锡进回的那个信里面
Hu Xijin with
我就很坦诚
Iwas very candid
我没有给他是去掩盖
I didn't try to hide anything
我就说我这个东西不懂
I said I don't understand this
但是我这个不懂
But my lack of understanding
不是我一个人的问题
isn't just my personal problem
这个时代的问题
I's an issue of this era
这个是中国两个亿人都有这个问题
Around 200 million people in China face this problem
对吧 因为这两个亿人没结婚
because those 200 million people aren't married
我觉得甚至是全球的问题
I think i's even a global problem
我认力是全球的问题
I believe i's global
我认为是全球的问题
I believe it's global
美国其他国家也是一样
The US. and other countries are the same
韩国日本都是一样的都是‘
South Korea and Japan are the same
都有这个困境
They all have this difficulty
对对
Right
对都有这个困境
they all face this dilemma
你说太对了
Eactly
对吧 是个全球性的问题
It's a global problem
当然我个人呢
Personally
也是在摸索
I'm still exploring it too
我个人也是在摸索
I'm still exploring
其实我感觉我以
and I feel like
我仿佛在这个规律中
within these patterns
我感觉我有一套理论和答案
I may be developing a theory and an answer
包括我有做那期视频"黄毛思维"
including the video I made about the yellow-hair mindset
这个
that one
孙哥感兴趣的话
If you're interested, Sun-ge
我们可以私下
we can talk privately
对吧 我可以给你
and I can
理一理它背后的逻辑和规律
walk you through the logic and patterns behind it
好好好
sure, sure
对对对
Yes
好好好把
Great
你可以把那期视频先发给我
Send me that video first
我先认真读一下
I'll study it carefully
对你可以看一下
Yes, take a look
看有没有道理 对吧
and see whether it makes sense
有你觉得有道理我们再继续探讨
If you think it makes sense, we can discuss it further
对是的是的
Yes, absolutely
但这个我觉得也是
I think this is also
当然很需要摸索
something that really needs exploration
因为这个是
because it's
人生的非常重要的一个组成部分
a very important part of life
特别特别重要
exiremely important
就是如果你这 -块没有搞定的话
If you haven't figured this part out
它总是一种缺失的状态
there' always a sense that something is missing
对是的是的
Yes, yes
跟薄肌类似 对吧
Similar to lean muscle, right
是
Yes
薄肌搞定了
Once you solve lean muscle
而且从思想根子上搞定
and solve it at the level of first principles
你就搞定个人健康了 讲白了
you basically solve your personal health problem
是的是的
Exactly
是好
Yes,okay
那就是在婚姻家庭这个东西
So in the area of marriage and family
这个方面呢
at least for now
目前这个补丁暂时还没有
that patch still doesn't exist yet
这个版本还没有发出来
that version hasn't been released
大家先自己
Everyone has to
还在摸索
keep exploring on their own for now
大家就先按照自己的东西玩
So for now, play according to your own understanding
给我们一点时间
Give us a little time
看一看我们能不能
and let's see whether we can
说不定过段时间
maybe after a while
孙哥给出了正确答案了 对吧
Sun-ge will come up with the right answer, right
大家先
For now everyone should
就"坚持住"
just "hang in there"
“坚持住"
"hang in there"
好对
All right
“坚持住"
"hang in there"
™坚持住"
Okay
好
那下一个问题就是
The next question is
那下一个间题就是
那下一个问题就是
The next question is
您现在觉得人活着的意义是什么
what do you think the meaning of life is now？
就是真正让您不断
Wnat is it that truly keeps you
往前走的这个东西是什么
moving forward？
好我讲讲
Okay, let me talk about that
这个活着意义我觉得挺有意思
I think the meaning of life is an interesting question
我呢其实是一个玩家心态
I basically have a player's mindset
就是我呢
I's like
相当于就是被人扔进
was dropped into
这个“地球 Online “这个游戏了
this game called "Earth Online"
然后呢我现在就开始玩
and now I've started playing
然后呢 我觉得这个游戏挺有意思的
I think the game is pretty interesting
然后呢 我现在呢
And right now
还处于一个就是这个
I'm still in
游戏的一个探索期
the exploration phase of the game
就是这个
The question of life's
活着的意义这个问题太难答了
meaning is too hard to answer
所以我觉得我呢
sO l definitely
真的不敢说我怎么想通了
wouldn't dare say I've figured it out
但是呢我呢
But
我现在觉得就是逐步摸清了一些
I do feel l've gradually understood some
这个游戏里面的这个门道吧
of the mechanics of this game
就相当于我自己就是
It's likel
开始有点懂这个游戏
am starting to understand the game
什么意思
What does that mean？
什么东西是关键 对吧
What things are actually important, right
就是这个 对吧
That kind of thing
就有点像你今天如果问大模型
It's like if you ask about large models today
你哪怕问这个 奥特曼
even if you ask Sam Altman
你问这个 达里奥
or Dario
他都回答不了你
they can'tfully answer you
是什么呢
What question？
就说这个
This one
刚才我们讲的这个
what we just discussed
为什么灌更多的东西
Why does feeding in more information
训练更多
and doing more training
这个大模型的这个
make a large model's
智商就会显著提升
intelligence improve so dramatically？
它其实这个你可以问 AI
You can ask Al about this
AI 都可以给你答
and Al can give you an answer
它现在是黑盒
But internally it's still a black box
就里面这个推导机制
The mechanism of inference inside
包括这个逻辑链 思维链
including the logic chain and chain of thought
这个是怎么形成的
how exactly does that form？
这个也是为什么人类恐惧AI
This is also an important reason
的一个挺重要的原因
humans are afraid of Al
你知道吧
you know
就是为什么达里奥
It's why Dario
说是"要对齐 要刹车〞
talks about alignment and slowing down
就是因为他们
because they haven't
没搞清楚里面是怎么弄的
fully figured out what's happening inside
就是人家 AI是像个魔术师一样
Al is almost like a magician
你就是这个黑盒子
You have this black box
灌数据灌更多
you feed it more data
更聪明的这个AI
and a smarter AI
就会被产出
comes out
那你灌数据灌更多
Then you feed it even more data
你说这个聪明会不会向邪恶靠近
Could greater intelligence move toward evil？
以及所谓的善恶到底是怎么定义的
And how do you even define good and evil？
在这个数据中是怎么被标记
How are those things labeled in the data？
以及怎么去理解这个智商的
How do you understand the intelligence itself？
所有这个东西本身没有定义
None of these things have clean definitions
确实没有定义
They really don't
而且就是连最强的AI 的
Even the researchers building
这个研发人员也没搞清楚
the strongest Al systems haven't fully figured it out
然后呢 所以呢
So
很多东西就都是靠猜
a lot of it relies on informed guesses
也以及做些实验 对吧
and experiments, right
就是你自己
When you're on the front line
你在一线总有一些看法
you develop some views of your own
就是它就是这么一个混沌的体系
It's still a chaotic system
其实 AI 现在也就这样
Al today is like that too
所以这个混沌也
And that uncertainty
造成一定程度的恐惧
creates a certain amount of fear
因为你不懂
because you don't understand it
你就恐惧嘛 对吧
Then you get afraid, right？
就我觉得人生
As for life
我现在目前也还是我觉得
where l am right now, I still think
前 50年吧
the first 50 years or so
因为我们现在人类
because today humans
对吧 如果练了薄肌
if you build lean muscle, right？
我估计我
Iestimate | can
90 打底吧
make 90 the baseline
对对对
Right, exactly
90-100 打底吧
90 to 100 as the baseline
那我前面 50 年可能都是一半
So my first 50 years may only be half
所以以我前面那个
That's why my earlier
孙学的这个理论呢
Sunology framework
就是也是数学
also has a kind of mathematical
有数学依据的
basis
就前50% 咱们就是先看
For the first 50%， just observe
先不急着下结论
Don't rush to a conclusion
你知道吧
You know？
就是不急着下结论
Don't rush to a conclusion
前 50 %先看
Spend the first 50% observing
这个后 50%的时候
Then in the second 50%
如果有比前面 50％
if something is better than what
我们觉得对的
we thought was right in the first half
那就赶紧可以下结论了
then you can update the conclusion quickly
就是基本是这么一个理论框架
That's basically the framework
所以我们今天给大家讲的
So what we're sharing today
这些薄肌 孙学这理论
these ideas about lean muscle and Sunology
就真的是替
really come from
一线的悟的
firsthand experience on the front line
最新资料
with the latest information
有点像是这个 最新资料
It's like having the newest data
而且是一线人员
from people actually on the front line
我们这很多东西不是
A lot of what we say isn't
就自己吹的
just us hyping ourselves up
我现在就是没有发言权的
Ifl don't feel qualified to speak
我也不说
I don't say anything
我就真的悟通了
I only speak once I've really understood it
才说
Once it has clicked
悟通了才说
Ispeak after it clicks
所以我们这个视频是极其干货
So this video is packed with substance
不悟通也不敢轻易下结论
If we haven't figured something out，
就是 所以我对人生的意义我也是这样
I take the same approach to the meaning of life
你知道以前
You know, in the past
我小的时候我就有
when I was young
想过很多人生的意义
I thought a lot about the meaning of life
但都逐步被打破
but those ideas were gradually broken down
比如说我给你举个最简单的例子
Let me give you the simplest example
就以前我小时候
When I was younger
人生的意必我都想过
one meaning of Ifie I considered was
我就是为人类为地球做贡献
contributing to humanity and to Earth
我想过
I really thought that
但这个后来我发现被打破了
but later that idea broke down too
为什么呢
Why？
我去了一趟太空
Iwent to space
后来我发现"都不对"
and realized that framing may not be right either
可能我们人类过些年
In a few years, humanity
说不定都离开地球了
may even leave Earth
那为地球做贡献也没有意义
Then contributing only to Earth may be too narrow
我为火星做贡献
Maybe I contribute to Mars
我为别的星球做贡献了 对不对
or another planet, right？
那你这地球是不太窄了
Then focusing only on Earth is too narrow
对吧 后面说"为人类做贡献"
Then you say， "contribute to humanity"
那也不一定
but even that isn't certain
现在都AI 都出来了
Now Al exists
后面有没有其他智能生命体
and maybe there will be other intelligent life
包括人类未来的有没有
and we don't even know what humanity itself becomes
你就也不一定了 对吧
in the future, right？
所以后来我就是
So later | realized
就知道的越多就越不敢下结论
the less willing you are to make absolute conclusions
你知道吧
You know？
所以我现在就是
So now
但是我觉得这个游戏的
I still think you can understand
规律还是能够体会的
some of the rules of the game
然后所以在这个游戏中
And within this game
所以我现在觉得就是
what I think now is
有个更深层次的一个话
a deeper idea
当然也是跟以前的一样
It's related to what I thought before
但是领悟可能更深了
but l understand it more deeply now
我觉得就叫“享受生活”对吧
I call it "enjoying life" right？
就是体验
Experiencing it
享受 也是体验
Enjoying and experiencing
对享受这个 体验的是什么呢
Right-what are we enjoying and experiencing？
就是我刚才前面讲了
Like I said earlier
前50%我们先看
for the first 50%， observe
不发表观点
without rushing to state an opinion
因为根本不懂
because you simply don't understand enough yet
前面 50％看了
After you've seen the first 50%
对吧 我们也有资格发表观点的
then you're at least qualified to form some views
因为我前50%我看过对吧
because you've seen half of it, right？
这个东西我再发表观点
Then you can express an opinion
如果后面马上出现有更好的观点
and if a better view appears later
可以用了 对吧
you can adopt it, rignt？
所以这个也是我的一个态度现在
That's basically my attitude now
了解
Got it
人生对你说的太对了
You're absolutely right about life
你刚才总结的很对
Your summary just now was right
我觉得 先体验
I think first, experience it
先体验
Experience it first
人生增加体验
Add more experiences to your life
先增加体验
Build experience first
前面这个50%的这个资料用来灌体验
Use that first 50% to accumulate experience
也是灌数据嘛 讲白了
which is really accumulating data
所以您现在状态就是
So your state right now is
规律看到了
you've seen some of the patterns
意必暂且不明
but the meaning is still unclear
对暂且不明
Right, still unclear
规律也是
Even the patterns
咱也不敢多说
I don't want to overstate them
其实就领悟了一小部分
I've only understood a small part
这个图也不敢说全开了
Iwouldn't say the whole map is revealed
就是 但是也就领悟一小部分
I've just understood a small part
领悟一小部分 就是
And that small part
真的是这个理论
this theory really
我跟你讲
I'm telling you
能解释我很多行为
explains a lot of my behavior
很多我自己的行为
a lot of things I do
我为什么要做
Why do l do them？
我还不知道吗 对吧
I should know, right？
我觉得很多行为
A lot of behavior
就是理论解释行为
can be explained by theories
就是理论解释行沩
有很多理论
There are many possible theories
但是呢
but
你要拉长时间才能看清楚什么理论
to see which one really explains things
比如说解释孙宇晨的成功
For example, explaining Justin Sun's success
有一个理论叫”炒作论"
there's one theory you could call the "publicity theory"
我自己网上看的
I've seen it online
别人观察我之后
People observe me
别人得出的“炒作论"
and conclude it's all publicity
说孙宇晨
They say Justin Sun
我上个月这个风波
with last month's controversy
加上什么巴菲特
the Buffett dinner
加上什么上太空
going to space
“孙宇晨都是为了炒作"
that everything Justin Sun does is for publicity
疯狂炒作
constant publicity
这是一个理论
That's one theory
这是炒作论
The publicity theory
就是说“孙宇晨
It says Justin Sun
就是为了获得更大的
is always trying to get more
热度或者更大流量
attention or traffic
他就不断炒作
so he keeps creating publicity
螺旋上升"
and it spirals upward
对吧 那孙宇晨到时候当了地球总统
Right? If Justin Sun someday became president of Earth
我为了炒作
under that theory, I'd still be doing it for publicity
为了提升我的外星人的知名度
to increase my recognition among aliens
我可能发动银河系战争 对吧
maybe I'd start a galactic war, right？
但是发动银河系战争
And if a galactic war
可能死几百万人
killed millions of people
最后说"孙宇晨都是
people would still say Justin Sun did it
为了获得更高知名度"
for even greater fame
因为打响一场银河系战争
because once you start a galactic war
你想那不光地球人了
it's not just people on Earth
整个银河系的人都知道我了 对吧
everyone in the galaxy knows you, right？
这是一个理论
That's one theory
但第二个 我还有个理论我自己
But I have another theory of my own
比如说我又不敢解释说所有行为
1 wouldn't claim it explains every behavior
但我有一个行为
but there's one thing I did
我觉得是用这个理论
that I think this theory explains
因为我自己知道
because I know my own motive
我觉得用这个理论
I think this theory explains it
就是你刚刚讲的 体验论
It's what you just called the experience theory
就是解释哪个呢
What does it explain？
解释我上太空
Why I went to space
我上太空这个事
Going to space
其实一不是为了任何炒作
wasn't for publicity
第二不是沩了任何
and it wasn't for
第二不是为了任何
第二不是 了任何
and it wasn't for
第二不是为了任何
就是好像为什么荣誉也好
honor or prestige
什么东西也好
or anything like that
其实我也是本着一个实验的态度
I approached it like an experiment
我就单纯的是为了体验
I simply wanted the experience
其实也不敢做什么决定 因为没人
I didn't even want to make a big conclusion
你说谁上过太空
who has actually been to space？
没上过之前
Before you've been there
你能对此做出啥评论
what meaningful judgment can you really make about it？
其实我觉得做出
I think making
这个评论是很无力的 对吧
strong judgments beforehand is pretty weak, right？
咱们呢我觉得就是先上再说
Sol think you go first and see
就跟咱们这个上车这个概念一样
It's like our idea of getting on the train
这个先上再说
Get on first and see
所以就是去获得更多信息
The point is to obtain more information
对获得更多信息
Right, get more information
这个先上再说
Go first and see
有些人说我上得不够猛 对吧
Some people said I didn't go far enough, right？
说是你要一开始上国际空间站
They said I should have gone straight
上个月球 对吧
or the Moon, right？
指责我这个上太空上得太软
They criticized my space trip for being too mild
就只是上一下不行
just going up briefly wasn't enough
但我觉得这个也是有点苛贵了
But l think that's a bit demanding
因为我们这个
because
我也不一定觉得上太空是对的
I'm not even certain going to space
你首先 对吧
First
我可能先试一下
I may want to try it
先上再说
Go first and see
上完有体验有想法
Afterward, I have the experience and some thoughts
回来再消化
then I come back and process them
后面要不要上月球
Whether to go to the Moon later
后面要不要再进一步
whether to go further
未来要不要去火星
whether to go to Mars someday
我们再说 对吧
we can decide later, right？
但前面这个
lf the upfront
如果这个体验
cost-benefit ratio of the experience
投入产出比我们算了好
looks acceptable
那就先上再说
then go first and see
其实这是一个我觉得
I think this is
一个真实的一线的一个体会
a genuine firsthand insight
它并不是说所有东西都是想好了
It isn't that everything must be fully thought through
所有东西有个结论
with a condlusion
所有东西有个目的
and a clear purpose
我们才去做这件事情
before we do it
所以您的意思就是说
So what you're saying is
想要去找到人活着的意义
if you want to find the meaning of life
你可以先去多体验
first go experience more things
多获得更多信息
and gather more information
然后再慢慢靠这些新的体验
then gradually use those new experiences
新的信息再去推这个意义
and new information to infer the meaning
但现在不着急下结论
but don't rush to a conclusion now
你说的太对了
Exactly
这个是我
That's my
当然我这个不知道 对不对
Of course, I don't know whether this is right
是不是对有一些
or whether it has
有的人觉得这个生活
any ultimate truth to it
自己生活没意义
but it's how I currently see things
有的人可能都涉及到抑郁症
Ithink
这个问题其实也是
the more experiences you have
我觉得这个也是一个疗法
the richer your data becomes
就是我不试图给你去
and the more likely you are
灌输什么东西有意义
to discover a useful pattern
或者是什么东西有意义
So
但是我可以给你讲一个理论
when new technology appears
就是你可以先不急着 对吧
new medicine
先不急着结束
new forms of transportation
你可以再等等 对吧
new places
有什么东西就立刻要下结论的
new ways of living
没有什么东西要立刻下结论的
Ithink
再看一看
we should be willing to try them
可以看一看
as long as the cost isn't absurd
什么东西
We should treat them as experiments
一个疗法也好
Whether it's space
什么东西也好
or some new treatment
我们不一定是很功利的
we don't have to be purely utilitarian
说是一定要是这个东西
and demand that everything
一定要明天早晨就要解决 对吧
solve a problem tomorrow morning, right？
或者这个疗法就一定要有用不一定
or that every treatment must definitely work
但是你可以都试一下
You can still try and learn
就是我觉得是
I think
我现在越来越就是
the older l get, the more
怎么说呢
how should Iput it
就是也不能说是滑向不可知论吧
1 wouldn't say I'm sliding into agnosticism
我现在是越来越觉得就是
but l increasingly feel
提早下结论可能有一点太早了
that condluding too early is often too early
不一定有意义
It may not be meaningful
我这是我是一个
For me thisis
怎么说是一个新的认知吧
a new understanding
相当于是
In other words
我觉得就是体验大于结论
I think experience matters more than conclusions
这个可能我觉得
And maybe
也是人生本身的意义
that's part of the meaning of life itself
甚至不排除
It's even possible
就是
that
我们大家都试图好像是要
we all keep trying to
寻找意义以及寻找结论
find meaning and conclusions
然后好像通过这个东西呢
as though those conclusions
就可以去跳过体验
could let us skip the experience itself
但是我们有时候有没有想过
But have we ever considered
其实人生本身意义
that perhaps the meaning of life
就是你的体验的集合
is simply the collection of your experiences？
其实体验要大于意义
Maybe experience matters more than meaning
就是这个是我觉得
That's
可能的一种情况
one possibility I see
就不敢直下结论
I don't want to state it as a final conclusion
但是我是觉得体验可能要大于意义
but l do think experience may matter more than meaning
对因为马斯克说过
Right, because Musk has said
他说我们人
that he thinks humans
现在的人类活在一个模拟世界
may be living in a simulation
活在这个虚拟世界里面的概率是
and that the probability we're in a simulated world
就超过99%的
is over 99%
那所以可能我们的这个意识
So maybe our consciousness
我们的意识可能就是
our consciousness itself
一个游戏
is part of a game
我们就是来体验的
and we're here to experience it
所以体验就是一切
So experience itself is
对
Right, right
对你说的很对
Exactly
对 就是这概念
Yes, that's the idea
对 所以我觉得就是可能
Sol think maybe
就是这个意义本身
meaning itself
可能并没有那么大 对吧
isn't as important as we assume, right？
这个东西我推荐大家看一个
On this point, I recommend a show
就是一个这个
it's
就是一个剧
a series
挺有意思的
that's very interesting
叫《瑞克和莫蒂》
called Rick and Morty
就是《瑞克与莫蒂》 就是
Rick and Morty
《瑞克和莫蒂里》面呢
In Rickand Morty
那个莫蒂呢
Morty
就是经常会问爷爷一些
often asks his grandfather
就是他
Rick
莫蒂是一个小孩
Morty is a kid
那个瑞克是他爷爷
and Rick is his grandfather
然后他就经常就是会问
And he often asks
爷爷一些"人生有什么意义"
his grandfather questions like，
然后他爷爷呢
Then his grandfather
就是笑而不语 然后呢
usually just smiles without giving a simple answer
那个莫蒂呢
Morty
就会给爷爷马上讲一个结论
will quickly state some conclusion to his grandfather
然后呢那个爷爷呢马上
and his grandiether immediately.
这个爷爷很很恶搞
Rick is awery irreverent character
当然爷爷是个恶搞的角色
a deliberately outrageous character
就那个莫蒂呢
Whenever Morty
每次讲一个无论什么样的结论
comes up with any kind of conclusion
爷爷都能立刻在宇宙中带他
Rick can immediately take him somewhere else
去宇宙的另外一个地方呢
to another corner of the universe
就是找出反例
and find a counterexample
就让莫蒂就是根本
sO Morty simply
无法总结整个宇宙
can't summarize the entire universe
因为他无论怎么讲
because no matter what he says
他爷爷立刻找到一个反例
his grandfather can immediately find a counterexample
然后就是
And that's
挺有意思的一个
part of what makes
就是就这么一个电视剧
the show interesting
然后就是
So
但是某种程度上
in a sense
当然他爷爷都能找出这返利
Rick can always find counterexamples
就是因为他爷爷其实是一个
because he's basically
就是宇宙之王吧
the king of the universe
可以说是整个宇宙
a character who seems to know
他无事不知
almost everything
无事不晓的这么一个角色
about everything
但是他就是也是通过这个原因
That's why he can do it
他才能 但是也某种程度上就是
but it also
说明我们刚才这个问题 对吧 就是
illustrates the point we were just discussing, right？
其实站在瑞克的角度
From Rick's perspective
当然有点虚无了
it can look a little nihilistic
但是瑞克最后其实
but Rick's ultimate
这个结论其实就是
position is basically that
可能就是他不再追求什么意义了
he no longer chases some single meaning
而是整个人生就
Instead, his whole life
他体验的一个集合
is a colestionof experiendes
其实就是这个概念
That's the basic idea
好 那如果您是认为"人生体验论"
Okay, so if you believe in this "life-as-experience" view
以及接下来可能这几十年
and over the coming decades
可能就是去增加更多的体验那
you want to accumulate more experiences
那继续比如说继续您的事业
then when you continue your career
比如说挣钱
making money, for example
发展 TRON 以及您的
developing TRON and
那个 TRX 在美股上市
listing TRX-related businesses in U.S. markets
那这些本质上它的
those are still fundamentally
还是一个商业行为
commercial activities
它是去扩张您的商业版图
expanding your business footprint
但是更多的商业行为和您
How do those business activities overlap with
比如说接下来想要获得更多的体验
your desire to gain more experiences
它们这两件事情之间是怎么样
going forward？
有没有重合
Where do the two overlap？
以及你怎么看
How do you see that relationship？
对肯定是重合的
They definitely overlap
因为每个人他体验
because any individual's experiences
他肯定不能体验全球所有的东西
can never include everything in the world
就是 就比如说我自己在商业上
For example, in business
就像博尔特的短跑一样 对吧
I'm a bit like Bolt in sprinting, right？
就博尔特在乎的体验是什么呢
What kind of experience does Bolt care about？
就是博尔特在乎的体验是
He cares about whether
“我如果跑到9秒80"
if he can run 9.80
"我能不能跑到9秒40"
can he run 9.70？
对吧 当然
Right? And of course
随着你不断突破
as you keep breaking through
其实你是
you're
你不仅其实是代表牙买加在跑步
not only representing Jamaica when you run
你也不仅仅代表整个美洲在跑步
and not only representing the Americas
当然你这个东西
Of course, that status
不是靠你自己说的
isn't something you declare yourself
是由你一个一个目标你在突破
it's earned one milestone at a time
你当突破9秒90的时候
When you break 9.90
你可能是牙买加最快的人
you may be the fastest person in Jamaica
等你突破9秒80的时候
When you break 9.80
你是整个美洲最快的人 对吧
you may be the fastest person in the Americas, right？
等你突破9秒70的时候
When you break 9.70
你可能已经是整个人类最快的人了
you may already be the fastest human alive
然后你这时候你9秒70往后
Then once you're beyond 9.70
你都是代表人类在突破
every further breakthrough represents humanity
你的9秒60
9.60
9秒58 对吧
9.58, right？
在博尔特的跑到9秒58的时候
When Bolt ran 9.58
他代表人类在突破了
he was pushing the limit for humanity
当然只不过呢
But
我们作为商人 商业企业家
as businesspeople and entrepreneurs
我们很碰巧从事了
we happen to work in
一个很好的职业
a very fortunate profession
就是我们这个职业的寿命很长
because our career can last a very long time
对吧 对吧
Right？
就巴菲特包括很多企业家
Buffett and many other entrepreneurs
只要你愿意做
if they want to keep working
你都可以做到死 对吧
can basically do it until they die, right？
你可以 当然我也很幸运
And I'm also fortunate
我 22 岁开始创业
I started entrepreneurship at 22
我那个时候我小时候
Back then, when | was young
我22岁刚创业的时候
when I had just started at 22
我就定了一个规矩
I made a rule for myself
我就说“我打算创业到 122岁"
I said I planned to be an entrepreneur until age 122
因为为什么呢
Why？
因为人类的极限就是123岁
Because the known human lifespan record
一个女的活到 123岁
A woman lived to around 122
我说我不可能大于 123
Sol said I probably can't expect to exceed that by much
刚好我 22 岁开始创业
I happened to start my business at 22
我说我要活
sOl said |wanted to live
“我想活到122岁"
to 122
然后我呢
Then
做了个计划
Imade a plan
我就创业 100年
to be an entrepreneur for 100 years
然后我说创业100年
I I could do that
我就将打破一个人类纪录
I'd break a human record
就是创业时间最长
for the longest entrepreneurial career
然后我这个创业时间最长呢
And within that long career
我就要在这个创业时间最长里面
I want to see
看看我能够代表
how far lcan help
人类摸索到什么地步
humanity explore through entrepreneurship
当然那个时候因为我创业
Of course, when I had just started
刚创业没有什么说服力 对吧
that claim wasn't very convincing, right？
我现在好歹2026年了
Now at least I've been doing it for quite a while
我从2012年创业
I started in 2012
我现在倒也14年了 对吧
so it's been about 14 years, right？
我100年的进度条
On my 100-year progress bar
我也走过了 14 %了 对吧
I've already completed about 14%， right？
虽然跟别人比
Compared with others
跟巴菲特比
compared with Buffett
可能不算什么
that may not be much
但跟我自己比
but compared with my younger self
以及跟很多没有创过业的人比
and with many people who have never started a business
我肯定创业的进度条已经很长了
my entrepreneurial progress bar is already pretty long
我都创了14年业了 对吧
I've already been doing this for many years, right？
就是 但是我还是在一个不断增长的
And I'm still in a profession where
这个时间不断拉长的行业
the time horizon can keep extending
当然我比体育明星
I'm luckier than athletes
比体育这些的人要幸运
or professional sportspeople
因为他们的运动周期很短
because their competitive careers are short
体育可能就10年对吧
maybe ten years, right？
然后就
Then
就不能做了
they may no longer be able to continue
当然这个其实也是我前一段时间
Actually, this reminds me of
这个C罗不是来香港踢比赛
when Cristiano Ronaldo came to Hong Kong recently
这C罗亲自也来了我家
He personally came to my home
我跟C罗聊了很久
and I talked with Ronaldo for a long time
吃了两三次饭呢
We ate together two or three times
合影
and took photos
当然他给我合影
Of course, we took photos together
给我签了球衣
and he signed ajersey for me
但这都是表面的
but those are surface-level things
我还跟C罗交流了
I also talked with Ronaldo
很多人生的这个概念
about a lot of ideas about life
我觉得C罗其实也是我们
I think Ronaldo is actually
这个理论的一个践行者
another practitioner of the kind of theory we're discussing
就是说C罗是什么概念
What does Ronaldo represent？
其实现在就是说不断的
Right now, it's really about continually
延长他运动体验
extending his experience as an athlete.
他在追求这个什么呢
What is he chasing？
进 100球什么感觉
What does scoring 100 goals feel like? Then 900，
200 球一直往后推
then 200 more—just keep pushing the number higher.
现在是900 球
Now he's at 900 goals.
当然全世界人都在
And of course, the whole world is
等待C罗进第1,000个球 对吧
waiting for Ronaldo's 1,000th goal, right？
我觉得是一个人类极限和足球
I think it's about the limits of human ability and football，
体验不断边界被扩张的结果
and constantly expanding the boundaries
就是说 相当于这个
So in a sense，
足球也带给他一个使命
football itself has given him a mission.
所以就是C罗不是现在都4142了
That's why Ronaldo is already in his 40s，
还在踢
and he's still playing.
当然有些罗黑就会
Of course, some Ronaldo haters will say，
说“你怎么不踢到52呢”对吧
“Why don't you keep playing until you're 523"
"你踢到 102算了"对吧
"Why not play until you're 102？"
这个体育的
But in sports，
但是c罗其实就是在不断的
Ronaldo is really just constantly
在拓展这个边界嘛
pushing that boundary outward.
讲白了 其实他就是做这个拓展边界
Put simply, he's expanding the boundary.
所以我个人觉得我的商业呢
And I think with my own business，
以及我这个追求
and with what I'm pursuing，
其实我也是在拓展
I'm also trying to push
这个边界
that boundary.
拓展这个边界
To expand that boundary.
当然我也不是说这个拓展边界
Of course, I'm not saying that this boundary-pushing
很多东西不是一开始就想好的 对吧
was all planned from the beginning, right？
就像我刚才讲的
Like I said earlier，
也不排除波场以及
I can't rule out TRON or whatever comes next for us.
就是现在我们已经在做B.AI 了嘛
We're already working on B.Al now.
对吧 我也不会说
Sol wouldn't say，
甚至是我很难下结论
and it's actually hard for me to conclude，
你说未来我们公司
that our company in the future
就是个区块链公司吗
will simply be a blockchain company.
也未必吧 对不对
Not necessarily, right？
就你就跟巴菲特
It's like Buffett's
那个伯克希尔哈撒韦
Berkshire Hathaway.
你知道吗
You know？
那个公司一开始是个纺织厂
That company started out as a textile mill.
对吧 大家听到伯克希尔哈撒韦
When people hear Berkshire Hathaway now，
你以为是投资巨头
they think of an investment giant.
现在一听到
Today, when you hear the name，
第一反应是“这个是个投资巨头"
your first thought is， "That's an investment giant."
没有 一开始创建的时候是个纺织厂
But no—it started as a textile mill.
后面迭代变成金融巨鳄了 对吧
Then it evolved into a financial powerhouse, right？
世界上最出名的投资公司
One of the world's most famous investment companies.
但是没有
But no，
一开始成立的时候是个纺织厂
when it was founded, it was a textile mill.
所以就是我就讲就是
So what I'm saying is，
你说波厂以及
TRON and
包括我未来会做什么
whatever I may do in the future，
这个其实也很难说
it's really hard to say.
说不定还在区块链领域
Maybe we'll still be in blockchain.
说不定未来 AI了
Maybe we'll move into AI.
说不定未来都从事宇宙殖民了
Maybe one day we'll be working on space colonization.
谁知道呢 对吧
Who knows, right？
就是这个
That'sthe thing.
但是我呢
But for me，
有一点是不变的
one thing won't change：
就是我会在这个
Ill stay within the realm of
推进体验的这个范畴内 对吧
pushing the boundaries of experience, right？
我前面都
Like I said before，
最早说创业就想过
when I first started a business, I thought，
刚好122岁干100年对吧
“Ifl live to 122, I can work for 100 years" right？
这个不断去拓展这个边界
Just keep pushing that boundary.
我觉得就是这个理论其实
I think that's really the idea.
了解 所以您现在给自己
Got it. So the life strategy you've set for yourself
制定的人生策略
is basically this：
就目前来说
at least for now，
就是说既然你已经在
since youre already
玩商业版图这个游戏了
playing the game of building a business empire，
那你就不断地去测它的边界
you just keep testing its limits，
然后就用一个可能
and maybe use
金钱这个作为数字
money as the number，
它就像积分一样 对吧
like a score, right？
比如说踢到 900个球
Like scoring 900 goals，
你可能挣到 900 亿
or maybe making 90 billion.
这样的一个概念
That's the idea，
一直往上去突破
and you just keep breaking through to the next level.
你说的太对了
Exactly.
我呢还问过A
I've actually asked Al about this too.
我呢还问过 AI
就是当然我现在也
Of course, right now l
也不好说我挣了多少钱 对吧
can't really say how much money I've made, right？
但是我呢试图问过 AI
But I did ask Al about it.
我们俩都讨论过
We discussed it together.
比如说这个
For example，
数字也不是个无穷值吧 对吧
the number can't be infinite, right？
那肯定有边界
There has to be some limit.
我就问AI一个很简单的
Sol asked Al something simple.
我说就是现在我发现在世界首富
I said， "I noticed that the world's richest person，
马斯克 可能也就是挣2000亿美金
Elon Musk, may only be worth around $200 billion.
我说“这为什么是这个道理"
Why is that？
“为什么没有人能挣5万亿美金”
Why can't anyone make $5 trillion？
就是继续往上呢
Why can't the number just keep going up？"
Al就给了我一个很
Al gave me a very，
很有意思的答案
very interesting answer.
AI 就说"你首先你挣多少钱不重要
Al said， "First of all, how much you make isn't the key.
你首先得看
You first have to look at
其实这个金钱是整个衡量整个
the fact that money is really a measure of
可接触范围内的经济活动的一个总值
the total value of economic activity within reach.
就比如说 你美联储
For example, the Federal Reserve
美国的GDP一年也就
The GDP of the United States in one year
比如说11万亿 14万亿 15万亿 20万亿
eleven trillion, fourteen trillion，
你再加上中国10万亿美金
plus ten trillion US dollars of China，
你总共 比如说全球GDP
the total global GDP
可能就四五十万亿
maybe forty or fifty trillion.
你说你一个人
For one person，
你挣最多钱
there's a maximum amount you can make."
你就挣地球GDP的1%吧对不对
Maybe you can make 1% of Earth's GDP, right？
你不可能全地球人的钱
You can't have all the money on Earth
都让你一个人挣了吧
go to one person, can you？
对不对
Right？
那你就是前面它这个经济总值
So the total size of the economy
比如说 50 万亿
might be, say， $50 trillion，
就决定了你 1%
and that determines what 1% means.
你就最多挣到 5000亿
At most, you'd make $500 billion.
然后这个
Andthen，
再加总
when you add it all up.
就是说 科技本身
technology itself
可能会提升这个天花板
may raise that ceiling.
就比如说如果前面没有AI
For example, before Al，
没有这个 东西
before all these new things，
那挣最多钱就只能苹果 对吧
maybe the biggest opportunity was Apple, right？
智能手机
Smartphones.
4万亿一个美金
A $4 trillion company
一个公司就极限了
might have been the upper limit.
但现在可能又捅破了
But now that ceiling may be broken again.
你未来有 AI
In the future you have Al，
有这个因为 AI会增加集中度 对吧
and Al can increase concentration, right？
这个新行业这个集中度
New industries can create new structures，
你不排除可能有 10 万亿
so maybe you could see a $10 trillion company.
但是它都是有极限的
But there is still a limit.
所以就是这个
So that's the point.
但是这个极限也在不断的被往前推
The limit itself keeps getting pushed outward.
未来举个最简单例子
Here's the simplest example.
可能人类发现外星人了
Maybe one day humanity discovers aliens，
我们开始星际贸易了
and we start interstellar trade.
那整个 GDP 就空前膨胀了 对吧
Then total GDP would explode, right？
可能从 50万亿直接千到 1000万亿了
Maybe from $50 trillion straight to $10 quadrillion.
对吧 所以我觉得就是这些
So I think all of these things
东西全部都是动态的
are dynamic.
所以其实挣多少钱本质上也是
How much money you make, fundamentally，
其实只是衡量这个
is really just a way of measuring
所有动态东西的一个
all of those changing things，
一个度量衡
a unit of measurement.
你刚才讲的很对
What you said just now was exactly right.
其实就是一个值
It's basically just a number.
这其实除了这个值之外
Other than being a numper，
不代表任何东西
it doesn't represent anything else.
了解了解
Got it, got it.
那如果几十年
Then decades，
甚至几百年以后
or even centuries from now，
这个世界大家只记得
if the world remembers
孙宇晨做成了一件事情
Justin Sun for one thing he accomplished，
您希望是什么
what would you want it to be？
我觉得
Ithink...
我自己也不能说几百年后吧
I can't really speak for centuries from now，
这个因为我前面也没有参照系 对吧
because I didn't have a reference point before, right？
首先我其实觉得我想当一个就是
First, what I really want is to
成为参照系的人
become a reference point for others.
成为参照系是什么意思呢
What do l mean by becoming a reference point？
就是说未来的企业家
I mean that future entrepreneurs，
比如说50年后的一个人类企业家
maybe an entrepreneur 50 years from now，
或者是这样
or someone like that，
会说
might say，
“我想成为一个像孙宇晨这样的人"
"I want to become someone like Justin Sun."
因为他在他这个人生坐标中
Because within their map of life，
具有某种定义的价值 对吧
he has some kind of defining value, right？
“他成了个坐标系了"
He becomes a coordinate on that map.
"我想成为他"
"I want to become like him"
因为我定
because I've defined—
"他定义了我的人生目标"
he has helped define my life goal.
因为每个人出生之前都
Before any of us are born，
超改煮 入 ！
nobody，
都没有任何人
一出生就是一个标杆 对吧
is born already being the benchmark, right？
对对
Right, right.
对吧 就是别人都是用
You always use someone else
你都是用别人当标杆嘛 对吧
as your benchmark, right？
我希望就是
What I hope is，
如果你说
if you ask me，
我是希望我成为别人的标杆
I hope l can become someone else's benchmark.
最后别人说
So eventually someone says，
"我想成为这个孙宇晨"对吧
"| want to become this Justin Sun" right？
"我想成为孙宇晨"
"1 want to become Justin Sun."
然后呢 在我之前的标杆
And before that, my own benchmarks
其实我是有几个偶像
were a few people l admired.
当然我是有几个标杆的
I had several benchmarks myself.
我的标杆就是这个 马斯克
One of them was Elon Musk.
其实我是很早
Iactually started seeing
就把 马斯克 作为一个标杆
Elon Musk as a benchmark very early on.
2012 年的时候我就开始很关注他
I started following him closely in 2012.
2012 年之后为什么关注他呢
Why did I start paying attention to him then？
因为我关注他的时候
Because when I was following him，
我觉得他是 乔布斯 死了之后
I felt that after Steve Jobs died，
最有可能成为美国商业领袖的
he was the person most likely to become
这个商业人物
the next major American business leader.
其实那个时候我就有点看好他
I was already optimistic about him then.
实际上
And actually，
当然那时候 Tesla 那些
Tesla's market cap at the time
其实市值不高的
wasn't that high，
才二三十亿美金
only two or three billion dollars.
你知道吧 不是
You know, it wasn't
不是那种
anything like what it is now.
就是比苹果肯定是差远了
It was nowhere near Apple.
就是这个
And at thattime，
这个 马斯克 也远没有达到
Elon Musk himself was also nowhere near
美国首富的水平
being the richest person in America.
就是那个时候就刚开始
He was just getting started.
但是我就觉得他很有潜力
But I felt he had a lot of potential.
很有潜力
A lot of potential.
所以 马斯克 各种事我是知道很多
Sol know a lot about all the things Elon Musk has done，
因为我很早
because I started following him
就如果是追星的话
very early, almost like being a fan.
我是很早追他
I followed him from very early on.
很早追他
Very early on.
所以他的细节我都知道很多
So l know a lot of the details about him.
所以他的细节我都知道很多 加he detalls about him.
Sol know a lot
所以他的细节我都知道很多
Sol know a egof the detalls about him.
但是我呢 之
And for me，
相当于就把他做一个标杆
1 basically used him as a benchmark，
把他当做一个标杆
as someone to measure myself against.
然后也很有意思
And i's interesting，
就我们今天节目谈到的
because from what wetve talked about today，
其实我就有三个标杆
I actually have three benchmarks：
马斯克 巴菲特 和 特朗普
Elon Musk, Warren Buffett, and Donald Trump.
刚好这三个人
As it happens, those three people
就是我做商人的时候的三个标杆
were my three benchmarks when | was building businesses.
刚好碰巧都是宾大毕业的
And by coincidence, all three went to Penn.
我没有故意就是说是找宾大毕业的
I didn't deliberately go looking for
去当标杆 没有
Penn graduates to use as benchmarks. Not at all.
刚好我就感兴趣
It just happened that the three people
这三个人就都是宾大毕业的 很诡异
I was interested in all went to Penn. It's kind of strange.
都是宾大毕业的 然后呢
They all went to Penn. And then，
这三个人呢
these three people，
我跟你讲
let me tell you，
都代表了不同的一个象限
each represent a different quadrant.
我这三个人也不是乱选的
I didn't choose these three randomly.
确实
There really is a reason.
三个人代表不同的象限什么呢
They represent different quadrants. What do I mean？
马斯克 呢
Elon Musk
代表我的这个行业
represents my industry.
就他都是从事的
The things he works on
就是高精尖以及科技行业
are cutting-edge technology and engineering.
工程师 工程师
He's an engineer—an engineer.
其实讲白了
Put simplya
我们这个时代不就是工程师的时代嘛
isn't our era really the era of engineers？
对吧 工程师 就工程师的时代
Right? Engineers. It's the engineers' era.
就我当然我自己也是
And of course, l'mupart of that too.
那我下面的所有的员工
Most of the people working under me，
主力就是软件工程师 对吧
the core group, are software engineers, right？
都是软件工程师
They're software engineers.
都是做工程的
They all work in engineering.
所以呢我呢
So for me，
在 马斯克 这一块呢
what llearn from Elon Musk
相当于是学习工程
is engineering，
以及怎么样成为一个好的工程师
and how to become a good engineer.
讲白了
Put simply，
怎么样成为一个好的工程师
how to be a good engineer，
以及怎么样好的去做工程
and how to do engineering well.
这个是我看 马斯克 学习的
That's what I learn from Elon Musk.
当然他就在这个路上
He's on that path，
就是他是代表这个象限
and that's the quadrant he represents.
然后 巴菲特 在我
Then Warren Buffett，
这边代表的象限呢
the quadrant he represents for me，
他是代表常青
is longevity.
常青？
Longevity.
常青就是一直火着一直做
Staying around and continuing to do the work.
就是 巴菲特 是最著名的一个
Warren Buffett is probably the most famous example
就是什么
of this idea.
他就讲的是“雪坡理论"
He talks about the snowball theory.
就说你前面
The idea is that what you do early on
就是怎么做都不重要
isn't the most important part，
但是你要这个雪球要滚的
but for the snowball to grow，
这个雪坡要时间足够长
the hill has to be long enough.
优势才能放大
That's how the advantage compounds.
长期主义
Long-term thinking.
所以这个 巴菲特
So Warren Buffett
就讲求一个长期主义
is really about long-termism，
超长待机
staying in the game for a very long time.
而且就是要提前埋伏
And you position yourself early，
然后超长待机
then stay in the game for a long time.
他就是讲究这么一个理论 然后呢
That's basically his philosophy.
而且他的这个象限是代表金融
And the quadrant he represents is finance.
金融
Finance.
然后特朗普
Then there's Trump.
然肩特朗普
这个赛道也是代表
The lane Trump represents
就是我觉得是三个东西
is really three things. in my view.
第一个就是个人 IP
The first is personal brand
影响力对
and influence.
个人IP 运行影响力
Operating a personal brand and influence
商业的一个极致
to the extreme as a business.
这特朗普 应该是
Trump is probably，
对吧 全世界最有名的这么一个品牌
right, one of the most famous brands in the world.
相当于一个姓氏品牌 对吧 然后呢
His surname itself is a brand, right？
而且 特朗普 是可能全世界第一个
And Trump may be the first person in the world，
我觉得把他的姓氏当做一个品牌来
in my view, to deliberately operate his surname
运营的
as a brand.
变成家族资产
It became a family asset
有很多人成功了
and many have succeeded.
就什么 香奈儿
Take Coco Chanel.
不香奈儿 也挺出名的嘛
Chanel is very famous too.
但是他跟 特朗普 不一样
But that's different from Trump.
他们是先运营产品
They built the product first.
香奈儿 是等于一个包 然后呢
Chanel was first associated with a bag，
再把 香奈儿 推出去的
and then the Chanel name spread outward.
没有人是
Nobody really did it
就特朗普 可能是唯一一个
the way Trump did—he may be the only one
是知道人 人再去追产品
where people knew the person first
对吧你其他东西都是
With the others，
我刚才讲的 香奈儿
Iike Chanel，
这些所有的什么Ferrari
or Ferrari，
都是什么
it's the opposite.
姓氏也都是创始人自己
Those surnames are also the founders' names，
但是他是做了一个产品
but they first made a product.
Ferrari 你联想到车
When you hear Ferrari, you think of cars.
香奈儿联想到包
When you hear Chanel, you think of bags.
后来才知道这个
Only later do you learn
创始人是做包或者做车的
that the founder made bags or cars.
特朗普 是第一个就是人直接运营
Trump was one of the first to market the person directly.
特朗普 你第一想到没有产品
When you hear Trump, you don't first think of a product.
想到是他
You think of him
而且第二个呢
The second thing
是代表跨界
is crossing industries.
巴菲特 是最专注
Warren Buffett is extremely focused，
就是做生意的事
basically only on business and investing.
马斯克 已经有点点偏了 对吧
Elon Musk has already branched out a bit, right？
这个介入一些跨界
He's moved into some other areas，
介入一些
and into public affairs too.
特朗普 是跨界做的最好的
Trump is the strongest example of crossing industries.
对吧 特朗普 是多元跨界
Right? Trump has crossed into many different fields.
千万不要以为只跨了政治跟经济
Don't think it's only politics and business.
特朗普 就是娱乐圈、选美
Trump has been in entertainment and beauty pageants，
WWE、综艺对一切
WWE, reality TV-everything.
赌场、WWE、综艺 对吧
Casinos, WWE, reality TV, right？
《学徒》对吧
The Apprentice, right？
就是无数跨界
Countless crossovers.
特朗普呢 其实是一个无数
Trump is really the result of
跨界和运营之后的一个
countless crossovers and years of brand-building，
一个结果
all coming together.
当然就最后爆发出了非常强的
And in the end, that created an extremely powerful
一个核武器一样的能力 对吧
capability, almost like a nuclear weapon, right？
这个其实我也
And for me，
当然每个人只能代表自己 对吧
of course everyone can only represent themselves, right？
我也谈不上我是会怎么运营
I can't say Ill operate exactly the way they do.
但是我呢
but for me，
吸收的这个商业的思想的基本盘
the foundation of my business thinking
我就是从 特朗普
comes from Trump，
马斯克 和 巴菲特三个人身上吸收
Elon Musk, and Warren Buffett.
这个
That's where l absorb a lot from.
所以你可以看我的
So when you look at
这个整体的这个思路
my overall way of thinking，
有一点点这个他们的这个
you can see a little bit of
真的就是他们三个人的影子
There are traces of all three，
结合的这种感觉
combined together.
就从您身上能看到
You can see that in you，
他们三个人的影子
shadows of all three of them.
对吧 这第一个就是影子是什么呢
Right. So what are those influences？
我 巴菲特 其实跟我离得最近
Warren Buffett is actually the closest to me，
因为我们两个都是做金融的 对吧
because both of us are in finance, right？
都是做金融的
We're both in finance.
本业是最像金融的
Our core businesses are the most similar.
但是我的这个个性呢
But my personality，
和以及我做的事又
and the things I do，
有点像马斯克 和 特朗普
are a bit more like Elon Musk and Trump.
所以就是
So.
当然 而且我呢
of course, for me，
其实也是个不轻易下结论的人
I'm also someone who doesn't like
所以我呢
Sol
也不知道其实
don't really know for sure either，
因为你如果只学一门
because if you only study one school，
只学一个老师
or only learn from one teacher，
这个老师经常会
that teacher will often
告诉你什么东西是错的
tell you that other approaches are wrong.
你像比如说我相信
For example, I believe
巴菲特 是相当看不起特朗普的
Warren Buffett probably doesn't think much of
他觉得"你做商人就做商人
He might think， "lf you're a businessman，
你在那别的乱跨界
Why keep crossing into unrelated fields？
你不浪费你自己时间吗
Aren't you wasting your own time？
然后 而且你严重的削弱了
And aren't you seriously weakening
你商业的基本盘”对吧
the foundation of your business？"
“这个你不应该做"
You shouldn't do that.
"你应该老老实实就搞"
You should just focus on
巴菲特
the Warren Buffett approach.
所以你看巴菲特绝对不跨界
So you can see that Warren Buffett basically
而且巴菲特就为了专注
And in order to stay focused，
他就自己就连奥马哈他都不出
he doesn't even leave Omaha.
他觉得我如果我这个
He thinks，“|f1
伯克希尔•哈撒韦我要搬到 New York
move Berkshire Hathaway to New York，
反而是一个干扰
that would actually be a distraction."
因为我就专注
Because he just wants to focus.
我就是投资
"l invest.
我就是看财报
I read financial statements.
我就是专注我自己做的事情
I focus on the workI do."
我要到 New York
If he moved to New York，
肯定那你想我是巴菲特
think about lit-hes Warren Buffett.
我连晚宴每天参加都参加不完
He'd never finish all the dinners he'd be invited to.
对吧 这个
Right？
多少社交的这些东西
There would be endless social obligations.
故意不搬
So he deliberately didn't move.
那你说你都是全世界
You might say， "You're one of the world's
最大的金融公司了
biggest financial companies.
你不去 New York 吗
How can you not be in New York？
这个你必须去 New York 吧“我不去”
You have to move to New York." But he says， "No.
我就在奥马哈
I'm staying in Omaha."
就他每个人有自己的选择
Everyone makes their own choices.
有自己的选择 对吧
Their own choices.
但是我呢是一个 卜
But for me，
但是我呢是一
But for me
我觉得我不敢轻易下结论谁是对的
I don't dare conclude too quickly who is right.
就跟学武功一样 对吧
I's like learning martial ants, right？
这个什么青城派
You have the Qingcheng School，
这个五岳派
the Five Great Mountains schools，
这个桃花岛
Peach Blossom Island.
你说谁对谁错呢
Who's right and who's wrong？
都是练武功
They're all practicing martial arts.
你不知道哪边那个武功练通了
You don't know which school's method，
他一下就是武林霸主了
will make someone the strongest in the martial world.
其实 对吧
That's really how it is, right？
所以我就是选了三家练
Sol chose three schools to learn from.
选了三家练 对吧
Three schools, right？
我就练这个 马斯克
I study Elon Musk，
这个 巴菲特
Warren Buffett，
特朗普
and Donald Trump.
就是 马斯克 的工程师
Elon Musk for engineering，
这个巴菲特 的金融
Warren Buffett for finance，
以及这个长赛道
and for playing tne /ong gime
再加 特朗普 的跨界个人IP
plus Trump's cross-industry approach and personal brand.
但是我觉得他们也是互相通的
But l think they're interconnected too.
你看 马斯克
Look at Elon Musk.
我相信也有很多借鉴的特朗普
I'm sure he's borrowed a lot from Trump too，
因为他也是一个个人 IP
because he's also become a very strong
我觉得很强的运营者了 对吧
personal-brand operator, right？
以及跨界
And he crosses industries.
你看 马斯克
Look at Elon Musk：
现在产业也很多了
he's in many industries now.
又做电动车
Electric vehicles，
又做 AI 对吧
Al, right？
然后又做 X
And X.
他自己买了个社交平台 对吧
He bought a social platform himself, right？
对对对
Right, right.
这个谈不上是对是错
It's hard to say whether any of this is right or wrong.
有可能有的人觉得他收购 x是对
Some people think buying X was the right move.
有的人觉得收购是错 对吧
Others think it was a mistake, right？
就是
That's the thing.
这个有人觉得他去 特朗普
Some people think his involvement with Trump，
这个帮 特朗普 竞选是对
helping Trump's campaign, was right.
有的人觉得是错
Others think it was wrong.
就都很难说
I's very hard to say.
实话实说 对吧
That's the truth, right？
但是我呢
But for me，
我们就是只能看
all we can do is watch，
然后学 对吧
and learn, right？
我刚好我有个好处
One advantage I have is
我是学他们
that I'm learning from them.
所以他们往前走
So as they move forward，
这个我就是
Ican
有标杆
use them as benchmarks
在后面学
and learn from behind.
对 我有个标杆
I have a benchmark.
我有个标杆
I have a benchmark to follow.
对 就跟我开船的时候
It's like when you're sailing.
不大家有个北极星嘛 对吧
Everyone has a North Star, right？
有一个北极星 对吧
A North Star.
那你就是看到这个北极星
Once you can see that North Star，
你就可以
you can
冲着这个方向开船
steer the ship in that direction，
你就对了
and you're on course.
否则你在这个大洋里面
Otherwise, out in the middle of the ocean，
你都不知道该怎么开了
you don't even know where to steer.
对吧 这是我前面有
So earlier in my life，
至少有几个北极星 但是呢
I had at least several North Stars. But now，
我自己呢
for myself，
就是也是根据这个学习
as I learn from them，
我自己也会建立
I'm also building
我自己的方法论
my own methodology.
所以我的这个孙学
That's why my Sunology
这个不是乱搞的 对吧
isn't something ljust made up, right？
我就是也是我自己在自己的路上
It's something I've built along my own path.
我也
Ialso
吸收他们的
absorb things from them，
但我也建立我自己的方法论
while building my own methodology.
然后当然我自己这个方法论未来
And of course, in the future, my methodology may also
也会成为中国乃至世界别的创业者
other entrepreneurs in China and around the world，
或者别的人家从商的人
or other people in business，
对吧 未来就说
can look at and say，
“我的这个IP
“My personal brand，
我这标杆
my benchmark，
我是学孙宇晨的”对吧
is Justin Sun." right？
当然 我也有些中国的痕迹
Of course, l also have some Chinese influences.
就我中国的我就主要是学马云
In China, the person I mainly learned from was Jack Ma.
对吧就是我们湖畔大学
Right? Through Hupan University.
我原来在湖畔大学读书 对吧
I studied at Hupan University before, right？
这个也有这个痕迹在
So that influence is in there too.
但是我觉得就是 我的这个怎么说呢
But l think, how should I put it，
这个
this...
这个其实这个思路也
this way of thinking
跟我前面这个思路很像
is similar to what | said earlier.
就我觉得也不要过于
I don't think you should
早的把自己的武功
lock in your own martial-arts style
以及把自己的这个思维定型
or your way of thinking too early.
就说我就是一个偶像
You shouldn't say， "This is the one person l idolize."
对吧 一个门派
One school, one style, right？
我就是练一个武功
"This is the one martial art I practice."
我觉得不一定
I don't think it has to be that way.
我觉得成武学
D think the true masters of martial arts，
成大学 大者
the people who reach the highest level，
都是触类旁通
all learn by analogy across different schools.
就是 这个金庸的那个
In Jin Yong's
小说里面那个武功最高的
novels, the strongest martial artists
最后都是好几门的武功加起来
usually combine techniques from several schools.
就是那个
That's the idea.
你单独练一门就不行
If you only practice one style, it doesn't work as well.
这个是我自己
That's just my own
当然是一个主观思维
subjective view, of course.
也不一定准确
It may not be right.
但是就是 我是练多门
But I personally study several schools，
练多门武功
several kinds of martial arts.
是而且他们之间也会有很多交集嘛
And there are lots of overlaps between them.
他很多行为都是互通的
A lot of their behaviors and principles carry across.
对对对 但是我觉得呢
Right. But I also think
不要轻易下判断说那个人就不靠谱
you shouldn't quickly decide that someone is unreliable.
就是比如说 巴菲特
For example, Buffett
可能最早就下结论说“特朗普这种
might have decided early on that someone like Trump
不靠谱 商业也做不好
wasn't credible and couldn't do business well，
跨界也做不好
couldn't succeed by crossing industries，
最后都坏"
and that it would all end badly.
那特朗普没有
Burt Trump didn't.
人家特朗普做在选总统
When Trump ran for president，
这个事上就爆发了
that's where his approach really broke through.
对不对
Right？
是
Exactly.
所以不要轻易地下结论
So don't rush to conclusions.
是是是
Right, right.
你不要轻易地下结论
Don't rush to conclude
说这个路线就不靠谱
that one path is unreliable，
或者这个思路就不靠谱
or that one way of thinking doesn't work.
我觉得这个是
I think that's
我觉得也是
also something important：
就是不要轻易下结论
don't rush to conclusions.
其实各门各派这个武功各有所长
Every school of martial arts has its strengths.
不要轻易地说“就我这个武功
Don't be too quick to say
就比别人的好多少"
that your style is much better than everyone else's.
其实不一定
It may not be.
是是
Right.
其实而且这个其实我们
And I think this connects to
前面讲的这个自我问题
what we said earlier about ego.
我觉得也是很对
Ithink that's very true too.
就是越成功就越有自我
The more successful you become，
越有自我就越难吸收别人的武功
the harder it is to absorb other people's skills.
对吧 就比如说巴菲特
Take Buffett, for example.
他也是自成一派
He has his own fully formed school.
所以他就瞧不上 马斯克
So he doesn't think much of Elon Musk.
瞧不上特朗普
Trump
他要瞧得上他早收购马斯克了
If he did, he would have bought into Elon Musk long ago.
对不对
Right？
我也给他提了这个主意 对吧
leven suggested that idea to him, right？
包括 特朗普 And Trump一
那就更瞧不上了
he probably thinks even less of Trump.
他觉得特朗普都不入流 对吧
He may see Trump as outside the mainstream, right？
但是人家
But still，
你看
look at them.
也在各自领域当然是
In their own fields，
有人家自己的东西 对吧
each of them clearly has something unique, right？
当然这个那个 马斯克 就瞧不上
And of course Elon Musk doesn't think much of
巴菲特
Buffett either.
当然这个马斯克瞧不上巴菲特
I think Musk looking down on Buffett
我觉得是一个应激反应
is partly a defensive reaction，
因为巴菲特瞧不上他
because Buffett didn't respect him，
所以他也鄙视
so he pushes back too.
你知道他是一个攻击 反击型的
He's the type who responds when attacked.
因为他 比尔盖茨和这个
Bill Gates and
那个巴菲特就老钱看不上他 Buffett—the old-money establishment一
那个巴菲特就老钱看不上他
didn't really accept him，
所以他就好像很反老钱
so he became very anti-establishment in return.
所以他们
So the people
我现在学的这几门武功的人呢
behind these different schools I'm studying
互相师傅互相之间还
actually don't think very highly
互相之间看不上
of one another.
对他们有点陷在这种
They're kind of at the stage
就是大神打架的这个阶段
where the masters are fighting each other.
但您就是去吸收他们所有好的东西
But you absorb the best things from all of them，
然后进行一个整合和自己的理解
then integrate them with your own understanding.
你说太对了 我相反
Exactly. In fact，
因为我在局中
because I'm in the arena myself，
他们的这个原来发展
I've watched how each of them developed
我都看在眼里
with my own eyes.
所以我觉得他们每个人
Sol think every one of them
都有自己的独到之处
has something uniquely valuable.
所以在我呢
For me，
我觉得不要有这个自我
I think you should let go of ego
不要有这个门派之见
and avoid sectarian thinking.
更要就是说
Instead，
他们三个的我都吸收
I absorb things from all three of them，
然后呢 触类旁通
then connect the lessons across fields.
对因为强如他们三个人
Right. Because even people as strong as those three
那他们也有致命缺点
still have major weaknesses.
他们都没有
None of them
他们没有接受薄肌
has embraced lean muscle.
他们这个很致命的缺点
That's a serious weakness they share.
每个人都有对
Everyone has weaknesses.
还有共性 对吧
And they even share this one, right？
是是
Exactly.
共性就是没有薄肌
The common weakness is no lean muscle.
没有薄肌
No lean muscle.
对吧 这个
Right？
所以我觉得真是这个道理
Sol really think that's the point.
所以就是触类旁通 多吸收
Learn across fields and absorb more.
我觉得比较重要
I think that's very important.
不要过早定型
Don't lock yourself in too early.
不要过早定型我觉得
Don't define yourself too early.
而且不要先入为主
And don't go in with preconceived conclusions.
我觉得很多东西先入为主
With many things, people start with a preconceived view.
你一进去你就判断“这错 对"
The moment they enter, they decide what's right or wrong，
一下就下结论
and immediately reach a conclusion.
很容易就是错的
That conclusion can very easily be wrong.
对好的
Right. Okay.
我想问一个问题
I want to ask you something.
就是 你知道就是
You know，
现在当今社会嘛
in society today，
很多人就是这种大众想法就是说
a very common way of thinking is that
都想就是 想尽快做到财富自由
people want to achieve financial freedom
然后就对
and then
躺平什么都不干了
just I'e flat and do nothing，
就可以不用上班了
so they never have to work again.
但是我听你播客说到
Burt I heard you say on a podcast
就是当然这是不成立的
that this idea doesn't really hold up.
因为如果你真玩的话
If all you do is play，
你会玩吐的
you'll eventually get sick of it.
你会玩不进去
You won't even be able to enjoy it anymore.
它不符合我们人类的这个
It doesn't match
这个基因这个需求
what human beings are wired to need.
那我想问就是说
So my question is，
那比如说
for example，
那这个时候他们比如说
for most people at that point，
大部分他就没有蓝图了
they don't have a blueprint anymore.
他比如说他的终局是财富自由
Their end goal was financial freedom，
然后什么都不干
and then doing nothing.
那假设说一部分人做到了
If some of them actually reach that point，
那你给他们的建议就是
what advice would you give them？
这个地图他继续怎么去开呢
How should they keep opening up the map from there？
你讲的太对了
That's a great question.
我跟你讲
Let me tell you，
这个都是我自己一个头疼的点
this is actually something I've struggled with myself.
我跟讲 所有人
Everyone，
都是缺啥补啥
ends to want whatever they're missing.
是什么呢
What do l mean？
上班的人就不想上班
People who work a job don't want to work.
像我这个没上班的人呢
Someone like me, who doesn't have ajob，
特别想上班
really wants to go work for someone.
你知道我特别想上班
I genuinely want ajob.
为什么呢
Why？
我就处于这个迷茫期
Because I'm in this period of uncertainty.
我告诉你
I'm telling you，
我现在孙宇晨我要做什么
lask myself， "What should Justin Sun do now？"
我特别想做
And I really want to
谁要是能让我入职 OpenAI
join OpenAI，
入职 Anthropic
orjoin Anthropic.
我愿意为了这个工作机会
I'd be willing to pay
免费给 5000 万美金 行吧
$50 million just for the opportunity to work there.
我就是想去 OpenAI 和 Claude 上班
ljust want to work at OpenAl or Anthropic.
他们不用给我钱
They wouldn't have to pay me.
一分工资不用给我
Not a single dollar of salary.
我绝对完成指标 好吧
I'd absolutely hit my targets, okay？
我给这公司 5000 万
I'd give the company $50 million，
但是你前提条件是 你就让我上班
but the condition is that you let me work there.
但是他们两个家肯定都不愿意
Of course, neither company would want that.
怕我孙宇晨进来偷吃
They'd be afraid | was joining to learn their secrets.
怕去偷他们信息
They'd worry I'd get access to confidential information.
对偷他们的信息
They'd definitely be concerned.
明天 B.AI就做大了
tomorrow B.Al might become huge，
所以不给你入职
so they wouldn't hire you.
所以我还头疼呢
That's why it's frustrating for me.
我还想去上班呢
I still want to go work somewhere.
我为什么想去上班呢
Why do I want ajob？
其实有一个很简单的一个原因
There's actually a very simple reason.
就是因为我自己
It's because I personally
没有怎么上过班
have barely ever worked for someone else.
我就一开始就创业的
I started out as an entrepreneur.
但是呢就构成了我的 个小缺陷
But that created a small blind spot for me.
—个小缺陷 但是呢就构成了我的
But that created a small blind spot for me：
但是呢 就构成了我的一个小缺陷
就是我不是特别了解
I don't fully understand
别的公司是怎么运营的
how other companies operate.
至少我没有一手信息 对吧
At least | don't have firsthand information, right？
我当然可以通过面试别的
Of course, I can get information by interviewing
公司的员工什么的去获取嘛
employees from other companies，
网上的总有信息
and there's always information online.
我可以获取
I can get that.
但是我没有第一视角的信息
But l don't have a first-person perspective.
因为我确实没有上过班
Because I've genuinely never really had a job.
对吧 然后呢
Right? And so，
我其实是老板视角
I mostly have the owner's perspective.
我能在下面下面往上看
I can look from the top down，
上面往下面看
from above to below，
但我没有从下面往上看的视角
but l don't have the view from below looking up.
所以呢 我是很难知道
So it's hard for me to know.
就我其实想去的别的公司上班
That's why l actually want to work at another company.
因为从别的公司上班
Ifl worked somewhere else，
我一下
I'd immediately be like， "Wow，
"你们公司怎么管的"
so this is how you manage your company."
"对对对对对"
Right, exactly.
又可以学到东西的
you could learn things that way.
学到非常多东西
1 could learn a tremendous amount.
所以就是我觉得从这个角度来说呢
So from that perspective，
对吧 有的人可能就是
some people may already have
从下到往上的视角很多了
a lot of bottom-up experience，
因为他经常打工
because they've spent years as employees.
但他因为没有当过老板
But because they/ ve never been the boss，
或者他没有财富自由
or haven't reached financial freedom，
或者什么
or something like that，
他缺乏从上往下的视角
they lack the top-down perspective.
但是呢 我觉得呢
But I think
其实都是个缺啥补啥
we all want to fill in whatever we're missing.
你在我看来
From my perspective，
就是说每个人都说
everyone gets tired
我自己的这个视角
of their own viewpoint.
那看得都吐了 对吧
They ve seen it until they're sick of it, right？
但是说
But then they say，
"别人的视角我想去"
"I want to see someone else's perspective.
"我想去看"
I want to experience it."
这个
That's
所以呢就是说
the point.
我其实还是回到刚才那个体验说
Sol come back to what | said about experience.
其实我觉得所有的
Ithink all of these ideas，
刚才讲财富自由也好
whether it's financial freedom
这个思路也好
or any of the other frameworks we discussed，
都是个神话
are myths.
其实都是一个神话
They're all myths，
都是要被打破的
and they all need to be broken.
或者一种迷思 对吧
Or you could call them misconceptions, right？
中文翻译叫迷思
A kind of myth or misconception.
是什么呢
What do l mean？
就说你以为你缺这个东西
You think you're missing something.
你以为你想要那个东西
You think you want something else.
但是等你到达那个彼岸
But once you reach the other side，
等你到达那个
once you actually get there，
你会发觉
you realize，
"我又缺回来了"
"Wait, now I'm missing something again."
其实 它是个循环
It's a cycle.
是一个循环
A cycle.
就是这个
That's really it.
我创业之后
After I became an entrepreneur，
我最缺的其实是上班
was the experience of being an employee.
因为我觉得上班
Because I think working for someone，
尤其去好的公司止班
especially at a great company，
尤其去好的公司上班
能给我提供很多
could give me a lot of
标杆能给我提供很多
benchmarks and reference points.
就像我开船的时候
Like when I'm sailing，
我就知道怎么开
I'd know roughly how to steer，
大概一个情况
and what things should look like.
这个东西可能这个肌肉记忆
That kind of muscle memory
只有我在那公司上了班
may only come from actually working at that company.
我才能体现
Only then could I really feel it
体验出来
and experience it firsthand.
但是如果我没上班的时候
But if l were working ajob
我光在那个公司上班
and had never been an entrepreneur，
我可能觉得“好枯燥"
I might think， "This is so boring.
"好没意思〞对吧
This is so meaningless, right？
“好没意思"对吧
"被人管着好不爽"
It feels awful being managed by someone."
对不对 是不是这概念
Right? That's the idea.
就是我觉得就是
Sol think
其实是个互补
it's really about complementing what you lack.
但我后来觉得
Later Icame to feel
我觉得人生其实是个互补
that life itself is about these complementary experiences.
所以我有时候还喜欢玩游戏
That's also why I sometimes like playing games.
我电脑游戏
With computer games，
我专门喜欢玩
lespecially like
现在就是"什么什么模拟器"
simulator games.
我特别喜欢玩
I really enjoy them，
主要是体验别人的人生
mainly because I get to experience someone else's life.
对对 这个你别说
Exacdy. And honestly
真的这个模拟器挺有意思什么呢
simulators are really interesting. Here's why.
就你不真玩
if you don't actually play one.
你是进入不到那个视角的
you can't enter that perspective.
你玩一下就进入那个视角了
But once you play it, you enter that viewpoint，
一下很多东西就想通了
and suddenly a lot of things make sense.
你要不玩 不玩那个模拟器
If you don't play that simulator，
虽然那个模拟器已经比这个人生
even though the simulator is already
我觉得只剩可能砍了本来
maybe it cuts
百分百的体验都已经砍得只剩20了 a 100% real-life experience down to only 20%一
但是这个20分的体验
even that 20% experience
对我来说都挺关键的
is very important to me.
因为它给我提供了一个全新视角
Because it gives me a completely new perspective.
就是这个是我其实觉得挺有意思
I think that's really interesting.
一p
我甚至玩过那种“流浪汉模拟器"
I've even played homeless-person simulators，
就是在每个不同城市之间流浪汉
where you wander through different cities，
对吧 然后去白撸一点钱
trying to scrape together a little money
勉强活着这种
just to stay alive.
"打工 流浪汉模拟器〞我都玩过
I've played working-and-homeless simulators too.
就我经常玩这模拟器
I play these kinds of simulator games a lot.
就是模拟器给我的感觉
What they give me
就是提供个不同视角
is a different perspective.
我觉得就是这个其实 就有点是说
I think it's really about this idea：
你自己不珍惜的东西
something you don't value yourself
可能在别人眼中很宝贵
may be incredibly precious to someone else.
其实是就是一个这个
That's really
人生的这么一个
one of those lessons
体验
from experiencing life.
所以您的意思就是说
So what you're saying is，
那人生您是偏向这个体验论的
you lean toward seeing life through the lens of experience.
那基于体验论的情况下
And from that perspective，
当你达到了财富自由之后
once someone has reached financial freedom，
它其实可能只是一个
that may actually be just one
只是一个门票
a ticket
让你能玩这个游戏了
that lets you start playing the game
然后接下来的任务就是说
Then the next task is
去不同扩大视角和体验
to keep expanding your perspective and experiences
然后去实现这个体验论
and actually live out that experience theory
获得最大体验
to gain as much experience as possible
对 但是而且但不同的人
Right. And different people
有不同的体验模式
have different ways of experiencing life
好吧 我有一个朋友
I have a friend, for example
也是上太空的
who also went to space
叫王纯
his name is Wang Chun
也是其实是个中国人
he's Chinese as well
他就是体验
His whole thing is experience
他就是要全是
He wants to experience everything
他也跟我做 Crypto 的
He's also in Crypto like me
但他不像我就是做商业了IP
but unlike me, he doesn't build a public business persona
他相反很低调他就是
He's actually very low-key
出钱让别人把他名字删掉这种概念
He'll even pay to have his name removed from things
他就不走这个路线
He doesn't follow my route
但他也跟我一样
But like me
碰巧我们俩太空探索
he happens to share
的这个路我们俩通的
an interest in space exploration
所以我们俩还挺熟的
so we know each other fairly well
因为我们俩都探索太空
because we' ve both explored space
还碰巧都是华人
and we're both Chinese
探索太空
Space exploration
然后他的体验
As for his experiences
他就要走
he wants to
周游全世界
travel around the entire world
他这个周游全世界是
And when Isay the whole world
字面意义上周游全世界
I mean literally the whole world
他就是全世界的每个国家他都要去
He wants to visit every country
就是说这个东西
That's his thing
每一趟火车他都要坐
He wants to ride every train route
它（人生的意义）没有正确答案
There is no one "correct answer"
就是他给自己设置的
He sets his own
这个体验和视角
experiences and perspectives to pursue
对对对
Right, exactly
我相信他的这个体验视角
Iimagine his experiences
也会很有意思
and perspective must be fascinating too
他去过太多地方我没去过了
He's been to many places I've never visited
他去过挪威
He's been to Norway
他去过南极
he's been to Antarctica
他做那种南极的那种徒步
he does Antarctic trekking
哇塞 就是你知道
Wow,you know
就是完全是可能我
that's a perspective I personally
没有体验过这一个视角
have never experienced
就是
Exactly
但他就去做他这个视角的事 是吧
Burt he goes and lives out that perspective, right？
但他和我是生活有些交集
Our lives overlap in some ways
因为他做 Crypto
because he works in Crypto
他也去太空
and he's gone to space
这是我们俩就是人生的交集部分
Those are the parts of life we share
但他有太多和我是不交集的部分
that don't overlap with mine at all
了解那因为您是
I see. Because for you
您的追求是这个商业嘛 对吧
your pursuit is business, right？
在商业版图去突破它的极限
You keep pushing the limits of your business footprint
那比如说一个人他
But suppose someone
不是商业版图的
isn't focused on building a business empire
他比如说就是挣钱
Maybe they just earn money
存了笔钱
save some of it
然后投资
investit
然后实现了财富自由
and reach financial freedom
那这个时候他接下来做的
At that point, what they do next
他就不一定再拿钱去做标杆
doesn't have to use money as the benchmark anymore
去追求商业的扩大
or keep expanding a business
而是他就可以给
Instead,they can
自己设置一些支线任务
set side quests for themselves
支线任务
Side quests
就比如说周游世界
Like traveling around the world
比如说探索太空
exploring space
比如说坐每一趟火车
riding every train route
或者就是换一个游戏
or switching to a different kind of game entirely
或者去跑马拉松
or running a marathon
当然这个不提倡
though we don't recommend that one
或者说给自己设一个标准去练薄肌
or setting a goal to build lean muscle
就是它是一个
So basically
就随便你怎么玩
you define the game yourself and play however you want
都没有正确答案
There is no one correct answer
对你讲的非常对
Exactly, you said it very well
本来就是没有正确答案的
There was never one correct answer to begin with
就千万
And most importantly
就是 其实所有成为正确答案的人
people who later become the "correct answer"
他在他成为正确答案之前
didn't know they were the correct answer beforehand
他不知道自己是正确的
They had no idea
我给你举几个例子
Let me give you a few examples
你一下就明白了
and you'll immediately see what | mean
就比如说爱因斯坦
Take Einstein
没有说前面发誓"我要成为
He didn't swear from the beginning that he would become
世界上最伟大的物理学家"
the greatest physicist in the world
爱因斯坦你知道他以前是一个
Einstein used to work as
瑞士的一个就是专利注册员
a patent examiner in Switzerland
职业是给人注册专利的
His job was reviewing patent applications
当然这个
Of course
你说这个注册专利员跟
you could ask whether patent examination
这个物理有没有一点相通
has anything to do with physics
可能也是有点相通
maybe there is some overlap
然后他对物理特别感兴趣
And he was deeply interested in physics
然后
Then
当然他后来专利注册员当上之后
after working as a patent examiner
他发现了光速不变定律
about the constancy of the speed of light
他发现了这些相对论之后
and relativity
他就去大学当教授了
then he went to a university as a professor
但是他一开始是专利员出身
But he started out as a patent examiner
就是每个人呢
So everyone
都在成为正确答案之前
before becoming the "correct answer"
其实没有发誓过自己
didn't begin by swearing
要成为正确答案 对吧
that they would become it, right？
像特朗普
Take Trump
对吧 那特朗普那就更是了
Trump is an even clearer example
特朗普一开始就是说
He started with
商业弄一弄的时候呢
business, and then
搞搞综艺
did reality television
然后呢
Then
就是自己的爱好嘛
that was just part of his personal interests
选美 WWE
beauty pageants, WWE
就可能就是一个想喜欢出风头
Maybe he simply liked attention
想高调 想出名的一个人
liked being high-profile and famous
一个动机 对吧
That may have been the motivation, right？
等后来后来 搞着搞着
Then as he kept going
然后又比较关心
he also became increasingly interested in
政治 对吧
politics, right？
搞成美国总统了 对吧
and ended up becoming U.S.president, right？
所以我觉得很多东西
Sol think many things
其实是说“柳暗花明又一村”吧
are about finding another path
很多东西就不是说
It's not that
你是说我好像一定要功利的去
you must always pursue something
去要干成什么事
and know exactly what you'll become
其实很多东西是触类旁通的
A lot of things connect across domains
这个 但是你说你说特朗普
And if you take Trump
难道一定要当了总统
did everything before becoming president
我前面这些事才有意义吗
he eventually became president？
其实也不是 对吧
Of course not, right？
在另外一个时间线
On another timeline
可能特朗普穿到别的地去了
Trump might have gone somewhere completely different
对吧 所以我觉得就是这个
Right? So l think
每个人就是
every person
有自己设立的一个地图
is creating their own map
所以他就是
That's really it
对吧 你包括比如说
And for example
我前两天不是设立这个“孙宇晨奖"
I recently created the Justin Sun Award
我也提到这个诺贝尔的人生 对吧
and also mentioned Nobel's life, right？
诺贝尔前面被骂惨了呀
Nobel was heavily criticized earlier in life
发明了炸药之后
after inventing dynamite
全世界用他这个炸药把
People around the world used his dynamite
炸死多少人 对吧
to kill so many people, right？
那大家都骂诺贝尔
So people attacked Nobel
说诺贝尔黑心把多少人害死了 对吧
and said he was responsible for so many deaths, right？
就直接给诺贝尔起了个名字叫
They even gave him the label
就是“死亡商人”是吧
"merchant of death" right？
"死亡商人"
"Merchant of Death"
多难听 是吧
That's a terrible name, right？
但诺贝尔也没办法
But Nobel couldn't really control it
"你们要用我的炸药炸死人
If people used his dynamite to kill others
这也我也拦不住"
he couldn't physically stop them all
但诺贝尔后来
Then later
临死的时候
when Nobel was nearing death
这都跟诺贝尔没关系了
this had almost nothing to do with his life's main work
说诺贝尔毕生都
He had not spent his life
没有为这个事奋斗过
working toward this outcome
只是诺贝尔临死的时候说
He simply said near the end
“那行吧死的时候遗产设立5个奖
all right, use my estate to create five prizes
要不发给这个
and give them to
这个“
people in these fields
结果后面别人用别人的开始发奖
Then after his death, other people kept awarding them
对吧 现在诺贝尔你说
Right? Today when you hear Nobel
发明炸药谁知道
who remembers the dynamite itself？
也之前炸死人谁知道
Who remembers everyone killed by explosives before？
没人知道
Almost nobody
大家都觉得
People hear "Nobel" and think
诺贝尔一听好学术
academic excellence
对吧 好这个什么
authority
权威对
prestige
好权威的感觉
something very authoritative
好权威 好学术
very scholarly
但其实诺贝尔没有搞过学术
But Nobel himself wasn't an academic scholar
没有权威
he wasn't an academic authority
诺贝尔只是发明炸药而已
He was an inventor of explosives
然后临死的时候说
Then before he died he said
“你们搞这个奖"
set up these prizes
当然他也不知道这个奖
And of course he had no idea
后面会发展 100多年 对吧
they would continue for more than a century, right？
发了无数人
and honor so many people
所以就是我觉得就是怎么说呢
Solthink
就是 其实人生这个际遇是挺奇妙的
life's twists and turns are fascinating
所以我们呢
And sometimes
有时候就我刚才讲的
like ljust said
你刚才讲的东西很对
what you said is very true
就是说很多人就包括大家很多事
A lot of people, with many things
一开始的时候都想追求一个意义
try to find a meaning at the very beginning
或者给一个比较高的意义
or give a higher meaning.
但是其实我后来觉得这个
But actually, I later thought that this
这个很多时候 开始的时候是个意义
This is a lot of times, at the beginning it is a meaning
其实存在的意义不大
it doesn't really have much meaning.
就追求意义其实没什么意义
Pursuing meaning doesn't really matter.
对 体验本身可能就是意义
The experience itself may be the meaning.
对吧 就是这个
Right？
先上路 是吧
But sometimes you should just get on the road first
先上路比为什么
Getting started
想清楚为什么上路还要重要
fully understanding why you're starting
先上路吧
Get on the road first
先上路 对吧
Start moving, right？
你说很多东西就是
A lot of things
一开始去追求这个意义
may not need a fully defined meaning at the beginning
可能是没有意义的
That search itself may not help
你在上路的时候
Once you're moving
可能机缘巧合
chance and circumstance
就碰到那
may bring you somewhere unexpected
对吧 我觉得就是不要先入为主
Right? That's why I think avoiding preconceptions
我觉得挺重要的其实
is very important
这个就尤其是
Especially
你看我们刚才讲的
when you look at what we just discussed
你看每个人的这个
every person s
人生就是有点误打误撞
life contains a lot of accidental turns
就是他后来成名的这个东西
What they later become famous for
跟他想的这个没有任何关系
may have nothing to do with what they originally imagined
我再给你举个例子
Let me give you another example
你知道古时候有个皇帝叫李煜
There was an emperor in ancient China named Li Yu
李煜
Li Yu
南唐的一个皇帝
an emperor of Southern Tang
然后呢
And then
这个李煜呢
Li Yu
就是单纯亡国了
simply lost his kingdom
老婆被人抢走了
and his wife was taken away
老婆被宋朝的皇帝抢走了 很悲痛
The Song emperor took his wife, and he was devastated
然后李煜就自己就写了很多词和诗
So Li Yu wrote many poems and ci lyrics
你知道吧
You know？
然后李煜
And Li Yu
李煜是单纯
really was just
没有任何炒作的想法
not trying to generate publicity at all
李煜是单纯很悲痛
He was genuinely heartbroken
老婆被人抢走了很悲痛
His wife had been taken and he was devastated
李煜就写了几首词
So he wrote a few ci poems
表达自己的悲痛之情
to express his grief
结果呢
And then
这几首词就
those works
火了 是吧
became famous, right？
什么"问君能有几多愁”是吧
"How much sorrow can one man have？" right？
"恰似一江春水向东流"
"Like a river of spring water flowing east"
这是他写的 对吧
That's his line, right？
这就是他很悲痛
It came from deep pain
但就这悲痛的词
But those painful poems
大家说“打到痛点了"
resonated deeply with people
"确实悲痛"
They were genuinely heartbreaking
"我们都懂"
Everyone understood that feeling
然后李煜一下就成了
And Li Yu suddenly became
中国就是最有名的词人 对吧
one of the most famous lyric poets in China, right？
这个
And
词大家
those poems
你说当皇帝没怎么当
He wasn't much of an emperor
但这个词一下子成全世界出名了
but his poetry became famous everywhere
对吧
So,right？
成了中国这个宋词
He became a major figure in Song-style ci poetry
唐诗宋词
Tang poetry and Song ci
他成宋词的代表人物了 对吧
he became one of the representative figures of ci, right？
这个那个宋朝的皇帝把他老婆抢了
The Song emperor took his wife
对吧 但没想到自己的这个发明的
but ironically
这个宋词反而被李煜统治了
being dominated in memory by Li Yu
李煜其实
Li Yu
对吧 你说他接受前面
Right? Of course, before that
接受这个宋词的教育
he had been educated in the Iiterary tradition
也是一些文化教育而已
and had cultural training
然后他后天的这个
Then later
人生给他这个东西
his life experience
经历给他这个词增添了一些魅力
added emotional force to his writing
碰巧一下成了
And by coincidence he became
全中国最有名的词人
one of the most famous lyric poets in Chinese history
所以就是所有东西就是
Sol think everything
我觉得都是一个随机混沌
contains some randomness and chaos
绝对是占一定比重的
It definitely plays a role
你说李煜是文盲行不行
Could Li Yu have been illiterate? No
那肯定不行
Of course not
你文盲你不会写词也不行
If you can't write, you can't produce great poetry
对吧 但你说“我就要成为
Right? But if you simply declare
世界上最牛的词人"
"I will become the greatest poet in the world"
你在那狂写词
and just keep writing frantically
不行
that won't necessarily work
因为那个文学很多是体验的结果
because literature is often the product of experience
体验经历加上文学功底
Experience and life events plus
共同训练的结果
literary skill training together
所以就是这个
So
所有东西它是个随机碰撞
all of it is a kind of random collision
它lt
它此t
并不是说所有东西
isn't that everything
怎么说就是一开始想好的
was planned from the very beginning
对吧 就是这个
Right？
所以我觉得这个角度吧
That's howllook at it
因为我是可能北大学历史的嘛
Maybe because | studied history at Peking University
所以我从这个角度来思考
I tend to think this way
就这个人生可能更大
Life to a large extent
Life, to a large extent
都密^公告可熊黑太
程度上是一个混沌
may be a chaoticsystem
但是我觉得就您的
But looking at your own path
这个道路来说的话
iactually seems
还是其实还是蛮按照您设计的走的
fairly close to something you designed
就比如说您模仿那个
For example you modeled yourself after
三个顶级男人嘛
three top figures
那其实你走的路也是
and your path really has
蛮往那个方向走的
moved in those directions
就您这个结果不是很混沌的
So your result doesn't look that random
更像是一个战略和执行
It looks more Iike strategy plus execution
但是你讲是因为你现在看我
only because we're looking at it now
这还不是终极体
and this still isn't the final form
对你可能100年后
Right. Maybe 100 years from now
一个年轻人只知道孙宇晨
a young person will only know Justin Sun
因为孙宇晨奖
because Justin Sun Award
比如说我获得这个数学
for example, honors people in mathematics
我表彰很多人
and recognizes many people
我随便讲 对吧
I'm just giving an example, right？
就跟诺贝尔一样
Just like Nobel
其实前面的事都没人在乎了
people may stop caring about
你 100年后的人看我一下
A person 100 years from now might look at me
对吧 你此时此刻你看诺贝尔说
the way you now look at Nobel
"你炸药发明的很有名
and say， "You invented dynamite"
你炸药大家
But if you asked Nobel himself
化学家"
the chemist
诺贝尔说“没有没有没有"
he might say， "No, no, no
我都不知道我自己要干嘛
I didn't even know what | was ultimately doing"
这个其实是这个炸药发明了之后
After dynamite was invented
我很负疚 对吧
he actually felt guilty, right？
都死了这么多人"
because so many people died
所以就是每个每时每刻
So at every moment
那个角度看的不一定一样
the perspective can look different
对吧 当然你说的很对
Right? But what you said is true
你说每个人有没有一个北极星呢
Does everyone have some kind of North Star？
绝对是有
Absolutely
以及这个北极星有没有
And does that North Star
给他的人生带来一些
introduce certain variables
变量 绝对是有
into their life? Absolutely
比如说我自己设立
For example, when I created
孙宇晨奖的那个时候我就讲了
the Justin Sun Award, I said
诺贝尔
Nobel
诺贝尔奖的设置跟诺贝尔
the design of the Nobel Prize has a lot to do with Nobel
本人的口味有很大关系
his own preferences
诺贝尔因为他是个炸药学家
Nobel was an explosives scientist
他是个化学家所以呢
a chemist, so
诺贝尔奖没有数学家
there is no Nobel Prize in mathematics
因为诺贝尔呢
because Nobel
不相信单纯的
didn't believe in rewarding
除了发明之外的东西
pure theory disconnected from invention
所以诺贝尔只奖物理
So the Nobel Prize emphasizes physics
只奖化学
and chemistry
因为他觉得物理化学是做实验直接
physics and chemistry involve direct experiments
就是能够导致现实生活发生变化的
that visibly change real life
你说你数学纯研究理论
If you're doing pure mathematical theory
那诺贝尔奖说觉得
Nobel's standard would say
你拿不了诺贝尔奖
you don't get a Nobel Prize
“因为我们不奖励纯理论
because pure theory isn't what we're rewarding
必须和现实生活结合
It has to connect to real life
体验改变生活"
and change how people live
体验改变生活〞
这个跟他生产炸药是非常 对吧
That lines up closely with making explosives, right？
他可能生产炸药是人类
Explosives may be one of the most extreme ways humans
最极端的一种改变自然以及
physically change nature
改变这个东西的一个方式嘛
and change the world around them
对吧 都炸药了 对吧
Right? They're explosives, after all
对吧 但是他就是
So
那诺贝尔奖带有深刻的诺贝尔色彩
the Nobel Prizes carry a strong Nobel flavor
因为他不奖励理论
because he didn't reward pure theory
他不奖励理论
And because he didn't
所以你说 每件事触类旁通
you can see how his life experience
跟他之前的人生经历有没有关系
shaped the structure of the prize
绝对是有关系
Absolutely
就跟你说李煜的这个词 对吧
Just like Li Yu's poetry, right？
跟他是皇帝
Did the fact that he was an emperor
亡国了有没有关系
who lost his kingdom matter？
绝对有关系
Absolutely
但是呢又和他可能没有完全的关系
the later result can become something separate
你说这个词和他这个完全不一样了
The poems became something beyond
诺贝尔和诺贝尔奖
Nobel and the Nobel Prize
完全两个不同东西
also became two very different things
所以他是一个共扼 对吧
They're linked, right？
这个中文叫共扼
Interconnected
他是个共鸣共生的这么一个关系
almost a symbiotic relationship
其实
Really
但是呢 就是有一点我是很坚信
But there is one thing I firmly believe that
就是你人生的体验
is your life experience.
只要在正确的方向上
as long as you are on the right track，
没有任何体验是作废的
no experience is wasted.
怎么定义“正确的方向"
How to define the right direction？
怎么定必“正确的方向"
我觉得就是 怎么说呢
how should I put it
就是你自己
you yourself
像我现在不是有个正确方向
like me now, you should still have some broad direction
像这三个人吧
These three people, for example
大概其实也是个大概的方向
give me roughly a broad direction
大概的方向
A broad direction
我觉得你只要尽
I think as long as
只要这个大概方向是对的
the broad direction is roughly right
你尽情去体验
you can experience freely within it
好 就是定一个有意义的目标
Set a meaningful goal
就是尽量有意义的目标
or at least a goal that seems meaningful
对然后你就顺着这条路就是去做
Right, then follow that road and act
你也不用太去纠结说
You don't have to constantly worry
"我是不是一定在正确的道路〞对吧
whether every step is definitely on the one correct path，
那这个意义一定是要
Does that meaning have to be
那这个意必一定是要
基于给世界创造价值吗
based on creating value for the world？
还是说 比如说
Or could something like
我环球旅行就纯增加体验也可以
purely for experience also count？
我觉得这个不一定
I don't think it has to be one thing
不需要 不一定需要给世界创造价值
It doesn't necessarily have to create value for the world
因为价值其实很主观
because value is subjective
价值其实很主观
Value is subjective
你就像我刚才讲的这个
Like I said earlier
其实每个人都去
everyone tries
试图去定义它的意义
to define meaning
其实最后你会发现这个
but in the end you often find
本身不是什么定义
it's not an objective definition
只是你的口味而已
it's mostly your preference
就比如说连诺贝尔
Even Nobel
对吧 我前面讲的
like I said earlier
他都试图给价值
tried to define value
做一个很明确的定义
very explicitly
他就说“你必须给人类做贡献"
He said you must contribute to humanity
他的做贡献都必须精确到
and his idea of contribution was very concrete
就是“你必须改变这个世界"
you must physically change the world
对吧 你
Right？
比如说你这个改变
For example, if you create change
而且理论不算改变世界
pure theory doesn't count as changing the world
比如说你说“我数学解出了一个题"
If you solve a math problem
诺贝尔说"你对世界没有任何影响"
Nobel's framework would say，
因为你只解出来一个题 对吧
because you only solved a problem, right？
你并没有这个
You didn't
你比如说 我诺贝尔不一样
do what Nobel did
我发明炸药
l invented dynamite
这个山是50米
this mountain was 50 meters high
我明天炸了只剩 25米了
tomorrow I blast it down to 25 meters
这绝对改变世界了吧 对吧
That definitely changed the world, right？
“就是你如果没做到我这个水平
I you haven't done something at that level
你就不算改变世界"
then by his standard it doesn't count as changing the world
他就是有一个这样定义
That's one definition
但是可能也是错的 对吧
But maybe that definition was wrong, right？
数学后来证明
Mathematics later proved
其实改变世界的威力一点不比
it can change the world just as powerfully
你这个诺贝尔奖的炸药差呀 对不对
as Nobel's explosives, right？
就是说
Exactly
更何况人家数学还不屑于在
And mathematics may not even care
你这个参照系跟你对比的 对吧
about comparing itself within that framework, right？
谁说我这个数学就
Who says mathematics
一定要转化成炸药才算数学
has to become explosives before it counts？
对不对 我数学不想跟你比
Right? Math doesn't need to compete on that basis
就是 但就以诺贝尔自己的标准
But even by Nobel's own standard
可能数学最后都超过了
mathematics may ultimately have exceeded it
因为数学也改变世界了 对吧
because mathematics also changed the world, right？
你像比如说我经常讲
For example, l often say
我们这个加密货币其就是
cryptocurrency itself is
数学加密算法的一个产物
a product of mathematical cryptography
这个
So
所以从这个角度来讲呢
from that perspective
我觉得确实不要去特别
I don't think we should try too hard
深刻的好像试图定义意义
to define meaning in some extremely rigid way
其实我们很多对意义的定义
A lot of our definitions of meaning
其实本身可能就是错的
may themselves be wrong
所以我个人觉得就是
So personally I think
只要在一个大的方向上是
as long as your broad direction
你是有意义的 对吧
is meaningful, right？
我觉得就是可以放心去尝试
then you can confidently experiment
其实
Really
就是大的方向
it's about the broad direction
我相信每个人也有自己的方向
I believe everyone has their own direction
比如说我自己的方向就是说
For me, for example
对吧 我就
我对 AI感兴趣
am interested in AI
我对 Al Crypto 对吧
Al and Crypto, right？
这些东西感兴趣
I'm interested in these things
我就做这个东西 对吧
solwork on them, right？
就是这个
That'sit
但每个人可能有自己不同的想法嘛
Other people may have different interests
对吧 就只要这个大面上
As long as at the big-picture level
我觉得没什么问题
there isn't a serious problem
你就可以尽情去尝试
you can freely experiment
其实这个方向什么错了什么
Whether one specific direction was wrong or not
其实 后来你再回来 回头看
when you look back later
这个
well
没什么
maybe a lot of things
可能很多东西都是无用功
turn out to have been wasted effort
试图去定义这个
Even trying to define
也有可能是无用功
which efforts were useful may itself be wasted effort
了解对
Got it
但是这个定方向不能
But the direction can't simply be
定成就是单纯地偷懒
pure laziness
或者说单纯地每天就消费享受
or pure daily consumption and enjoyment
啥也不干
doing nothing
就这样定肯定不行
That definitely doesn't work
我觉得
Ithink
没有什么意义
there's no meaning in that
对你说的太对了
Exactly
人类也分两种活动
Human activity can also be divided into two types
一种创造活动
creative activity
一种消费活动 对吧
and consumption, right？
这个我觉得大面上是创造活动
At a high level, 1 think you should emphasize creation
创造活动 对吧
Creative activity, right？
单纯的消费没有意义 对吧
Pure consumption by itself has little meaning, right？
你说
Take
比如说我们的这个
our earlier example
再讲李煜 对吧
Li Yuagain,right？
李煜最后能体现出价值
Why did he ultimately create value？
他不也是创造了
Because he created something
写了一首词至少
he wrote at least one great poem
对对
Right
对吧 你说亡国的昏君呐
Right? Fallen emperors
这太多了 对不对
there are plenty of those, right？
每个朝代都有 对不对
Every dynasty has them, right？
那但你亡国单纯亡国是消费
If you only lose your kingdom, that's just consumption
你转化为词是创造 对吧
but turning the experience into poetry is creation, right？
是这么一个理论吧 对吧
That's roughly the theory, right？
那就是这个大致的蓝图
So the broad blueprint is
就是说多创造少消费
create more, consume less
然后你做什么基本上都是对的
and then almost anything you do can be worthwhile
对 其就就是的
Right, that's basically it
定好一个方向 把大方向 对吧
Set a direction, a broad direction, right？
大方向
A broad direction
我觉得就是
I think that's basically
其实就是这个概念
the idea
了解了解
Got it got t
而且很多东西很有意思
And a lot of things are really interesting
我跟你讲
Let me tell you
就我看足球嘛
I watch football
你包括那个很多东西都有意义
and a lot of things have meaning
就比如说那个哈兰德的
Take Haaland, for example
爸爸哈兰德也是个球员
Haaland's father was also a footballer
你知道吧
You know？
但是也就踢得一般
He was only an average player
但是就因为他
But because of him
结果生了个儿子
he had a son
然后就创造了这个
and then created
很伟大的
something extraordinary
而且他
And
对他儿子踢球
his son played football
然后他呢
and he
辅导他儿子踢球
coached his son
当然他不知道他儿子
But he didn't know his son
会变成世界巨星 对吧
would become a global superstar, right？
他只是自己踢球
He simply played football himself
喜欢踢球
and loved football
他的人生过就这个意义就是踢球
Football was a major part of his life's meaning
然后他自己结了婚
Then he got married
生了儿子之后
and had a son
他说我也辅导你
and said, Ill coach you too
你去踢球
Go play football
然后他就
And then
他是在一直在这个方向上 对吧
he just kept moving in that direction, right？
但你说也没有说太出彩
He himself may not have been spectacular
但是你说
but then
他到他儿子的时候就出彩了因为
it became spectacular through his son
但你说哈兰德是不是打上
And is Haaland deeply
深刻的这个老哈兰德的烙印
marked by the influence of his father？
那是绝对的
Absolutely
因为他爸不踢球
If his father hadn't played football
他怎么可能有他的儿子
how would his son have existed in that environment？
以及他怎么可能走上
And how would he have ended up
这条踢球这个路线呢
on this football path？
这都是不可能的
It wouldn't have happened that way
所以基本上就是
So basically
所以我就是为什么
that's why I think
我觉得很多体验都有意义
sO many experiences have meaning
就你不一定
You don't even
甚至不一定得要追求
necessarily need that meaning
但你身上有这个意义 对吧
to materialize through you personally, right？
你的后人很有可能就是
Your descendants may very well
因为你的这个选择就
have their lives completely changed
就完全改变了他的人生 对吧
because of a choice you made, right？
而且他爸确实创造了嘛
And his father really did create something
生了个儿子嘛
He created a son
他不是消费行为
That isn't consumption
他是创造行为
that'screation
所以得是创造行为
So it has to involve creation
他创造
He created
他一是创造儿子
first, he created a son
第二他辅导他儿子踢球
second, he coached his son in football
对创造了
Right, he created something
他这种教育也是创造
That kind of education is also creation
对教育也是创造
Right, education is part of the path too
对你说太对了
Exactly
对吧 然后他就
Right? And then
一下子就
suddenly
他儿子就起来了 对吧
his son took off, right？
你最后连他那个姓氏
Even the surname
其实用的他爸的呀
came from his father
你现在觉得哈兰德好牛
Now everyone thinks Haaland is incredible
其实那哈兰德那个名字是他爸的
but the name Haaland was already his father's name
只不过叫哈兰德
It's the family name
这现在这个哈兰德踢起来了
Now this Haaland became the star
但名字都是用的他爸的 对吧
but he's still carrying his father's name, right？
对也是留名了
Right, so the father is remembered too
绝对留名了
Absolutely remembered
这个姓氏是他爸的
The surname is his father's
这讲白了
That's the point
所以就是说
So
当你有这个条件去
when you're in a position
比如说不需要去为了
where you no longer have to
生存而出卖自己的时间
sell your time just to survive
达到一种自由选择的时候
and you have freedom of choice
你就应该去多创造少消费
you should create more and consume less
对对 某种程度上是这样
Yes, to some extent
那这个比例
Then what about the ratio？
那消费和创造的比例怎么去
How do you balance consumption and creation？
因为你不可能完全不消费
Because you can't completely stop consuming
对 我觉得是创造为主吧
I think creation should be the main thing
其实你看我们那个《财富自由之路》
If you look at our discussion of financial
我也讲的是挺明确
freedom, I made this pretty clear too
其实你消费久了也没意思了
If you consume for too long, it gets boring
实话实说
Honestly
对吧 你得回到一些创造
Right? You eventually need to return to creating
但创造太久呢
But if you create for too long
干活太猛也头晕脑胀
and work too hard, you also burn out
你得有一些消费来回回血 对吧
You need some consumption to recharge, right？
它其二者相辅相成
The two complement each other
并不是谁压制谁的这么一个关系
It's not a relationship where one suppresses the other
就是人你不可能追求百分百创造哈
You can't pursue 100% creation
这个就 对
Exactly
太残忍了
That would be too harsh
这个不符合人性
It's not human
对是的是的
Right, exactly
而且也压抑了你的创造性可能
It might even suppress your creativity
你百分百创造了你这 对吧
If you create 100% of the time
你没有充足的消费
without enough consumption
可能压抑你的创造
that can suppress your creativity
对对对
Right, right
不过我觉得现代人
But I think modern people
大部分的问题是创造不够
mostly have the opposite problem: not enough creation
消费太多
and too much consumption
对是的是的
Yes, exacty
哇这个
Wow
我觉得这一期播客非常非常 哇
I really think this episode has been
非常有深度
very, very deep
如果真听进去的话
If people truly take it in
会获得很多认知上的
they can gain a lot of
提升和版本更新
new understanding and upgrade their mental model
对是的是的
Yes, yes
可以不错
Pretty good
我们这个都赶上我觉得
I think this is already up there with
那个 罗根 的那个播客了
a Joe Rogan podcast
哇 我觉得这个质量反而很高
Honestly, the quality is very high
这期质量非常高了
This episode is really strong
对是的是的
Yes, absolutely
也非常非常感谢孙哥
And I'm extremely grateful to you, Justin
愿意拿出这么多宝贵的时间
for giving us so much valuable time
进行这样一个可以帮助到
for an interview that can help
很多现代年轻人的一个
sO many young people today
采访和就是完全掏心窝子的
and for speaking so openly
就真诚的
sO sincerely
真实的最新版本的分享
and sharing the latest version of your thinking
是的是的
N
Yes,yes
没有我这个分享也是看到你的
And my sharing also came from seeing your
这个《薄肌圣经》以及很多那个
Lean-Muscle Bible and other things
我觉得那个理论讲得很好
I thought the theory was very good
而且很接地气
and very grounded
就也是更新了我的版本
It updated my own thinking too
所以我也才能说这么多
which is why I can say so much now
你知道吧
You know？
是一个互相
It's mutual
因为我自己也获得这个体验了
because l gained that experience myself
是是是
Exactly
我才能说这么多
That's why I can share so much
因为你最近获得了新信息
You've recently gotten new information
获得了一些新的学习
and learned new things
然后这个时候你
and then when you
分享出来就会很自然
share them, it feels natural
因为你刚学会
because you just learned them
所以你就会很记得
so they're still fresh in your mind
对对对
Exactly, exactly
就这概念
That's the idea
所以我自己也在学
I'm learning too
我自己也在改
and changing too
所以一线我才能分享这么多思路
That's why I can share so many frontline thoughts
对吧 而且我觉得
Right? And I think
这个对我自己很有用
this is very useful for me personally
我觉得对年轻人应该也有用
and it should be useful for young people too
因为我也是个探索嘛 对吧
because I'm exploring as well, right？
对而且说出来其实
Right and saying it out loud
也是巩固自己的认知
also reinforces your own understanding
我觉得我们这个就是播客
I think our podcast
就是打到年轻人痛点
hits young people's real pain points
解决一些大家就是当务之急
and addresses things they urgently care about
对对
Right, right
而且呢 我们是既能接地气
And we can both stay grounded
又能拔上去
and zoom out to a higher level
确实
Exactly
它这个范围很宽
The range is very wide
非常宽
Very wide
对对对 是吧
Right,exactly. right？
之所以能这么宽
And the reason it can be so wide
就是我觉得核心原因就是
is mainly because
因为我们也是真体验了
we've actually lived these things
对才能说出来
Right, that's why we can talk about them
是有 绝对是有经历的
There is real experience behind it
对光装说不出来
Right, you can't fake it and still explain it well
说不出来
You just can't
就跟我的那个
It's like my
是吧
right？
我那个风波的小作文 对吧
my long post about that controversy
我这个一下写了 6000字 对吧
I suddenly wrote around 6,000 Chinese characters, right？
快到1万字了
Nearly 10,000
那都是因为是有生活做一个铺垫
because life had already given me the material
你知道吧
You know？
That's why people say
这叫做“苦难是文学的温床”对吧
suffering is the seedbed of literature, right？
你看没有这个苦难
Without the hardship
没有这个经历 写不了
without the experience, you couldn't write it
写不出这个文章来
You couldn't produce that piece
你知道吧
You know？
是的 是的
Exactly
很多人说 AI 说我是AI写的
A lot of people said Al wrote it for me
肯定有润一下色
Of course Al polished it somewhat
肯定有 AI润一下色吧
Of course Al helped polish it
这个你还是要润
You still want to refine it
对AI帮我修改一下
Right, Al helped me edit it
校对一下
and proofread it
对但是呢
But
这个整体的这个
the overall
思路以及整体的这个
ideas and overall
这个这怎么说呢
how should Iput it
这个感受
feeling behind it
如果没有人的这个输入
without human input
Al 是绝对体验不到的
Al could never truly experience that
这是
That's
对吧 是我刚才讲这思路
right, the point | was making earlier
就是 OpenAI 刚才讲的思路
It's like the OpenAl example we discussed
那肯定前面得有那个
There first has to be
纽约那个数学家输入
that mathematician in New York providing input
如果他不输入那 AI
If he never provides the input
你要它干拔的
you can't expect Al to create it from nothing
肯定干拔 拔不出来
It can'tjust pull it out of thin air
因为语料里面没有嘛
because it isn't in the training data
是吧 你看语料里面没有
Right? If it isn't in the data
你再干想想不出来的
you can't simply think it into existence
有一定输入
There has to be some input
AI这个学会了
Once Al learns it
就是出类旁通
it can generalize from there
我觉得这个
I think this
模式真的非常好
model is really, really good
然后我相信因为
AndI believe
孙哥也在不断进化嘛
Justin keeps evolving too
也在每天吸收新的信息
absorbing new information every day
时不时肯定会有一些新的见解
and from time to time there will definitely be new insights
新的看法
new perspectives
新的补丁
new patches
那我这边也就是
So on my side
真诚地邀请一下孙哥
I'd sincerely like to invite you, Justin
可能过一段时间
maybe after some time
我们可能时不时地
from time to time
可以给大家更新一下
we can give everyone another update
补充一些
and add more
比如说这些视频发出去
For example, after these videos go out
大家可能还有一些
people may still have
觉得没有讲清楚的点
points they feel weren't fully explained
或者好奇的点
or things they're curious about
或者说孙哥愿意分享的点
or things you'd like to share
那我就真诚地邀请一下
So l'd sincerely invite you
可能过一段时间我们可以再
to come back after some time
再做一期这样的事情
and do another episode like this
然后也帮助到年轻人提升认知
to help young people upgrade their thinking
然后 对打补丁
and add more patches
好好的好的 没问题
Sure, sure, no problem
好的好的
Absolutely
非常非常感谢
Thank you so much
孙哥这一次接受采访 对
Justin, for doing this interview
占用了您非常多的时间 对
and giving us so much of your time
好
Okay
对对对 然后最后再说一句
And one last thing
其实我很很早的时候
Actually, a long time ago
我一年前
about a year ago
就是各个平台给您发过私信就是说
I messaged you on multiple platforms
对我当时就说能不
At the time l asked whether
我就是我想
I could
就我
就是我发了一封自荐信
sent you a long self-introduction
就是说想加入您的团队
saying | wanted to join your team
因为我感觉您的理理念看法
because I felt your ideas and views
和我对 Crypto 的认知
and my understanding of Crypto
就各方面
in many ways
我觉得是有很多重合的
overlapped a lot
包括您想做个人IP嘛
And you wanted to build a personal brand
那个人IP 其实是需要一些传播
which needs strong communication
和懂内容的人去加持的
and people who understand content
所以我当时给您发过
Sol sent you
那个很长一封私信说想
a very long private message saying
想能够帮到您在内容方面
I hoped | could help you with content
现在也可以给我发一下
You can send it to me now too
好呀好呀
sure, sure
我把那段话我重新润个色
I'll polish that message again
然后发给你看一下
and send it to you on WeChat
不用润色了
No need to polish it
原汁原味截图发我就可以
Just send me a screenshot of the original
好那我就把那个旧的
Okay, then Pll send you
那个私信发给您看一下
that old private message
你可以感受一下
so you can see what it was like
对好好好
Great, great
好的好的
Okay,okay
好的
Okay
对然后那一期
And that earlier episode about
之前不是说
the thing we discussed before
刚刚说到那个关于
the part about
两性方面的那个认知
relationships and gender dynamics
黄毛思维那个
the Yellow-Hair mindset
我那个把链接发给你
Fll send you the link
也发给我
Send it to me too
对你有空可以看一下
Right, take a look when you have time
你看看说的有没有道理
and see whether it makes sense
然后可能会有一些启发
Maybe it will give you some ideas
然后可以探讨
and we can discuss it
对行
Sounds good
好好好
Okay, okay
那这期采访差不多就到这边
Then I think that's about it for the interview
您还有任何要补充的吗
Anything else you'd like to add？
没有了 没有了
No, no
应该是覆盖了所有的话题了
I think we covered everything
对覆盖了
Yes,we covered it
好的好的
Great
那非常非常感谢孙哥
Thank you so much, Justin
然后希望尽快看到
And I hope we can soon see
孙哥的薄肌版 版本答案
your lean-musdle "optimal build"
好 薄肌版本
Yes, the lean-muscle version
好的好的
Okay, okay
应该快了
It should happen soon
认知因为现在已经到位了
The mindset is already in place now
对时间问题
Right, it's just a matter of time
认知到位了就快了
Once the mindset is in place, it comes quickly
好嘞好嘞
All right
感谢孙哥
Thank you, Justin
好的谢谢
Thank you
好的 我们再联系
We'll stay in touch
好拜拜
Bye
谢谢
Thanks